<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Psychol Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PSM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Psychological Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0033-2917</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1469-8978</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4595860</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291715001166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0033291715001166</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00116</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Religious and spiritual interventions in mental health care: a systematicreview and meta-analysis of randomized controlled clinical trials</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">J. P. B. Gon&#x000e7;alves et al.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Religious and spiritual interventions in mental
health care</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>J. P. B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vallada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Psychiatry</addr-line>,
<institution>University of Sao Paulo Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Sao
Paulo</addr-line>, <addr-line>SP</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Federal University of Juiz de Fora</institution>,
<addr-line>Juiz de Fora</addr-line>, <addr-line>Minas Gerais</addr-line>,
<country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Preventive Medicine</addr-line>,
<institution>University of Sao Paulo Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Sao
Paulo</addr-line>, <addr-line>SP</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><addr-line>Address for correspondence: J. P. B.
Gon&#x000e7;alves</addr-line>, <addr-line>Department of Psychiatry (ProSER/LIM23)</addr-line>,
<institution>University of Sao Paulo Medical School</institution>, <addr-line>Street Dr.
Ov&#x000ed;dio Pires de Campos, 785</addr-line>, <addr-line>Zip Code 05403-010</addr-line>,
<addr-line>Sao Paulo</addr-line>, <addr-line>SP</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country>.
(Email: <email>juliane.pbg@usp.br</email>)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>45</volume><issue>14</issue><fpage>2937</fpage><lpage>2949</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Cambridge University Press 2015</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Cambridge University Press</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits
unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S0033291715001166a.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="normal"><sec id="sec_a1"><title>Background.</title><p>Despite the extensive literature assessing associations between
religiosity/spirituality and health, few studies have investigated the clinical
applicability of this evidence. The purpose of this paper was to assess the impact of
religious/spiritual interventions (RSI) through randomized clinical trials (RCTs).</p></sec><sec id="sec_a2" sec-type="methods"><title>Method.</title><p>A systematic review was performed in the following databases: PubMed, Scopus, Web of
Science, PsycINFO, Cochrane Collaboration, Embase and SciELO. Through the use of a
Boolean expression, articles were included if they: (i) investigated mental health
outcomes; (ii) had a design consistent with RCTs. We excluded protocols involving
intercessory prayer or distance healing. The study was conducted in two phases by
reading: (1) title and abstracts; (2) full papers and assessing their methodological
quality. Then, a meta-analysis was carried out.</p></sec><sec id="sec_a3" sec-type="results"><title>Results.</title><p>Through this method, 4751 papers were obtained, of which 23 remained included. The
meta-analysis showed significant effects of RSI on anxiety general symptoms
(<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) and in subgroups: meditation (<italic>p</italic>
&#x0003c; 0.001); psychotherapy (<italic>p</italic> = 0.02); 1 month of follow-up
(<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001); and comparison groups with interventions
(<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). Two significant differences were found in
depressive symptoms: between 1 and 6 months and comparison groups with interventions
(<italic>p</italic> = 0.05). In general, studies have shown that RSI decreased stress,
alcoholism and depression.</p></sec><sec id="sec_a4" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions.</title><p>RCTs on RSI showed additional benefits including reduction of clinical symptoms (mainly
anxiety). The diversity of protocols and outcomes associated with a lack of
standardization of interventions point to the need for further studies evaluating the
use of religiosity/spirituality as a complementary treatment in health care.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words</title><kwd>Clinical care</kwd><kwd>clinical trials</kwd><kwd>meta-analyses</kwd><kwd>religiosity</kwd><kwd>spirituality</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="69"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Despite the interconnection throughout history between religion, spirituality and medical
practice, only in the last decades has the scientific literature demonstrated the important
role of religiosity/spirituality (R/S) in the physical and mental health of patients (Koenig
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>However, defining complex and multifaceted concepts such as spirituality and religiosity is
not easy as there is no universal definition accepted by researchers (Cook, <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Sullivan (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>) defined spirituality as an individual and unique feature that links the self
to the universe and to others, and may or may not include a belief in a god. Puchalski
(<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) describes spirituality as a way to find
meaning and purpose in life by connecting the inside with the sacred. In addition, Koenig
<italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) define
spirituality as &#x02018;distinguished from humanism, values, morals, and mental health, by its
connection to which is sacred, the <italic>transcendent</italic>&#x02019; and that religion
&#x02018;involves beliefs, practices, and rituals related to the <italic>transcendent</italic>,
where the transcendent is God&#x02019;.</p><p>This lack of consensus causes difficulty in comparing the results between studies
(Lucchetti <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Nevertheless, several studies have shown
positive correlations between R/S and the prevention of various diseases with evidence of
improved quality of life and increased survival (Sawatzky <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Chida <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>Different papers have reported a correlation between greater religious attendance and
increased immunity (Bormann &#x00026; Carrico, <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), lower blood pressure and cardiac complications in postoperative patients
(Lucchetti <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Masters &#x00026; Hooker, <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and correlation with remission of cancer (Ando
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Ka'opua <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><p>Regarding mental health, some studies have shown a direct relationship with psychological
well-being, such as satisfaction, happiness and moral values (Bonelli <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Moreira-Almeida <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Koenig <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) in their review reported a 95% positive
correlation with social support, 93.7% with purpose and meaning of life and 79% with
well-being, optimism and hope.</p><p>However, despite numerous positive correlations, there are also reports of negative aspects
of religiosity that are associated with thoughts of guilt, abandonment or punishment, such
as: &#x02018;God is punishing me, does not like me and has abandoned me&#x02019;. When these are present,
outcomes tend to be negative with a greater prevalence of depression, anxiety and mortality
(Pargament <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Stratta <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>Despite the extensive literature assessing correlations or associations between R/S and
mental health, few studies have investigated the clinical applicability of this evidence
through controlled clinical trials. Given this, some authors have proposed strategies to
investigate whether the stimulation of religious/spiritual beliefs could result in better
clinical outcomes (Koszycki <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Ka'opua <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). It is believed that religious/spiritual
interventions (RSI) have a role in changing an individual's thoughts, promoting greater
acceptance of illness and social support and a deeper understanding of existence together
with encouraging belief and faith, that could have an impact on patients&#x02019; outcomes (Djuric
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Rosendahl <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>Despite the growing number of studies, the approaches are still quite distinct and lack
standardization. Some evaluate the increment of spirituality itself after the intervention
(Richards <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), others evaluate quality of life (Moritz
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) and others the physical or mental health
impact on patients (Huguelet <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The difference between the protocols
(frequency and duration) is also considerable, hindering comparisons between techniques.</p><p>Despite the theoretical evidence, at present, we found three meta-analyses comparing
treatment involving R/S in the literature; however, these comprised heterogeneous treatment
settings and selection criteria (McCullough, <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>;
Smith <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Oh &#x00026; Kim, <xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>In order to update and clarify the results found in the literature, the aim of the present
study was to perform a systematic review following PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for
Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses) guidelines, selecting only randomized controlled
trials, focusing on the impact of RSI on mental health outcomes, and to evaluate the
methodological quality of these articles. Considering the heterogeneity of these studies, we
aimed to perform a meta-analysis of studies capable of grouping through populations or
clinical outcomes.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec2"><title>Method</title><p>The present study is a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized clinical trials
involving RSI on mental health and it was conducted from January 2011 to June 2014.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Eligibility criteria</title><p>Randomized clinical trials were eligible if they explored the effects of RSI on mental
health outcomes without restrictions regarding the type of disease or population. RSI were
considered to be &#x02018;messages to health&#x02019; framed by themes of spiritual relevance. This
&#x02018;message&#x02019; could use spiritual or religious themes, such as taking care of the body God has
provided (Anderson &#x00026; Pullen, <xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>),
reflective discussions of moral and ethical values to accept the situation faced
(Breitbart <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), or meditation (Bormann <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>), among others.</p><p>Language was limited to English, Spanish and Portuguese; the date of publication,
however, had no restriction. Due to the importance of an appropriate randomization process
in clinical trials, we assumed as an exclusion criterion a randomization definition used
by the CONSORT (Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials) Group (Schulz <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), which comprises a checklist on how to
report a trial. If the randomization procedure was not specified in articles, the authors
were contacted.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Search strategies</title><p>We screened the literature using seven databases: PubMed, Scopus, Web of Science,
PsycINFO, The Cochrane Collaboration, Embase and SciELO. We decided to work with Boolean
expressions, since these access relevant articles in a single expression (Pohl <italic>et
al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), as follows: &#x02018;(spiritu* OR relig* OR faith
OR holistic OR multifaith) AND (assistance OR intervention OR treatment OR therapy OR
assessment OR group OR meditation) AND (clinical trial OR meta-analysis OR randomized
controlled trial OR controlled clinical trial)&#x02019;. A pilot search was run in June 2011 and
updated in August 2013.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title>Data abstraction</title><sec id="sec2-3-1"><title>Phase 1</title><p>Two reviewers (Camila Casaletti Braghetta and J.P.B.G.) examined the title and abstract
of studies to exclude those not comparing RSI with a control group, reviews, off-topic
or in other languages and repeated versions in different databases.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-3-2"><title>Phase 2</title><p>Each included study went through an extensive review of the intervention and
randomization processes. For articles without complete descriptions of adopted
procedures, the authors were contacted by email for further information. Those who did
not respond or provided insufficient information were excluded.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title>Data items</title><p>Outcomes extracted from each included article were: (1) participants&#x02019; clinical diagnoses;
(2) sample size; (3) intervention protocols (type, frequency, duration and follow-up); (4)
scales and outcome measures; and (5) results of interventions. The outcomes explored in
the meta-analysis were depressive and anxiety symptoms.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>To assess the risk of bias in the studies, we used the intraclass correlation coefficient
which quantifies the percentage of data variability. The score of this coefficient ranges
from 0 to 1.00; the closer to 1.00, the less variability exists between these measures.
For this calculation, SPSS version 17.0 (SPSS Inc., USA) was used.</p><p>Regarding the meta-analysis, the Cochrane RevMan 5.2 program was employed. We chose to
use random-effects models considering the possible heterogeneity in studies (Liberati
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), with a 95% confidence interval for each
measure. In order to explore the variability of the results, we used a standard mean
difference and an assessment of methodological quality in the articles.</p><p>Concerning the outcomes, in studies that used more than one control group, data were
extracted and used as different analysis (e.g. Rosmarin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>.1 &#x02013; control group <italic>versus</italic>
RSI; Rosmarin <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>.2 &#x02013; other intervention or waiting list
<italic>versus</italic> RSI).</p><p>With regards to heterogeneity, the Cochrane Collaboration classifies it into unimportant
(0&#x02013;40%), moderate (30&#x02013;60%), substantial (50&#x02013;90%) and considerable (75&#x02013;100%) (Higgins
&#x00026; Green, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). In the present study,
when heterogeneity was present, we explored possible explanations, by looking at
subgroups, at type of intervention, type of control model and length of follow-up.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title>Risk of bias in individual studies</title><p>Due to the nature of the RSI adopted, studies were not double-blind; therefore, we chose
to evaluate the risk of bias of each study using the Cochrane Back Review Scale which
contains 11 questions about methodology, providing a comprehensive assessment of important
items of clinical trials (Berger &#x00026; Alperson, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Acceptable studies met at least six out of 11 validity criteria (Van Tulder
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). To check the validity of the analysis,
three independent researchers (G.L., H.V., J.P.B.G.) rated the classification.
Disagreements were discussed topic by topic and resolved by consensus.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3-1"><title>Selection of studies</title><p>The survey of databases produced 4751 articles (see flowchart; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>). Phase 1 eliminated 4605 articles for not meeting the
inclusion criteria: 4100 were out of theme and 283 had a different methodology, 155 were
repeated citations and 67 were in other languages, resulting in 146 articles. In phase 2,
57 were excluded for not assessing spiritual interventions, 34 had a different methodology
and 17 did not have adequate randomization. Doubts about randomization appeared in 28
articles. Authors were contacted by email, and despite 15 not responding, 12 studies were
included of the 13 returned. These 12 were added to the 11 included in phase 2; a computed
total of 23 papers. <fig id="fig01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the selected studies following PRISMA (Preferred Reporting Items for
Systematic reviews and Meta-Analyses) guidelines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715001166_fig1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3-2"><title>Characteristics of studies</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table 1</xref> shows the general characteristics of
the selected articles. The papers were published between 2005 and 2013, and 56.5% of these
were from 2009 to 2013. <table-wrap id="tab01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Characteristics of studies</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715001166_tab1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author (year)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participants</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sample size</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scale</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type of intervention</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of sessions/duration of
sessions, min</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Follow-up, months</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Results compared with control
groups</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bay <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac presurgical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HADS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pastoral services</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Q-LES-Q, PSS, STAI, CES-D, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/N/+/+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-traumatic stress disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PTSD, Q-LES-Q, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann &#x00026; Carrico (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HIV+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bowland <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Post-traumatic stress disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">GDS, BAI, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breitbart <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HADS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breitbart <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MQOL, HADS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/N/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Djuric <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer survivors</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight, 7D-PAR, CES-D, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13/?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/N/+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hosseini <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac presurgical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pastoral services</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/45&#x02013;60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huguelet <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schizophrenia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNSS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1+n/?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelly <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug users</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">774</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Form90-D, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koszycki <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAS, PSWQ, BAI, BDI, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+/N/N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lloyd-Williams <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BEDS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">McCauley <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pain, MOOD, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Audiovisual sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/N/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terminal patients</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BDI, STAI, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Therapy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/N/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug users</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Form90-D, BDI, STAI, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Audiovisual sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12/?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/&#x02212;/&#x02212;/N</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moritz <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Emotional stress and depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">POMS, SF-36, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Audiovisual sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSS, MBI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rickhi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depression</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">HAM-D</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Audiovisual sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosmarin <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PSWQ, CES-D, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Audiovisual sources</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wachholtz &#x00026; Pargament (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Healthy</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">STAI, Pain, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/N/+</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wachholtz &#x00026; Pargament (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ID-MS, Pain, STAI, CES-D, MSQFS, S S/R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meditation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30/20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 to 6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+/N/N/N/+</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>HADS, Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale; S R/S, different scales of
religiosity/spirituality; N, no difference between groups; +, positive effect;
HIV+, human immunodeficiency virus-positive; Q-LES-Q, Quality of Life Enjoyment
and Satisfaction Questionnaire; PSS, Perceived Stress Scale; STAI, Spielberger's
State Anxiety Inventory; CES-D, Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression
Scale; PTSD, Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Scale; GDS, Geriatric Depression
Scale; BAI, Beck Anxiety Inventory; MQOL, McGill Quality of Life Questionnaire;
7D-PAR, Seven-Day Physical Activity Recall; HAS, Hamilton Anxiety Scale; PNSS,
Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale; Form90-D, alcohol questionnaire; PSWQ, Penn
State Worry Questionnaire; BDI, Beck Depression Inventory; BEDS, Brief Edinburgh
Depression Scale; MOOD, depressive symptoms; &#x02212;, negative effect; POMS, Profile of
Mood States; SF-36, Medical Outcomes Study 36; MBI, Maslach Burnout Inventory;
HAM-D, Hamilton Depression Scale; ID-MS, ID Migraine Screener; MSQFS, Migraine
Specific Quality of Life Scale.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Populations included sick and healthy people and represented a total sample of 2721
participants. Diagnoses included mental health disorders (26%), cancer (21.8%), chronic
diseases (21.8%), substance use/abuse (8.7%) and cardiac conditions (8.7%), totalling
2521. The healthy population was composed of health professionals and other individuals
(13%), including 200 people.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3"><title>Protocols of interventions</title><p>There were two main lines of approach in the selected papers: spiritual and religious.
Spiritual approaches consisted of themes such as moral values, belief in a &#x02018;high power&#x02019;,
coping and transcendence, and others in the form of therapeutic models, audiovisual
resources and meditation. Religious approaches explored the beliefs and specific
traditions of Catholics, Jews and Muslims, conducted in pastoral services and therapeutic
models.</p><p>Many papers shared similar techniques grouped as follows: psychotherapy (nine studies);
meditation (seven studies); audiovisual resources (five studies); and pastoral services
(two studies), described below:</p><sec id="sec3-3-1"><title>Psychotherapy</title><p>This method was predominant in the selected papers of which three followed a
conventional therapeutic approach (e.g. cognitive&#x02013;behavioural therapy), three an
educational method and one evaluated both.</p><p>Three different types of control groups were found: therapeutic ones, educational
approaches for disease and waiting list. The protocols varied from one to 12 sessions.
Only two were held individually and the rest involved group discussions.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3-2"><title>Meditation</title><p>In the seven papers about spiritual meditation, three associated an educational
approach for the procedures. They compared the groups with traditional meditation,
waiting list and informative videos about the disease concerned.</p><p>The facilitators of procedures were the authors who taught and answered questions about
the exercises. Three requested that meditation be carried out as many times as possible
during the day, while the rest counselled daily or weekly meditation sessions.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3-3"><title>Audiovisual resources</title><p>In these interventions, authors constructed material as booklets, audios or videos for
personal use, followed by questionnaires or discussion groups to debate absorbed ideas.</p><p>Two studies compared the intervention group with an informative group and waiting list,
two only with waiting list and one with informative group.</p><p>Protocols of videos consisted of two with spiritual strategies for coping with the
disease and one with Jewish beliefs. The booklets and audios were created and adapted
mentioning spirituality focused on the disease treated, and also followed by discussion
groups.</p></sec><sec id="sec3-3-4"><title>Pastoral services</title><p>Two studies in the form of chaplaincy were encountered, both in patients with
preoperative cardiac programming. This approach was compared with a standard treatment
approach in hospitals.</p><p>Chaplains followed guidelines for care, consisting of rituals (prayers, anointing,
etc.) and spiritual support tailored to the medical needs of patients, such as
hospitalization, postoperative complications, emotional and spiritual suffering. The
sessions occurred pre- and postoperatively, with four visits in one study and at least
five in the other. The time was not pre-set, but varied according to the needs of the
patients in both studies.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3-4"><title>Outcomes and meta-analysis</title><p>Populations found were composed of patients and healthy individuals (<xref ref-type="table" rid="tab01">Table 1</xref>). The mental health outcomes most assessed
were depressive symptoms (found in 15 papers), anxiety (14 papers), post-trauma stress and
stress levels (five papers), use/abuse of alcohol/drugs (two papers) and social function
(one paper).</p><p>Among the usable results in the meta-analysis, three of depressive symptoms and two of
anxiety were excluded because they did not present sufficient data for statistical tests
(mean, standard deviation and/or standard error).</p><p>There was a statistical difference between the studies related to anxiety
(<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001) favouring RSI, presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>. We found evidence of high heterogeneity among the studies
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;86%). After exploring the analysis, we identified a
study with a low score in the Cochrane Scale; therefore it was treated as an outlier. The
exclusion of these data was reflected in a resultant low heterogeneity
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;45%). <fig id="fig02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of effect sizes for anxiety symptoms. SD, Standard deviation; IV,
inverse variance; CI, confidence interval; df, degrees of freedom.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715001166_fig2"/></fig></p><p>Related to depressive symptoms there was no significant difference
(<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.12), despite the tendency to favour RSI, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>. There was low evidence of heterogeneity
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;26%). <fig id="fig03" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Forest plot of effect sizes for depressive symptoms. SD, Standard deviation; IV,
inverse variance; CI, confidence interval; df, degrees of freedom.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715001166_fig3"/></fig></p><p>In order to further explore the heterogeneity found in the studies related to anxiety
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;45%) and the trend of benefit in depressive symptoms,
we assessed three subgroups defined previously: types of intervention; follow-up; and
types of control groups.</p><p>Related to anxiety, we found significant differences for meditation
(<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001 and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0%) and
psychotherapy (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.02 and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;39%) (online
Supplementary Fig. S1). There were also significant differences in three distinct moments
of follow-up (online Supplementary Fig. S2), but the most impressive was assessments until
1 month post-interventions, without any heterogeneity between the studies
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0%). Regarding the control groups, studies that used
any type of intervention showed a difference for R/S (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001
and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3%), when compared with waiting list groups
(<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.19 and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;73%) (online
Supplementary Fig. S3).</p><p>Related to depressive symptoms, we found no differences between the types of
intervention, although there was a trend with audiovisual resources and therapy (online
Supplementary Fig. S4). We found, however, a difference in studies with follow-up from 1
to 6 months (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05 and <italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;61%) (online
Supplementary Fig. S5) and intervention control groups (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.06 and
<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;51%) (online Supplementary Fig. S6).</p><p>Concerning the results that were not usable in the meta-analyses due to the small numbers
of each and/or outcomes measured, we describe the main results below: <list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(<italic>a</italic>)</label><p>Healthy population: composed of four studies that explored mental health and
satisfaction. One of them explored adolescents and found less anxiety, better humour
and more spiritual experiences (Wachholtz &#x00026; Pargament, <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). The other three studies assessed health professionals
and all showed lower levels of stress, emotional exhaustion, higher job satisfaction
and even better quality of patient care (Oman <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Huguelet <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(<italic>b</italic>)</label><p>Use/abuse of alcohol/drugs: of two studies involving addicts that assessed the
frequency and intensity of consumption, one showed a decrease that lasted after
treatment (Kelly <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), and the other found a decrease in
consumption only after 4 months, but increased rates of depression and anxiety in
patients who received a RSI (Miller <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Both showed an incorporation of
spiritual practices and higher levels of faith.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(<italic>c</italic>)</label><p>Post-trauma stress: two spiritual interventions showed promising results with
significant reductions of post-trauma stress and a trend towards reductions in other
psychological symptoms in men (Bormann <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and women (Bowland <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(<italic>d</italic>)</label><p>Schizophrenia: one study explored this disorder and noted increased social
functioning, adherence to medical treatment and interest of patients in discussing
spirituality with their psychiatrists (Huguelet <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>(<italic>e</italic>)</label><p>Migraine: participants who did a spiritual meditation demonstrated a reduction in
the frequency of migraines and in levels of depressions and anxiety (Wachholtz
&#x00026; Pargament, <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>).</p></list-item></list></p></sec><sec id="sec3-5"><title>Risk of bias in individual studies</title><p>We found an intraclass correlation coefficient of 0.832 (0.752&#x02013;0.893) between examiners,
showing the positive reliability of the assessment of bias risk. <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab02">Table 2</xref> discriminates the items assessed in the 23 final articles. It
was noted that none reached the maximum score of 11 because these studies do not enable
the use of &#x02018;double-blind&#x02019; methods. The highest-scoring study at nine points was by
McCauley <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The
&#x02018;third-party blind&#x02019; method, which means that the examiner that has no idea of the
patient's allocation, was present in four studies. There was uniformity of intensity,
duration, frequency and follow-up (items H and J, respectively) in the protocols used.
<table-wrap id="tab02" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Description of the Cochrane Back Review Scale of methodological quality</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="S0033291715001166_tab2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="left" width="1*" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." width="1*" span="1"/><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Author (year)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">G</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">H</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">I</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">J</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">K</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bay <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bormann &#x00026; Carrico (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bowland <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breitbart <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breitbart <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Djuric <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hosseini <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Huguelet <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelly <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koszycki <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lloyd-Williams <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">McCauley <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miller <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moritz <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oman <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rickhi <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rosmarin <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wachholtz &#x00026; Pargament (<xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wachholtz &#x00026; Pargament (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">?</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>A, Randomization method; B, allocation concealed; C, similar baseline; D, patient
blinded; E, provider blinded; F, assessor blinded; G, co-intervention avoided; H,
acceptable compliance; I, acceptable drop-out; J, timing of outcome assessment
similar; K, intention-to-treat analysis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In order to respond to the need to develop the theme of RSI in terms of its clinical
application and scientific impact, we performed a systematic review and meta-analysis. The
results clearly showed that even RSI with different models, with distinct facilitators and
populations tended to be associated with benefits, comparing results between both pre- and
post-intervention groups, and control groups. The meta-analysis showed a significant
reduction in anxiety levels and a trend towards improvement in depression. Despite the
existence of other systematic reviews and meta-analyses of RSI, to our knowledge this is
first time that such a report covers different scientific databases (a total of seven), and
describes and discusses the methodology used in those selected studies in detail.</p><p>Despite the diversity of samples, the targeted goals converged into three basic groups:
(<italic>a</italic>) evaluation of the impact of R/S on mental health;
(<italic>b</italic>) comparison of the effect of R/S and conventional treatments described
in the literature; and (<italic>c</italic>) verification of the acceptance and satisfaction
of patients and facilitators in deployed research protocols. This is not an exclusive
division because, according to the proposals of each study, some of them overlapped in their
goals.</p><p>In our meta-analysis, statistical differences were found only in anxiety samples, with and
without exploitation of heterogeneity. For depressive symptoms, the heterogeneity proved to
be more suitable but there were no significant differences.</p><p>Previously, three meta-analyses compared conventional treatments with R/S. McCullough
(<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>) conducted a comparison of randomized
studies of conventional therapeutic treatments and religious approaches in patients with
predefined psychological symptoms. Of five studies selected, there was no difference to
religious approach, suggesting that it should be done by patient's choice. Another
meta-analysis conducted by Smith <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) examined 31 articles describing RSI in mental illness, showing a better
clinical effect in patients when therapy included spiritual aspects. They included
quasi-experimental studies and intervention without control group comparison. Nevertheless,
neither review considered the methodological quality of the selected articles. A more recent
study, by Oh &#x00026; Kim (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), followed PRISMA
guidelines and included psychiatric diagnoses in addition to other health problems.
Statistical differences were demonstrated for depression and anxiety in spiritual
complementary treatments, with a sample of high heterogeneity
(<italic>I</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;94% in both cases). Their selection included studies of
intercessory prayer and distance healing, besides clinical trials without randomization.</p><p>All protocols involving RSI had positive or neutral results &#x02013; after comparisons with the
control groups or between pre- and post-intervention in the same group &#x02013; with one exception,
in which patients had negative outcomes when compared with the control group (Miller
<italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). Each of these studies had its
particularities, but, in general, they demonstrated reliability of using R/S as a
complementary treatment (Tuck &#x00026; Thinganjana, <xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Stein <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>Currently, several complementary treatments have been used to treat chronic diseases,
minimizing symptoms and improving quality of life. We can cite psychotherapy, physical
exercises, acupuncture and yoga among others (McCullough, <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Allen <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>; Cramer <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Underwood <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>).</p><p>In our subgroup analysis, we searched for different impacts of RSI by dividing them into
types of intervention, follow-up and types of control groups.</p><p>Regarding the types of intervention, we found evidence of efficacy in meditation and
psychotherapy for anxiety symptoms. Although we found no difference between the types of
intervention for depressive symptoms, the meta-analysis graphics showed a trend towards
better results in audiovisual and therapeutic approaches.</p><p>We found in the literature two meta-analyses on different meditation techniques for both
symptoms. Both studies showed positive effects, with the strongest evidence for anxiety
(Abbott <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Chan &#x00026; Larson, <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). However, none of the authors mentioned religious/spiritual
meditation focus, which makes difficult the comparison with our study. There is little
evidence to understand the role of spiritual meditations on mental health symptoms.</p><p>Hook <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) compiled a
review about religious and spiritual therapies on mental health problems. They argued that
several types of therapies were able to help different psychological problems, such as
therapy based on religiosity can be more effective than other secular therapies and even
some drug treatments. They showed strong evidence for anxiety for different religious
therapies and Christian meditation, and all of them showed benefits between 1 and 3 months
of follow-up, in accordance with our meta-analysis. Although only two types of therapies met
their criteria for efficacy, Hook <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) discussed that this was due to insufficient evidence and not because these
therapies do not work. Recently, Nyer <italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) compiled a review on the role of complementary treatments in
depression, showing that therapies based on R/S and music therapy showed improved outcomes
in patients, but still with little evidence.</p><p>Some studies about self-help interventions on mental health (audiovisuals) have shown
promising results, especially for patients with depression, a population that seems to
benefit most from these interventions (Reins <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Fuhr <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Matcham <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). A recent meta-analysis evaluated, among
other subgroups, the impact of this type of intervention in patients with depression using
different lengths of follow-up, and found statistical difference between 1 and 3 months
post-intervention (Matcham <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In our study, we found statistically
significant differences in interventions for depressive symptoms between 1 and 6 months of
follow-up, although there was no distinction between the types of intervention. Sarris
<italic>et al.</italic> (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) mentioned in their
review that different approaches can and should be used in patients with depression
encouraging changes in lifestyle and this can take a while to adjust.</p><p>Following a methodological direction, we reinforce the importance of assessing the risks of
bias in studies. According to PRISMA, there is a need to investigate this carefully through
scales that examine the research item by item (Liberati <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Regarding clinical trials, they cite the
importance of allocation concealment for the randomization procedure, since its inadequacy
may affect the results. Studies with similar methodologies, but discrepancies in quality,
may have biased results (Liberati <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). This research considered adequate
randomization as an inclusion criterion; among all articles, only three possessed a score
below the cut.</p><p>The Cochrane Scale assesses, among other things, the randomization process and whether the
allocation sequence was performed by an independent person who has no influence on the
eligibility of patients, since these strategies improve the quality of research (Jadad,
<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Liberati <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The success of randomization depends on two
interrelated aspects: generating an appropriate sequence of unpredictable allocation and
concealment of the sequence until assignment occurs (Altman <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The choice of the randomization procedure and
its description in scientific papers therefore impose differences in the structure of the
research.</p><p>There are several ways to prepare randomization allowing options for the more convenient
and less expensive form for development studies. It is noteworthy that if authors have not
described this procedure, it does not necessarily imply that they have not done it. However,
we should remember that adequate description of the randomization procedure is essential in
clinical research.</p><p>Another point to observe is the limitation for the item &#x02018;double-blind&#x02019;, since exploration
in RSI happens with the knowledge and active participation of the patient, which makes it
impossible to &#x02018;blind&#x02019; the patient and the facilitator. Despite the importance of this item
to minimize bias in clinical trials, modified guidelines of CONSORT for non-pharmacological
approaches do not invalidate research without it, but suggest it to be justified in relation
to the limitations of the procedure (Boutron <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). There are several examples of studies that
have this type of restriction, such as research in psychotherapy, where at least applicators
are aware of the procedure performed (Belotto-Silva <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Devereaux <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>).</p><p>A way to minimize difficulties in studies faced with problems with double-blinding is to
use a &#x02018;third-party blind&#x02019;, an assessment that is not aware of patient's allocation, so the
evaluation of patients can be conducted with impartiality. Only 17.9% of studies used
&#x02018;third-party blinding&#x02019;, showing that this strategy still needs to be considered and explored
in future research.</p><p>We also observed that, regardless of the evaluated protocols and studied populations, there
was a general concern about the intensity, duration, frequency and follow-up results of
interventions. In studies of high quality, the authors chose to present protocols that had
similarities between the RSI and control groups, detailing all the deployed processes. Our
meta-analysis of subgroups presented a statistical difference in interventions that used
some procedure for comparison groups <italic>versus</italic> waiting list groups, but it
also can be explained by the high heterogeneity between the studies.</p><p>The analysis of quality has revealed important aspects to be considered when producing
clinical research on RSI. According to the natural difficulties already addressed in this
line of research, other relevant aspects for minimizing biases are important and easily
applicable. Attempts at improving the methodological issues of R/S studies may make a
difference to finding more credible and reliable answers to questions regarding this topic.</p><sec id="sec4-1"><title>Limitations</title><p>This research has some limitations regarding the review and meta-analysis. Concerning the
systematic review: (<italic>a</italic>) the definition of RSI adopted in the survey may
have limited the access to some clinical trials; (<italic>b</italic>) the option of
limiting the languages may have excluded other articles; and (<italic>c</italic>) although
the assessment included seven databases, it is possible that some studies indexed in other
databases have not been included, as well as articles published only in books or
proceedings of congresses.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-2"><title>Future directions for research</title><p>The need for more studies is clear, especially to understand the effects and mechanisms
of action of RSI to health. Despite there being few studies that show clinical worsening
with negative religiosity (Pargament <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>; Stratta <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), one should consider these data to explore
the pathways of R/S that can bring the benefits shown by many other studies. Adherence to
the CONSORT guidelines in respect to clinical trial steps and the consequent production of
quality research may help to reveal the benefits of these interventions. The use of
appropriate randomization protocols, employing a &#x02018;third-party blind&#x02019; method and
considering &#x02018;intent to treat&#x02019; are steps that can be included in these studies that can
make a difference when minimizing biases.</p><p>An interesting point for future research would be to compare RSI employing different
scales that measure spirituality, religiosity and daily spiritual practices among other
measures already validated, in order to identify the possible mechanisms of action of this
proposal.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusion" id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Clinical trials assessing the effects of RSI showed additional benefits compared with
control groups, including reduction of clinical symptoms (especially levels of anxiety). The
diversity of protocols and outcomes associated with the lack of standardization of
interventions points to the need for more studies evaluating the use of spirituality as a
complementary health treatment.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This work was supported by the Associa&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o Mantenedora Jo&#x000e3;o Evangelista, Sao Paulo, Brazil.
We thank Fernanda Gaspar do Amaral for help with the manuscript and Camila Casaletti
Braghetta for help in the selection of studies. H.V. received a CNPQ grant.</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec6"><title>Supplementary material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S0033291715001166sup001"><p>For supplementary material accompanying this paper visit http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0033291715001166.</p><media xlink:href="S0033291715001166sup001.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" orientation="portrait" id="d35e2508" position="anchor"><caption><p>click here to view supplementary material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes id="nts2" notes-type="other"><title>Declaration of Interest</title><p>None.</p></notes><ref-list id="reflist1"><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whear</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bethel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coon</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuyken</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of mindfulness-based stress
reduction and mindfulness based cognitive therapy in vascular disease: a systematic
review and meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Psychosomatic Research</source>
<volume>76</volume>, <fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>351</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24745774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schnyer</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hitt</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manber</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Acupuncture for depression: a randomized
controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Psychiatry</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>1665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1673</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Egger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidoff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elbourne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>The revised CONSORT statement for reporting
randomized trials: explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Annals of
Internal Medicine</source>
<volume>134</volume>, <fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>694</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11304107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pullen</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Physical activity with spiritual intervention
strategies: a cluster randomized trial with older African American
women</article-title>. <source>Research in Gerontological Nursing</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23244565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ando</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akechi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Efficacy of short-term life-review interviews
on the spiritual well-being of terminally ill cancer patients</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Pain and Symptom Management</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1002</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20538183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bay</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beckman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trippi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gunderman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The effect of pastoral care services on
anxiety, depression, hope, religious coping, and religious problem solving styles: a
randomized controlled study</article-title>. <source>Journal of Religion and Health</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19105001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Belotto-Silva</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Malavazzi</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valerio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fossaluza</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borcato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shavitt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Group cognitive&#x02013;behavioral therapy
<italic>versus</italic> selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors for
obsessive&#x02013;compulsive disorder: a practical clinical trial</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Anxiety Disorders</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21907540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alperson</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A general framework for the evaluation of
clinical trial quality</article-title>. <source>Reviews on Recent Clinical Trials</source>
<volume>4</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19463104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonelli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dew</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosmarin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vasegh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Religious and spiritual factors in depression:
integration and review of the research</article-title>. <source>Depression Research and
Treatment</source>
<volume>2012</volume>, <fpage>962860</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22928096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carrico</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Increases in positive reappraisal coping
during a group-based mantram intervention mediate sustained reductions in anger in
HIV-positive persons</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Behavioral
Medicine</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19127438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shively</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Redwine</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gershwin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bone</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belding</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Effects of spiritual mantram repetition on HIV
outcomes: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Behavioral
Medicine</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>359</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>376</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16847590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bormann</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wetherell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golshan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>A spiritually based group intervention for
combat veterans with posttraumatic stress disorder: feasibility study</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Holistic Nursing</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18356284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Extending the CONSORT statement to randomized
trials of nonpharmacologic treatment: explanation and elaboration</article-title>.
<source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18283207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bowland</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edmond</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fallot</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of a spiritually focused
intervention with older trauma survivors</article-title>. <source>Social Work</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breitbart</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poppito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vickers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abbey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cassileth</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Pilot randomized controlled trial of
individual meaning-centered psychotherapy for patients with advanced
cancer</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Oncology</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1309</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22370330</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Breitbart</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pessin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poppito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Meaning centered group psychotherapy for
patients with advanced cancer: a pilot randomized controlled trial</article-title>.
<source>Psycho Oncology</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19274623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Meditation interventions for chronic disease
populations: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Journal of Holistic
Nursing</source>. Published online 02 03 2015. doi:0898010115570363.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steptoe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Religiosity/spirituality and mortality. A
systematic quantitative review</article-title>. <source>Psychotherapy and Psychosomatics</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19142047</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>CCH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Addiction and spirituality</article-title>.
<source>Addiction</source>
<volume>99</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lauche</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dobos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Yoga for depression: a systematic review and
meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Depression and Anxiety</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1083</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Devereaux</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhandari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montori</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manns</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghali</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Double blind, you are the weakest link &#x02013;
goodbye</article-title>! <source>Evidence Based Medicine</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Djuric</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mirasolo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kimbrough</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heilbrun</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Canar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>A pilot trial of spirituality counseling for
weight loss maintenance in African American breast cancer survivors</article-title>.
<source>Journal of the National Medical Association</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>564</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19585923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fuhr</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salisbury</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Silva</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atif</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Ginneken</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effectiveness of peer-delivered interventions
for severe mental illness and depression on clinical and psychosocial outcomes: a
systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Social Psychiatry and
Psychiatric Epidemiology</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>1691</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24632847</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). Cochrane handbook for systematic reviews of interventions
version 5.1.0. The Cochrane Collaboration [updated March 2011]. <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane-handbook.org">http://www.cochrane-handbook.org</uri>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worthington</surname><given-names>EL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jennings</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hook</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Empirically supported religious and spiritual
therapies</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>46</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19904806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salehi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fallahi Khoshknab</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rokofian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The effect of a preoperative
religious/spiritual intervention on anxiety in Shia Muslim patients undergoing coronary
artery bypass graft surgery: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Holistic Nursing</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23942577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huguelet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>B&#x000e9;trisey</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Borras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gillieron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marie</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A randomized trial of spiritual assessment of
outpatients with schizophrenia: patients&#x02019; and clinicians&#x02019; experience</article-title>.
<source>Psychiatric Services</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jadad</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Randomised controlled trials: a user's
guide</article-title>. <source>Health Technology Assessment</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>214</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ka'opua</surname><given-names>LSI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Testing the feasibility of a culturally
tailored breast cancer screening intervention with Native Hawaiian women in rural
churches</article-title>. <source>Health and Social Work</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21446609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stout</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Magilli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tonigan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Spirituality in recovery: the lagged
mediational analysis of Alcoholics Anonymous&#x02019; main theoretical mechanism of behavior
change</article-title>. <source>Alcoholism, Clinical and Experimental Research</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>454</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>King</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carson</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name> (editors) (<year>2012</year>). <chapter-title>Definitions</chapter-title> In
<source>Handbook of Religion and Health</source>, pp. <fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38.</lpage>
<publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>: <publisher-loc>New
York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koszycki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bilodeau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raab-Mayo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradwejn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>A multifaith spiritually based intervention
<italic>versus</italic> supportive therapy for generalized anxiety disorder: a pilot
randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>509</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24114846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Koszycki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raab</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aldosary</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradwejn</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A multifaith spiritually based intervention
for generalized anxiety disorder: a pilot randomized trial</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Clinical Psychology</source>
<volume>66</volume>, <fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>441</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20143382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mulrow</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotzsche</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The PRISMA statement for reporting systematic
reviews and meta-analyses of studies that evaluate health care interventions:
explanation and elaboration</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lloyd-Williams</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shiels</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A pilot randomised controlled trial to reduce
suffering and emotional distress in patients with advanced cancer</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Affective Disorders</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>145</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23219061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>ALG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avezum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Religiosity, spirituality and cardiovascular
diseases</article-title>. <source>Revista Brasileira de Cardiologia</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>ALG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallada</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Measuring spirituality and religiosity in
clinical research: a systematic review of instruments available in the Portuguese
language</article-title>. <source>Sao Paulo Medical Journal</source>
<volume>131</volume>, <fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23657514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Masters</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hooker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Religiousness/spirituality cardiovascular
disease and cancer: cultural integration for health research and
intervention</article-title>. <source>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>206</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23148874</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matcham</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hutton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hotopf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Self-help interventions for symptoms of
depression, anxiety and psychological distress in patients with physical illnesses: a
systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Clinical Psychology Review</source>
<volume>34</volume>, <fpage>141</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508685</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haaz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tarpley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A randomized controlled trial to assess
effectiveness of a spiritually-based intervention to help chronically ill
adults</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Psychiatry in Medicine</source>
<volume>41</volume>, <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21495524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Research on religion-accommodative counseling:
review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Journal of Counseling Psychology</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chibnall</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Videen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duckro</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Supportive&#x02013;affective group experience for
persons with life-threatening illness: reducing spiritual, psychological, and
death-related distress in dying patients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Palliative
Medicine</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>343</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15890044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forcehimes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Leary</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanoue</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Spiritual direction in addiction treatment:
two clinical trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>434</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>442</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18657945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moreira-Almeida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucchetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Clinical implications of spirituality to
mental health: review of evidence and practical guidelines</article-title>.
<source>Brazilian Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24839090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rickhi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vintila</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sawa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soriano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toews</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A home study-based spirituality education
program decreases emotional distress and increases quality of life &#x02013; a randomized,
controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Alternative Therapies in Health and Medicine</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>26</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17131979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doorley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durham</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mischoulon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>What is the role of alternative treatments in
late-life depression?</article-title>
<source>Psychiatric Clinics of North America</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>577</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>596</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24229658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Meta-analysis of spiritual intervention
studies on biological, psychological, and spiritual outcomes</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Korean Academy of Nursing</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>842</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23364038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thoresen</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Passage meditation reduces perceived stress in
health professionals: a randomized, controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Journal of
Consulting and Clinical Psychology</source>
<volume>74</volume>, <fpage>714</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>719</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16881779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hedberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thoresen</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Passage meditation improves caregiving
self-efficacy among health professionals: a randomized trial and qualitative
assessment</article-title>. <source>Journal of Health Psychology</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>1119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1135</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18987085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pargament</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tarakeshwar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Religious struggle as a predictor of mortality
among medically ill elderly patients</article-title>. <source>Archives of Internal
Medicine</source>
<volume>161</volume>, <fpage>1881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1885</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11493130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zobel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moffat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). Extended Boolean retrieval for systematic biomedical reviews.
In <italic>Proceedings of the Thirty-Third Australasian Conference on Computer Science</italic>
<bold>102</bold>, 117&#x02013;126.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Puchalski</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Spirituality in the cancer
trajectory</article-title>. <source>Annals of Oncology</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22628416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Reins</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lehr</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riper</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cuijpers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berking</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Internet-based treatment of major depression
for patients on a waiting list for inpatient psychotherapy: protocol for a multi-centre
randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>318</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24279841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berrett</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardman</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eggett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Comparative efficacy of spirituality,
cognitive, and emotional support groups for treating eating disorder
inpatients</article-title>. <source>Journal of Eating Disorder</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rickhi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reesal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paccagnan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urbanska</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>A spirituality teaching program for
depression: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>International Journal
of Psychiatry in Medicine</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22439299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rosendahl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tigges-Limmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gummert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dziewas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albes</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Bypass surgery with psychological and
spiritual support (the By.pass study): study design and research
methods</article-title>. <source>American Heart Journal</source>
<volume>158</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19540386</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rosmarin</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pargament</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pirutinsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A randomized controlled evaluation of a
spiritually integrated treatment for subclinical anxiety in the Jewish community,
delivered via the Internet</article-title>. <source>Journal of Anxiety Disorder</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>799</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sarris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neil</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schweitzer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Lifestyle medicine for
depression</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24721040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sawatzky</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A meta-analysis of the relationship between
spirituality and quality of life</article-title>. <source>Social Indicators Research</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>CONSORT 2010 statement: updated guidelines for
reporting parallel group randomized trials</article-title>. <source>PLoS Medicine</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <elocation-id/>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bartz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Outcomes of religious and spiritual
adaptations to psychotherapy: a meta-analytic review</article-title>.
<source>Psychotherapy Research</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>655</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kolidas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moadel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Do the spiritual patients want spiritual
interventions?: a qualitative exploration of underserved cancer patients&#x02019; perspectives
on religion and spirituality</article-title>. <source>Supportive Palliative Care</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stratta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capanna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riccardi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carmassi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piccinni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dell'Osso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Suicidal intention and negative spiritual
coping one year after the earthquake of L'Aquila (Italy)</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Affective Disorders</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>1227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1231</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22100127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>It helps me to be the whole person: the role
of spirituality among the mentally challenged</article-title>. <source>Psychosocial
Rehabilitation Journal</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuck</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thinganjana</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>An exploration of the meaning of spirituality
voiced by persons living with HIV disease and healthy adults</article-title>.
<source>Issues in Mental Health Nursing</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>166</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17365165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Underwood</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lamb</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slowther</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Exercise for depression in elderly residents
of care homes: a cluster-randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>382</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23643112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Tulder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furlan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bombardier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bouter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>The editorial board of the Cochrane
Collaboration Back Review Group. Updated method guidelines for systematic reviews in the
Cochrane Collaboration Back Review Group</article-title>. <source>Spine</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>1290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12811274</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wachholtz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pargament</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Is spirituality a critical ingredient of
meditation? Comparing the effects of spiritual meditation, secular meditation, and
relaxation on spiritual, psychological, cardiac, and pain outcomes</article-title>.
<source>Journal of Behavioral Medicine</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16049627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wachholtz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pargament</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Migraines and meditation: does spirituality
matter?</article-title>
<source>Journal of Behavioral Medicine</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>366</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18551362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>