<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-1078</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5809815</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2018.00033</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychology</subject><subj-group><subject>General Commentary</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Commentary: Why Your Body Can Jog Your Mind</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>Francesca</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/180830/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/32367/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/14824/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>Simona</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/459829/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Biotechnological and Applied Clinical Sciences, Neurological Institute, University of L'Aquila</institution>, <addr-line>L'Aquila</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Post-Coma Rehabilitative Care Unit, San Raffaele Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Cassino</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Meryem Yilmaz Soylu, University of Nebraska-Lincoln, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Consuelo Borras, Universitat de Val&#x000e8;ncia, Spain; Takeshi Nishijima, Tokyo Metropolitan University, Japan; Glenna Batson, Winston-Salem State University, United States; Jos&#x000e9; Jes&#x000fa;s G&#x000e1;zquez, University of Almer&#x000ed;a, Spain; Hong Ni, Children's Hospital of Suzhou University, China</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Francesca Pistoia <email xlink:type="simple">francesca.pistoia@univaq.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Educational Psychology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Psychology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>33</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Pistoia, Sar&#x000e0;, Carolei and Sacco.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pistoia, Sar&#x000e0;, Carolei and Sacco</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e149" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="28337170" ext-link-type="pubmed" journal-id="Front Psychol" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" vol="8" page="362">A commentary on <article-title>Why Your Body Can Jog Your Mind</article-title> by Macedonia, M., and Repetto, C. (2017). Front. Psychol. 8:362. doi: <object-id>10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00362</object-id></related-article><kwd-group><kwd>physical exercise</kwd><kwd>embodied cognition</kwd><kwd>embodiment</kwd><kwd>rehabilitation</kwd><kwd>locked-in syndrome</kwd><kwd>vegetative state</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="24"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="1905"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>We read with interest the recently published paper by Macedonia and Repetto that highlights the role of physical activity and gesture use in improving cognitive functions, learning and well-being in healthy subjects (Macedonia and Repetto, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The aim of the authors is to translate recent scientific findings about this issue from neuroscience to the educational and learning framework in schools. It is stressed that better learning may be achieved when conceptual reasoning and thinking are associated with movement, due to the beneficial effects of physical activity on neurogenesis, the modulation of neurotransmitters and neurotrophic factors and neuroplastic brain changes. Benefits arising from physical activity are also evidenced by the observation that gesture use helps to internalize cognitive strategies in everyday performance due to mechanisms of visuo-motor learning facilitation. This occurs not only when gesture use is coupled with cognitive reasoning in the same subject but also when subjects observe others' actions while processing their own cognitive tasks (Conson et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p><p>While agreeing with all this evidence, we would like to highlight the educational role that physical activity has not only in healthy subjects but also in patients with a wide spectrum of motor, perceptive, and cognitive dysfunctions as a result of specific neurological diseases. For instance, physical activity has been shown to have protective effects on cognitive functions and memory in patients with Alzheimer's disease (AD), in whom functional alterations of several neurotransmitter systems in the early phases of the disease are driven by the Beta-amyloid action (Mura et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The beneficial effect of physical activity would be mediated by the induction of structural and neurochemical changes in the hippocampus and related medial temporal lobe areas that are important for learning and memory (Duzel et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Exercise has therefore been considered as a treatment for pre-clinical AD, later stage AD, and as a prevention strategy (Cass, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Similarly, physical activity has been reported to be beneficial in patients with Parkinson's disease (PD), the prevalence of which is progressively increasing as a result of population aging (Totaro et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Patients with PD, especially in the early stages of the disease, can benefit from sustained strength training, aerobic training, tai chi, or dance therapy lasting at least 12 weeks (Mak et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Some evidence has also demonstrated that physical exercise is able to boost motor learning in patients with PD (Marinelli et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), especially when the exercise has appropriate intensity and repetition, difficulty, complexity, and specificity (Mehrholz et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Moreover, the effectiveness of physical re-education in patients with PD may be improved by combining sensory stimulation, cueing and music in pleasant social contexts and environments that increase task enjoyment (Volpe et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Finally, some patients showing the most severe forms of cognitive and motor disability, such as vegetative state (VS) and Locked-In Syndrome (LIS), seem to benefit from rehabilitative approaches based on gesture observation and simulation. For example, a subgroup of patients with VS was recently reported to recover some elementary purposeful motor behaviors when they were stimulated through a combination of Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation and gesture observation (Pistoia et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>). This suggests that gesture observation may favor the transformation of some perceived actions into motor images and performances, probably depending on the activation of mirror motor neurons and ultimately resulting in the recovery of elementary motor activities in some patients (Sar&#x000e0; and Pistoia, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Pistoia et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>). Similarly, action observation may improve motor imagery and performance in healthy subjects as well as in patients with the most severe forms of motor disability, including LIS (Conson et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). LIS is a severe neurological condition characterized by the loss of any motor outputs with the exception of vertical eye movements and blinking. Patients with LIS are conscious but show a dramatic reduction of the motor repertoire, with quadriplegia, anarthria, and lower cranial nerve paralysis. They learn to interact with the environment using eye-coded communication. Moreover, recent evidence suggests that they also show a functional impairment of cortical neuronal synchronization mechanisms (Babiloni et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) and suffer from non-motor cognitive symptoms that can be interpreted as signs of an embodiment disorder (Sacco et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Conson et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Pistoia et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Rehabilitative approaches based on the observation of motor performances by others may help patients to overcome their selective motor imagery defects and to promote a virtuous cycle of movement observation, planning, and execution.</p><p>The aforementioned syndromes are not the only neurological diseases that can benefit from physical activity: aerobic exercise has been shown to be effective in the treatment of chronic tension-type headache and migraine (Pistoia et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>; Daenen et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Sacco et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) as well as in the reduction of risk factors associated with stroke (Niewada and Michel, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) or affecting stroke's outcomes (Sacco et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Mairb&#x000e4;url, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) and in the rehabilitative management of multiple sclerosis (Devasahayam et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, physical activity is a valuable educational tool to improve overall brain health not only in healthy subjects but also in patients with various neurological conditions, where neural plasticity may be enhanced either by the physical performance itself or by mechanisms of visuo-motor learning facilitation. It is no accident that the rehabilitative process is defined as an educational process where the patient is asked to relearn previously acquired motor and cognitive skills. For this process to be successful the patient has to learn how to learn. He should be guided in discovering the most effective strategies to recover learning abilities and original skills.</p><sec id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>All authors listed have made a substantial, direct and intellectual contribution to the work, and approved it for publication.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Babiloni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchio</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buffo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Resting state eyes-closed cortical rhythms in patients with locked-in-syndrome: an EEG study</article-title>. <source>Clin. Neurophysiol</source>. <volume>121</volume>, <fpage>1816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1824</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2010.04.027</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20541461?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541461</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cass</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Alzheimer's disease and exercise: a literature review</article-title>. <source>Curr. Sports Med. Rep</source>. <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/JSR.0000000000000332</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28067736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28067736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojano</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Recognition and mental manipulation of body parts dissociate in locked-in syndrome</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn</source>. <volume>73</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandc.2010.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20537784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20537784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojano</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Action observation improves motor imagery: specific interactions between simulative processes</article-title>. <source>Exp. Brain Res</source>. <volume>199</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00221-009-1974-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19690843?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19690843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daenen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varkey</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellmann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijs</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Exercise, not to exercise, or how to exercise in patients with chronic pain? Applying science to practice</article-title>. <source>Clin. J. Pain</source>. <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AJP.0000000000000099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24662498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24662498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devasahayam</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Downer</surname><given-names>M. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploughman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The effects of aerobic exercise on the recovery of walking ability and neuroplasticity in people with multiple sclerosis: a systematic review of animal and clinical studies</article-title>. <source>Mult. Scler. Int</source>. <volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>4815958</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/4815958</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29181199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29181199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duzel</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Praag</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sendtner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Can physical exercise in old age improve memory and hippocampal function?</article-title>
<source>Brain</source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awv407</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26912638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26912638</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macedonia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Repetto</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Why your body can jog your mind</article-title>. <source>Front. Psychol</source>. <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>362</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00362</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28337170?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28337170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mairb&#x000e4;url</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Red blood cells in sports: effects of exercise and training on oxygen supply by red blood cells</article-title>. <source>Front. Physiol</source>. <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>332</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fphys.2013.00332</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24273518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24273518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>M. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong-Yu</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Long-term effects of exercise and physical therapy in people with Parkinson disease</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Neurol</source>. <volume>13</volume>, <fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>703</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrneurol.2017.128</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29027544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29027544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marinelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quartarone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallett</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frazzitta</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghilardi</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The many facets of motor learning and their relevance for Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source>Clin. Neurophysiol</source>. <volume>128</volume>, <fpage>1127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1141</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinph.2017.03.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28511125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28511125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehrholz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kugler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Storch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Treadmill training for patients with Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Datab. Syst. Rev</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>CD007830</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD007830.pub4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mura</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Preda</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Racchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Beta-amyloid: a disease target or a synaptic regulator affecting age-related neurotransmitter changes?</article-title>
<source>Curr. Pharm. Des</source>. <volume>16</volume>, <fpage>672</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/138161210790883723</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20388077?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20388077</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niewada</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Lifestyle modification for stroke prevention: facts and fiction</article-title>. <source>Curr. Opin. Neurol</source>. <volume>29</volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WCO.0000000000000285</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26679568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26679568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Commentary: embodied medicine: mens sana in corpore virtuale sano</article-title>. <source>Front. Hum. Neurosci</source>. <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>381</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2017.00381</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28785213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28785213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojano</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colonnese</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Impaired conscious recognition of negative facial expressions in patients with locked-in syndrome</article-title>. <source>J. Neurosci</source>. <volume>30</volume>, <fpage>7838</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7844</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6300-09.2010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20534832?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534832</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013a</year>). <article-title>Behavioral therapy for chronic migraine</article-title>. <source>Curr. Pain Headache Rep</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-012-0304-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23263845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23263845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013b</year>). <article-title>Corticomotor facilitation in vegetative state: results of a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil</source>. <volume>94</volume>, <fpage>1599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1606</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2013.01.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23385107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivieri</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Contribution of hematocrit to early mortality after ischemic stroke</article-title>. <source>Eur. Neurol</source>. <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>238</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000107946</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17827968?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Degan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Conventional vascular risk factors: their role in the association between migraine and cardiovascular diseases</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>146</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102414559551</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25505017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25505017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Albertini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Management of pathologic laughter and crying in patients with locked-in syndrome: a report of 4 cases</article-title>. <source>Arch. Phys. Med. Rehabil</source>. <volume>89</volume>, <fpage>775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>778</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apmr.2007.09.032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18374012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sar&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Defining consciousness: lessons from patients and modern techniques</article-title>. <source>J. Neurotrauma</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/neu.2008.0804</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19323609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19323609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Totaro</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carolei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Prevalence of Parkinson's disease in the L'Aquila district, central Italy</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol. Scand</source>. <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2005.00426.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15932352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15932352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Signorini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchetto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A comparison of Irish set dancing and exercises for people with Parkinson's disease: a phase II feasibility study</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatr</source>. <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2318-13-54</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23731986?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23731986</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>