<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3621736</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23585882</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-00800</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurochemicals</subject><subj-group><subject>Serotonin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroscience</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Neurochemicals</subject><subj-group><subject>Serotonin</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuroimaging</subject><subj-group><subject>Pet</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Neuropsychology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Mental Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Substance Abuse</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Radiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Nuclear medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>PET imaging</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Verbal Memory Deficits Are Correlated with Prefrontal Hypometabolism in <sup>18</sup>FDG PET of Recreational MDMA Users</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Memory and Frontal Hypometabolism in MDMA Users</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>Oliver G.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000fc;hn</surname><given-names>Kai-Uwe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joe</surname><given-names>Alexius</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seifritz</surname><given-names>Erich</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>Wolfgang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Biersack</surname><given-names>Hans-J&#x000fc;rgen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quednow</surname><given-names>Boris B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Psychotherapy, and Psychosomatics, University Hospital of Psychiatry, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>German Center for Neurodegenerative Disorders (DZNE), Bonn, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Psychiatry, Saarland University Medical Center, Homburg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Nuclear Medicine, University of Bonn, Bonn, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Zurich Center for Integrative Human Physiology, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Sensi</surname><given-names>Stefano L.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University G. D'Annunzio, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>quednow@bli.uzh.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BBQ MW KUK WM. Performed the experiments: BBQ HJB AJ. Analyzed the data: BBQ FJ AJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HJB AJ. Wrote the paper: OGB BBQ MW ES.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e61234</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Bosch et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bosch et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, &#x0201c;ecstasy&#x0201d;) is a recreational club drug with supposed neurotoxic effects selectively on the serotonin system. MDMA users consistently exhibit memory dysfunction but there is an ongoing debate if these deficits are induced mainly by alterations in the prefrontal or mediotemporal cortex, especially the hippocampus. Thus, we investigated the relation of verbal memory deficits with alterations of regional cerebral brain glucose metabolism (rMRGlu) in recreational MDMA users.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>Brain glucose metabolism in rest was assessed using 2-deoxy-2-(<sup>18</sup>F)fluoro-D-glucose positron emission tomography (<sup>18</sup>FDG PET) in 19 male recreational users of MDMA and 19 male drug-na&#x000ef;ve controls. <sup>18</sup>FDG PET data were correlated with memory performance assessed with a German version of the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>As previously shown, MDMA users showed significant impairment in verbal declarative memory performance. PET scans revealed significantly decreased rMRGlu in the bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal and inferior parietal cortex, bilateral thalamus, right hippocampus, right precuneus, right cerebellum, and pons (at the level of raphe nuclei) of MDMA users. Among MDMA users, learning and recall were positively correlated with rMRGlu predominantly in bilateral frontal and parietal brain regions, while recognition was additionally related to rMRGlu in the right mediotemporal and bihemispheric lateral temporal cortex. Moreover, cumulative lifetime dose of MDMA was negatively correlated with rMRGlu in the left dorsolateral and bilateral orbital and medial PFC, left inferior parietal and right lateral temporal cortex.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Verbal learning and recall deficits of recreational MDMA users are correlated with glucose hypometabolism in prefrontal and parietal cortex, while word recognition was additionally correlated with mediotemporal hypometabolism. We conclude that memory deficits of MDMA users arise from combined fronto-parieto-mediotemporal dysfunction.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Dr. Quednow received personal grants from the German Research Foundation (DFG, grant QU 218/1-1), the University of Zurich (Nachwuchsf&#x000f6;rderungskredit), and the Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF, grant PP00P1_123516). The study was funded by the Department of Psychiatry, University of Bonn, Germany. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, &#x0201c;ecstasy&#x0201d;) is an illicit club drug predominantly used by adolescents and young adults for its euphoric, stimulant, and empathogenic/entactogenic properties <xref rid="pone.0061234-Christophersen1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Sumnall1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. After cannabis and cocaine, MDMA together with other amphetamines are the most commonly used illegal drugs in Europe and worldwide <xref rid="pone.0061234-European1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-United1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In a recent survey, 5.5% of the European general population between 15 to 34 years of age have taken ecstasy at least once, with an estimated number of 7.5 million users <xref rid="pone.0061234-European1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>.</p><p>The psychotropic effects of MDMA are mediated primarily through reversal and inhibition of the serotonin (5-HT) transporter (5-HTT) <xref rid="pone.0061234-Rudnick1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> leading to a significant increase of 5-HT in the synaptic cleft <xref rid="pone.0061234-Green1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Other central effects include increases of extracellular dopamine concentrations in the striatum and the prefrontal cortex <xref rid="pone.0061234-Hagino1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, glutamate release in the hippocampus <xref rid="pone.0061234-Anneken1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, an a massive elevation of peripheral cortisol levels of 150&#x02013;800% <xref rid="pone.0061234-Parrott1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>Numerous animal studies with different species provided compelling evidence for an impairment of the 5-HT system following MDMA exposure <xref rid="pone.0061234-Green1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, . In non-human primates, MDMA-induced loss of uniquely 5-HT nerve terminals with a concomitant depletion of up to 95% of 5-HT was observed predominantly in frontal and mediotemporal cortical regions, while other monoamine neurotransmitters such as dopamine or norepinephrine remained unaffected <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ali1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Wilson1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Early studies already suggested an impairment of the 5-HT system in human MDMA users because they display decreased cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) levels of the 5-HT metabolite 5-hydroxyindoleacetic acid (5-HIAA)<xref rid="pone.0061234-McCann1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ricaurte1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The human neurotoxicity of MDMA was also supported by the highly consistent finding that at least intense MDMA users display marked verbal and visuo-spatial memory deficits <xref rid="pone.0061234-Bhattachary1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Importantly, lowered 5-HIAA CSF levels in MDMA users have been shown to be correlated with memory deficits <xref rid="pone.0061234-McCann2" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Bolla1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. Finally, also electrophysiological studies suggested alterations of the 5-HT system in regular MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Croft1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Tuchtenhagen1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p><p>Human imaging studies using 2-deoxy-2-(<sup>18</sup>F)fluoro-D-glucose (<sup>18</sup>FDG) positron emission tomography (PET) showed reduced metabolism in the left hippocampus <xref rid="pone.0061234-Obrocki1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, in bilateral caudate/putamen, the left amygdala <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Obrocki2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, and in the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (DLPFC) <xref rid="pone.0061234-MorenoLopez1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> of MDMA users. Finally, in a large sample of MDMA users, increased glucose metabolism in the ventrolateral frontal cortex (Brodman areal [BA] 10) was reported as well <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p><p>PET studies using serotonergic radioligands consistently showed globally reduced 5-HTT binding in chronic MDMA users most pronounced in mediotemporal and frontal cortices <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert2" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-McCann4" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. These findings were confirmed recently, as widespread cortical and striatal reductions in 5-HTT levels were shown in MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Erritzoe1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. In this sample, time of abstinence was positively correlated with subcortical, but not cortical, 5-HTT binding, suggesting only a partial neuronal recovery in these subjects. However, another recent study failed to find alterations of 5-HTT binding in recreational MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Selvaraj1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Also investigations of postsynaptic 5-HT receptors revealed rather inconsistent results. While early SPECT studies demonstrated decreased cortical 5-HT<sub>2A</sub> receptor binding in current MDMA users and an increase of 5-HT<sub>2A</sub> receptors in former users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Reneman1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, recent PET studies reported either a small decrease <xref rid="pone.0061234-Erritzoe1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref> or an increase of cortical 5-HT<sub>2A</sub> receptor density in current MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-DiIorio1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Urban1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>.</p><p>Interpreting the neuropsychological profile, it was speculated that MDMA users have deficits during storage and/or retrieval of memory information arising from a dysfunction of the mediotemporal cortex <xref rid="pone.0061234-Fox1" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-GouzoulisMayfrank1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Fox2" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) studies also suggested differences in the activation of the hippocampus between MDMA users and healthy controls during working memory tasks and supported the view of a hippocampal dysfunction in MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Becker1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Moeller1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. However, further functional imaging studies additionally reported abnormalities in the activation of several other brain regions&#x02013;including frontal, thalamic, striatal, cingulate, temporolateral, parietal, and occipital regions&#x02013;of MDMA users during working memory tasks <xref rid="pone.0061234-Daumann2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Moeller1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Roberts1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. Neuropsychological evidence additionally points to an MDMA-related impairment of executive functions such as impulsivity, decision-making, and recall consistency indicating frontal dysfunction <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow3" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Valdes1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>.</p><p>Thus, although memory deficits are the most consistent finding in MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Kalechstein1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, their neurobiological basis are unclear so far. Moreover, no study explored cerebral glucose metabolism assessed by PET in relation to MDMA-related memory deficits subdivided into different functions such as learning, recall, and recognition. Therefore, we investigated regional cerebral glucose metabolism (rMRGlu) and verbal memory performance of recreational MDMA users and drug-na&#x000ef;ve controls by <sup>18</sup>FDG PET and the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT). Subsequently, we correlated rMRGlu with several RAVLT parameters in both groups separately to determine the origin of memory dysfunction in MDMA users. The neuropsychological pattern already published from this sample suggested that frontal and mediotemporal dysfunction might be involved in the development of memory deficits <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Thus, we expect to find correlations specifically between decreased rMRGlu in frontal and temporomedial brain regions and diminished memory performance in MDMA users.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Demographics and drug use</title><p>Both groups did not significantly differ with respect to age, handedness, years of education, and verbal intellectual performance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t001">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>). There were fewer smokers in the drug-na&#x000ef;ve control group compared to the MDMA group and mean cigarettes per day also differed between both groups (MDMA: 11.6&#x000b1;8.6 SD; controls: 3.1&#x000b1;8.0 SD; T(36)&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;3.19, p&#x0003c;.003). The amount of illicit drug use is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t002">
<bold>Table 2</bold>
</xref>. Importantly, the MDMA group used predominantly MDMA, while the use of amphetamine, cocaine, and hallucinogens was only sporadic. However, MDMA users also revealed a mild to moderate cannabis use. In contrast, drug-na&#x000ef;ve controls did not report any experiences with illicit drugs.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Demographic data of 19 male recreational MDMA users and 19 male drug-na&#x000ef;ve controls (numbers or means and standard deviations in parentheses).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDMA users</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>N</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Age</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8 (5.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.2 (5.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 (4.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Handedness right/left</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c7;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Smoker/Nonsmoker</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>&#x003c7;</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;8.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Verbal IQ</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.2 (12.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.6 (11.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105.7 (13.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;&#x02212;1.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Years of education</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.4 (1.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.3 (1.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5 (1.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>T</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;&#x02212;0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>T-tests or Chi<sup>2</sup>-test (with Yates correction) for frequency data.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Pattern and amount of illegal drug use: results of the Psychotropic Drug Interview (means and standard deviations in parentheses).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug characteristics<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDMA users</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MDMA</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tablets per week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.97 (2.73)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66 (1.95)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative dose (tablets)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">457.9 (433.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lifetime peak dose<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref> (tablets)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.1 (4.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last consumption (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 (14.6); <italic>n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;19</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cannabis</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Times per week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63 (1.62)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95 (3.11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative dose (times)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">547.1 (502.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last consumption (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1 (21.6); <italic>n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;16</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Amphetamine</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Times per week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (1.31)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37 (2.05)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative dose (times)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208.5 (279.5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last consumption (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.1 (89.9); <italic>n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;17</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Cocaine</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Times per week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04 (0.10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Years of use</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (1.70)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative dose (times)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.87 (12.51)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last consumption (days)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.5 (17.2); <italic>n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;4</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Hallucinogens</bold>
<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cumulative dose (times)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4 (38.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last consumption (month)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.86 (9.37); <italic>n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;14</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00 (0.00)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>Consumption per week, duration of use, and cumulative dose are averaged within the total group. Last consumption is averaged only for persons who used the drug. In this case, sample size, <italic>n</italic>, is shown</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>Highest single MDMA dose ever used.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>c</label><p>Primarily LSD and psilocybin-containing mushrooms were used.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Verbal Memory</title><p>As reported previously from this sample <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, immediate (supraspan, trial 1) and delayed recall (trial 7), learning performance (&#x003a3; trials 1&#x02013;5), and recall consistency from the RAVLT was significantly worse in MDMA users compared to controls with medium to large effect sizes (d&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.66&#x02013;1.13, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t003">
<bold>Table 3</bold>
</xref>). Moreover, MDMA users revealed a slight and non-significant reduction of verbal recognition, showing, however, a medium effect size. Previously, we already demonstrated that several indicators of MDMA use were significantly correlated with memory scores <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Performance in the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Task (RAVLT) of MDMA users and healthy drug-naive controls (means and standard deviations in parentheses).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MDMA users</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">df</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cohen's d</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Supraspan</bold> (<italic>trial 1</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1 (2.3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 (2.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.042</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Learning performance</bold> (<italic>&#x003a3; trials 1</italic>&#x02013;<italic>5</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.2 (8.2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7 (5.7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Delayed recall</bold> (<italic>trial 7</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.2 (2.9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.2 (1.0)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;4.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Recall consistency, trials 1&#x02013;5</bold> (<italic>in percent</italic>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.6 (8.6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.1 (4.8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Adjusted recognition performance list A</bold> (<italic>p</italic>(<italic>A</italic>))</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 (0.1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Brain metabolism</title><p>MDMA users showed a significant decrease of resting rMRGlu in the right and left DLPFC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g001">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
</xref>
<bold>, </bold>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t004">
<bold>Table 4</bold>
</xref>). Bilateral frontal hypometabolism ranged from BA 8, 9, and 10 up to the premotor cortex (BA 6), showing slightly stronger effects in the right hemisphere (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g001">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
</xref>
<bold>, </bold>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t004">
<bold>Table 4</bold>
</xref>). Moreover, a significant decrease of resting rMRGlu in MDMA users could be demonstrated for the bilateral inferior parietal cortex (BA 40), as well as in the right precuneus (BA 7). In addition, the bilateral thalamus showed significant hypometabolism primarily in areas connected with the prefrontal cortex (PFC) <xref rid="pone.0061234-Behrens1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. The significant cluster including the right thalamus extended to the right hippocampus. A significant decrease of rMRGlu could also be shown in the metencephalon (pons) and mesencephalon (at the level of the rostral raphe nuclei) as well as in the right posterior cerebellum of the MDMA users (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g001">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
</xref>). Increases of rMRGlu in MDMA users were not significant.</p><fig id="pone-0061234-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Brain regions in which regional glucose metabolism was significantly decreased in 19 recreational MDMA users compared to 19 drug-na&#x000ef;ve healthy controls (p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected, cluster level &#x0003e;25 voxel, clusters projected on an SPM MRI template).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0061234.g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Brain regions with significant decreased regional glucose metabolism in 19 recreational MDMA users compared to 19 drug-na&#x000ef;ve controls (MNI coordinates of maximum significant voxels, p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>z (df 36)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">MNI coordinates</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">P<sub>uncorrected</sub>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Hemisphere</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann area</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Voxel</italic>
</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>x,y,z (mm)</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>voxel-level</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle/superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;63</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">precuneus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;51</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cerebellum, posterior lobe</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;51</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">42</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">48</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle/superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">15</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thalamus (prefrontal), hippocampus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">9</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">thalamus (prefrontal)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;66</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">45</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pons, raphe nuclei</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label>a</label><p>
<italic>Cluster significant at p&#x0003c;.05 (corrected for multiple testing).</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>b</label><p>
<italic>Cluster significant at p&#x0003c;.05 (uncorrected).</italic>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Correlations of brain metabolism with verbal memory deficits</title><p>To investigate the relation of decreased resting rMRGlu with memory impairment we only investigated positive correlations between rMRGlu and memory performance (low performance in conjunction with decreased rMRGlu) in MDMA users (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g002">
<bold>Figure 2</bold>
</xref>
<bold> and </bold>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t005">
<bold>Table 5</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0061234-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Brain regions in which decreased regional glucose metabolism was significantly correlated with low memory performance in 19 recreational MDMA users (p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected, cluster level &#x0003e;25 voxel).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0061234.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Brain regions in which regional glucose metabolism was positively correlated with memory parameters in 19 recreational MDMA users (MNI coordinates of maximum significant voxels, p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t005-5" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>z (df 17)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">MNI coordinates</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">P<sub>uncorrected</sub>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Hemisphere</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann area</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Voxel</italic>
</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>x,y,z (mm)</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>voxel-level</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold><underline><italic>Supraspan</italic></underline></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;3</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">63</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">precentral / inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/44</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold><underline><italic>Learning performance</italic></underline></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">129<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">precentral gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold><underline><italic>Delayed recall</italic></underline></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">39</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">middle frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt108">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">18</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">36</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">precentral gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;45</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">54</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold><underline><italic>Recall consistency</italic></underline></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">30</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold><underline><italic>Recognition</italic></underline></bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior/middle temporal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38/21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;27</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gyrus rectus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;15</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;30</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parahippocampal gyrus/hippocampus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">33</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">angular gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt107">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior temporal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt107"><label>a</label><p>
<italic>Cluster significant at p&#x0003c;.05 (uncorrected).</italic>
</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label>b</label><p>
<italic>Cluster significant at p&#x0003c;.05 (corrected for multiple testing).</italic>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><sec id="s2d1"><title>Supraspan</title><p>Within the MDMA-group, low rMRGlu in the left inferior parietal (BA 40), left premotor (BA 6), left dorsolateral (BA 8), and left ventrolateral frontal cortex (BA 44, 47) was significantly correlated with worse performance during the first RAVLT trial (supraspan).</p></sec><sec id="s2d2"><title>Learning</title><p>Within the MDMA-group, rMRGlu in the right premotor (BA 6), bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal (BA 8, 9), and the left inferior frontal cortex (BA 47) was significantly correlated with the total learning performance in the RAVLT.</p></sec><sec id="s2d3"><title>Delayed recall</title><p>Within the MDMA-group, rMRGlu in the bilateral dorsolateral and ventrolateral PFC (BA 8, 9, 10), the right premotor cortex (BA 6), the right inferior parietal cortex (BA 40, cluster ranges into the occipital parts of BA 39 and BA 19), and the right superior temporal cortex (BA 13), were significantly positively correlated with the delayed recall performance in the RAVLT.</p></sec><sec id="s2d4"><title>Recall consistency</title><p>Within the MDMA-group, rMRGlu only in the right DLPFC (BA 9) was correlated with recall consistency during the first five RAVLT trials.</p></sec><sec id="s2d5"><title>Recognition</title><p>Within the MDMA-group, rMRGlu in the bilateral superior temporal cortices (BA 38), the right orbitofrontal cortex (gyrus rectus, BA 11), the left anterior hippocampus and parahippocampal gyrus (BA 28) and the left parieto-occipital part of the angular gyrus (BA 39) was associated with corrected recognition performance of list A (p(A)) of the RAVLT.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Correlation of MDMA intake and resting rMRGlu</title><p>To investigate the impact of cumulative MDMA intake across lifetime on structural alterations of the brain, we only investigated negative correlations between resting rMRGlu and drug dose (high consumption corresponding with decreased rMRGlu). Low rMRGlu was significantly correlated with high cumulative total dose of MDMA in the left dorsolateral (BA 8) and bilateral orbital and ventromedial PFC (BA 11, 25) as well as in the left inferior parietal cortex (BA 40) and the right lateral temporal cortex (BA 20, 37) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g003">
<bold>Figures 3</bold>
</xref>
<bold> and </bold>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g004">
<bold>4</bold>
</xref>
<bold>, </bold>
<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0061234-t006">
<bold>Table 6</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0061234-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Brain regions in which decreased regional glucose metabolism was significantly correlated with high MDMA cumulative lifetime consumption in 19 recreational MDMA users (p&#x0003c; 0.005, uncorrected, cluster level &#x0003e;25 voxel).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0061234.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone-0061234-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Brain regions with decreased regional glucose metabolism (red), and correlations of low memory performance (green) and high cumulative lifetime MDMA use with glucose metabolism (purple) in 19 recreational MDMA users (p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected, cluster level &#x0003e;25 voxel, clusters projected on an <sup>18</sup>FDG PET template drawn from the controls).</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0061234.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0061234-t006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0061234.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Brain regions in which regional glucose metabolism was negatively correlated with cumulative lifetime dose of MDMA in 19 recreational MDMA users (MNI coordinates of maximum significant voxels, p&#x0003c;.005, uncorrected).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0061234-t006-6" xlink:href="pone.0061234.t006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>z (df 17)</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster size</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">MNI coordinates</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">P<sub>uncorrected</sub>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Hemisphere</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Anatomical region</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brodmann area</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Voxel</italic>
</td><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>x,y,z (mm)</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">
<italic>voxel-level</italic>
</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt109">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">51</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">superior frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;57</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;21</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fusiform/inferior temporal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37/20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">57</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">right</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inferior parietal lobule</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">left</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">medial frontal gyrus</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11/25</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt109"><label>a</label><p>
<italic>Cluster significant at p&#x0003c;.05 (uncorrected). </italic>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Overlap of glucose hypometabolism, memory deficits, and drug intake</title><p>To investigate if there is an overlap between frontal hypometabolism, memory impairment and MDMA intake in MDMA users, we overlaid the significant clusters of the MDMA-control group contrast (rMRGlu hypometabolism in rest) with the correlation clusters between rMRGlu and delayed recall and between rMRGlu and MDMA intake in the PMOD 3.0 (PMOD Technologies, Z&#x000fc;rich, Switzerland). All three significant cluster sets were projected on an FDG PET template drawn from the control group (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0061234-g004">
<bold>Figure 4</bold>
</xref>). Delayed recall was chosen because MDMA users showed the strongest impairment here.</p><p>Glucose hypometabolism of MDMA users strongly overlapped with positive correlations of rMRGlu and delayed recall in the bilateral DLPFC (superior/middle frontal gyrus; BA 8/9). Moreover, there was a triple overlap of MDMA intake, delayed recall, and hypometabolism in the left DLPFC. Finally, drug intake and delayed recall correlations with rMRGlu overlapped in right inferior parietal cortex (BA 40).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The aim of this study was to investigate the neurobiological correlates of memory deficits in currently abstinent recreational MDMA users. Using <sup>18</sup>FDG-PET in rest, we demonstrated that MDMA users showed a significant reduction of cerebral glucose metabolism predominantly in the bilateral DLPFC and inferior parietal cortex, as well as the bilateral thalamus, right hippocampus, right precuneus, right cerebellum, and pons (at the level of raphe nuclei). In the group of MDMA users, learning and recall parameters were positively correlated with rMRGlu primarily in bilateral frontal and parietal brain regions, while word recognition was additionally related to rMRGlu in the right mediotemporal and bihemispheric lateral temporal cortex. In addition, cumulative lifetime dose of MDMA was negatively correlated with rMRGlu in the left DLPFC, bilateral ventromedial prefrontal and orbitofrontal cortex as well as left inferior parietal and right lateral temporal cortex. Importantly, glucose hypometabolism and rMRGlu correlations with recall deficits and cumulative MDMA intake altogether strongly overlapped within the left DLPFC of MDMA users, indicating that foremost drug-induced changes of the DLPFC might contribute to memory impairment in MDMA users.</p><p>Regarding affected brain structures in MDMA users, we replicated several previous findings reporting decreased glucose metabolism in the DLPFC <xref rid="pone.0061234-MorenoLopez1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> and hippocampus <xref rid="pone.0061234-Obrocki1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> in MDMA users. Our results are also in line with previous studies showing changes of serotonergic radioligand binding in prefrontal and parietal regions <xref rid="pone.0061234-Kish1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-McCann4" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Reneman1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, hippocampus <xref rid="pone.0061234-Kish1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, and in the thalamus <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert3" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-deWin1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref> of MDMA users. In contrast, we did not find decreased rMRGlu in the amygdala and cingulate cortex or increased rMRGlu in the ventrolateral PFC as reported from the so far largest sample of MDMA users (n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;93 compared to n&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;27 control subjects) <xref rid="pone.0061234-Buchert1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. However, our sample might have been underpowered to detect these additional changes.</p><p>Previous studies demonstrated that regional reduction of cerebral glucose metabolism might result from loss of neuronal connections and projections <xref rid="pone.0061234-Hampel1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0061234-Millien1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>. As such, the reductions of cortical rMRGlu in MDMA users might as well be explained by loss of neuronal connections and projections and thus be interpreted as a direct neurotoxic effect of the drug, as they were shown in many pervious animal studies <xref rid="pone.0061234-Hatzidimitriou1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Dzietko1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. Interestingly, the thalamic hypometabolism of MDMA users shown here occurred in anatomical areas that are well connected to frontocortical regions presenting also hypometabolism <xref rid="pone.0061234-Behrens1" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. Also the reduction of glucose metabolism at the brain stem level might be explained by lesions of the raphe nuclei as a previous study with non-human primates demonstrated pathological changes specifically in the dorsal raphe nucleus induced by MDMA <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ricaurte2" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Crucially, the symmetry of glucose hypometabolism in MDMA users, which occurred bilaterally in several regions such as the thalamus, frontal and prefrontal areas as well as the parietal cortex, confirms the validity and stability of the present results. Furthermore, it supports the argument of neurotoxicity, as neuronal damages would be expected to develop spatially nonspecific, thus equally distributed over both hemispheres <xref rid="pone.0061234-Rosenberg1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>.</p><p>Given that we have only investigated current users with a mean duration of abstinence of two to three weeks in a cross-sectional design, it can not be concluded if the reported alterations are lasting or transitory.</p><p>The results from this study confirm our hypothesis that hypometabolism in the frontal cortex and in the hippocampus is correlated with verbal memory deficits in recreational MDMA users. Within the MDMA group, worse working memory (supraspan) performance was correlated with low rMRGlu inferior parietal, premotor, dorsolateral, and left ventrolateral PFC. Given that the supraspan has a strong working memory component <xref rid="pone.0061234-Helmstaedter1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref> this correlation pattern might indicate a specific or combined impairment of articulatory rehearsal processes (premotor cortex, ventrolateral PFC), of the phonological loop (inferior parietal lobule), and/or the central executive (DLPFC) in MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Baddeley1" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. Furthermore, MDMA users showed a correlation of recall consistency with rMRGlu in the right DLPFC, which is in line with the view the recall consistency represents an aspect of executive functions related to the DLPFC <xref rid="pone.0061234-Alexander1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>,</p><p>Within the MDMA group, total learning performance was associated with the right premotor cortex, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal, and the left inferior frontal cortex. Therefore, learning deficits in MDMA users seem to be caused by dysfunction of frontal encoding or recall processes <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ranganath1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>. Interestingly, acute MDMA effects also seem to influence middle frontal gyrus (BA 10) activity leading to verbal memory encoding impairments <xref rid="pone.0061234-Kuypers1" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>.</p><p>The association of delayed recall and rMRGlu showed the broadest anatomical extension within the MDMA group. Delayed recall performance was positively correlated with the rMRGlu in a prefrontal cluster including the bilateral dorsolateral and ventrolateral PFC and right premotor cortex. Moreover, a parieto-temporal cluster including the right inferior parietal cortex and right superior temporal cortex appeared. Thus, prefrontal and parieto-temporal areas seem to be involved in the dysfunction of delayed recall in MDMA users, indicating disturbed memory formation into&#x02013;or diminished recall from association cortices, beyond the shown working memory and frontal encoding and recall deficits <xref rid="pone.0061234-Helmstaedter1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>.</p><p>Corrected recognition performance was associated with rMRGlu in bilateral superior temporal cortices, right orbitofrontal cortex (gyrus rectus), left anterior hippocampus and parahippocampal gyrus, and left parieto-occipital part of the angular gyrus. Therefore, particularly reduced recognition performance in MDMA users might be explained by hippocampal dysfunction <xref rid="pone.0061234-Aggleton1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>. However, also prefrontal and anterior temporal areas seem to be involved&#x02013;areas that were previously linked with recognition in several PET studies <xref rid="pone.0061234-Tulving1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>.</p><p>Notably, most of the areas showing glucose hypometabolism in MDMA users are part of the two core brain networks: the resting-state default mode network (DMN; precuneus, lateral temporal cortex and hippocampus)<xref rid="pone.0061234-Buckner1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref> and its anti-correlated cognitive control network (CCN; DLPFC, parietal cortex)<xref rid="pone.0061234-Niendam1" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. As cognitive impairment is assumed to reflect altered network connectivity between the DMN and the CCN, our findings might point to disrupted DMN-CCN connectivity, which should be further investigated using resting-state fMRI in MDMA users.</p><p>Taken together, the previously postulated dissociation of prefrontal and hippocampal functions as correlates of memory deficits in MDMA users, resulting from temporal or hippocampal dysfunction alone <xref rid="pone.0061234-GouzoulisMayfrank1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Fox2" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Daumann1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Jacobsen1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, could not be confirmed. In our sample, verbal learning and recall deficits of MDMA users were correlated with glucose hypometabolism in the prefrontal, frontal and parietal cortex, while word recognition was additionally correlated with mediotemporal hypometabolism. Thus, our imaging data support the neuropsychology-based hypothesis of a combined fronto-parieto-mediotemporal dysfunction in abstinent MDMA users <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow3" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. This assumption is in accordance to the results of early animal studies showing that MDMA-induced denervation of 5-HT axons in the frontal cortex and hippocampus display a relatively low regeneration, thus indicating a high susceptibility of these structures for MDMA neurotoxicity <xref rid="pone.0061234-Hatzidimitriou1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Fischer1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ricaurte3" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>.</p><p>The cumulative total dose of MDMA was negatively correlated with rMRGlu in the left dorsolateral and bilateral orbital and ventromedial PFC, left inferior parietal, and right lateral temporal cortex. This finding is largely in line with a recent study showing significant correlation of the severity of MDMA, heroin, alcohol, and cannabis use with rMRGlu in the DLPFC and lateral temporal cortex of polydrug users <xref rid="pone.0061234-MorenoLopez1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>.</p><p>A limitation of this study is the use of subjective reports for assessing the extent of drug consumption. The reliability of these reports may be questionable, as they depend on memory function and are probably influenced by anticipated social expectancies. A solution of this problem would be a toxicological hair analysis, which was not available for us at that time. In this regard, our urine drug screenings are only of restricted advantage, as water soluble substances such as MDMA can only be analyzed until few days post exposure <xref rid="pone.0061234-Ensslin1" ref-type="bibr">[77]</xref>. However, in a study that addressed this problem, a concordance of 91.3 % was found between subjective reports of drug consumption and toxicological hair analyzes of MDMA users, indicating an acceptable reliability of such reports <xref rid="pone.0061234-Stuerenburg1" ref-type="bibr">[78]</xref>. Collectively, it is a pertinent unsolved problems of neurotoxicological research, that an objective method to determine the cumulative lifetime drug consumption is not available to date <xref rid="pone.0061234-Curran1" ref-type="bibr">[79]</xref>. Another key issue of human neurotoxicity studies in illicit drug users is the high prevalence of polytoxic drug use in this population. Although, this study included only subjects with a predominant use of MDMA, these participants also used other drugs. A retrospective differentiation of single substance effects is difficult, as the use of the different substances is highly intercorrelated. In addition, potential protective or potentiating effects of substance combinations on neurotoxicity limit the interpretation of such results. Moreover, tobacco use was significantly more pronounced in MDMA users compared to controls. Given, that nicotine has considerable effects on brain networks and cognitive functions <xref rid="pone.0061234-Newhouse1" ref-type="bibr">[80]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Wylie1" ref-type="bibr">[81]</xref>, the modulating effect of nicotine on our results is not entirely clear although introduction of smoking as a covariate into the group comparisons did not change the main results. Finally, the abstinence duration from the different drugs was highly variable between subjects; however, the abstinence duration of MDMA, cannabis, cocaine, amphetamine and hallucinogens was not systematically correlated with rMRGlu in the user group.</p><p>The availability of biological markers for the central serotonergic system such as 5-HT or 5-HIAA CSF or plasma concentrations would have been of advantage for the interpretation of our study results. However, to date such markers have only low validity and reliability <xref rid="pone.0061234-Taffe1" ref-type="bibr">[82]</xref>. Using a specific serotonergic radioligand might have been of additional interest, as alterations of the cerebral glucose metabolism only reflect global functioning of neuronal tissue. Also in this case, the reliability and specificity of in particular 5-HTT PET ligands seem questionable, as they are not able to reflect global serotonergic functioning <xref rid="pone.0061234-Hoyer1" ref-type="bibr">[83]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Kish2" ref-type="bibr">[84]</xref>. Recently, we developed a novel method employing <sup>18</sup>F-altanserin PET in combination with a dexfenfluramine challenge in order to measure 5-HT release capacity <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow4" ref-type="bibr">[85]</xref>, which now provides the first functional measure for the 5-HT system in humans. Application of this method to MDMA users will allow the first functional investigation of the impact of chronic MDMA intake on 5-HT release capacity.</p><sec id="s3a"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our <sup>18</sup>FDG PET and neuropsychological data show that verbal memory deficits are correlated with glucose hypometabolism in dorsolateral prefrontal and parietal areas of the brains of abstinent MDMA users. This is especially true for global learning performance and delayed recall, while recognition is additionally associated with mediotemporal hypometabolism. Frontal and parietal areas show the highest overlap of glucose hypometabolism with impaired memory function and cumulative drug intake. In conclusion, memory deficits of MDMA users seem to arise from combined fronto-parieto-mediotemporal dysfunction.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Ethic Statement</title><p>The study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Medical Faculty of the University of Bonn. After being informed of the aim of the study by written and oral description, all participants gave written informed-consent statements. The study has been conducted according to the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Participants</title><p>Nineteen male, chronic but currently abstinent users of MDMA and 19 subjects with no history of illicit drug use were studied (all of Caucasian ethnicity). All participants were recruited by advertisements in a techno music magazine. Subjects of the MDMA group were required to have used MDMA at least 50 times in lifetime and over a period of at least one year. In addition, the use of MDMA clearly had to dominate the consumption of any other psychotropic drug and participants should especially have no substantial previous use of other amphetamine derivatives (e.g., methamphetamine) or cocaine. PET scans and neuropsychological assessments were carried out when participants were abstinent for at least three days. Inclusion criteria for both groups included negative drug urine toxicology. Exclusion criteria for both groups included use of any psychotropic medication, a present psychiatric disorder, a family history of psychiatric disorders, as well as a severe somatic disease. None of the participants reported a history of migraine, epilepsy, or craniocerebral trauma.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Procedure</title><p>On the first day the neuropsychological test battery was assessed in the afternoon (2 p.m.), while on the subsequent day the PET scan was carried out in the morning (8 a.m.). For the estimation of verbal intellectual performance, the <italic>Mehrfachwahl-Wortschatz-Intelligenztest</italic> was used <xref rid="pone.0061234-Lehrl1" ref-type="bibr">[86]</xref>. To control for psychiatric disorders, we conducted a <italic>Structured Clinical Interview</italic> (SCID-I) interview according to <italic>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual</italic> IV (DSM-IV) procedures. Drug history and present pattern of psychotropic drug consumption was assessed by the <italic>Interview for Psychotropic Drug Consumption</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow2" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. Afterwards a neuropsychological test battery was applied, including the RAVLT <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow3" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>. The whole battery took about 120 minutes; including breaks as needed, and was generally well tolerated by the participants. During the psychiatric and neuropsychological assessment, the subjects could ask for a break at any time.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Verbal memory assessment</title><p>Employment of the <italic>Verbaler Lern- und Merkf&#x000e4;higkeitstest</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0061234-Helmstaedter1" ref-type="bibr">[66]</xref>&#x02013;a German version of the RAVLT <xref rid="pone.0061234-Rey1" ref-type="bibr">[87]</xref>&#x02013;has been described in detail before <xref rid="pone.0061234-Quednow1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. In brief, the instrument consists of a word list A of 15 nouns (learning list), a second word list B of 15 different nouns (interference list) and a third list C of 50 nouns which includes all words of lists A and B as well as 20 new, but semantically- and phonetically-related words (recognition list). The dependent variables used here are: supraspan (trial 1), learning performance (&#x003a3; trials 1&#x02013;5), recall consistency in percent (according to <xref rid="pone.0061234-Delis1" ref-type="bibr">[88]</xref>), delayed recall (trial 7 after 30 min), and adjusted recognition performance (<italic>p</italic>(<italic>A</italic>)<sub>list A</sub> according to <xref rid="pone.0061234-Forrester1" ref-type="bibr">[89]</xref>). <italic>p</italic>(<italic>A</italic>) is comparable to the discrimination performance (d-prime) of the signal detection theory <xref rid="pone.0061234-Green2" ref-type="bibr">[90]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Positron Emission Tomography</title><p>On the second day, <sup>18</sup>FDG PET scans in rest were conducted according to the <italic>European Association of Nuclear Medicine Procedures Guidelines for Brain Imaging using <sup>18</sup>FDG-</italic>PET (<italic>Version I</italic>)<xref rid="pone.0061234-Bartenstein1" ref-type="bibr">[91]</xref>, using a whole-body, high-resolution positron emission tomograph (Siemens/ ECAT EXACT 47, with 5.8&#x000d7;5.8&#x000d7;5 mm) with <sup>18</sup>FDG as radiotracer. A ten-minute emission scan was started 30 minutes after injection of 296&#x02013;370 MBq <sup>18</sup>FDG. This was followed by a five-minute transmission scan using <sup>68</sup>germanium. Image reconstruction was performed due to filtered back projection using a Hannig-Filter (cut-off frequency of 0.5 cycles), thus leading to 47 transversal layers of 128&#x000d7;128 pixels each and voxel sizes of 2.059&#x000d7;2.059&#x000d7;3.375 mm. Blood glucose levels were assessed anterior to the injection of the tracer. Arterialized blood sampling was used to measure <sup>18</sup>FDG in plasma. Subjects were scanned once, under resting conditions (light dimmed, subjects lying, and eyes closed) during 8:00 and 9:30 a.m., each.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>Age, verbal IQ, years of education, and memory parameters were analyzed using t-tests for independent samples (SPSS 12, Chicago, IL). Handedness and the ratio of smokers and non-smokers were calculated using &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup>-tests with Yates correction.</p><p>PET data were analyzed using Statistical Parametric Mapping 5 (SPM5; Wellcome Functional Imaging Laboratory, London, UK). According to the convention of the <italic>Montreal Neurological Institution</italic> (MNI), the images were spatially normalized using the PET template provided in SPM5 and subsequently smoothed with an isotropic Gaussian kernel to 12&#x000d7;12&#x000d7;12 mm full width at half maximum (FWHM). The normalized and smoothed images were adjusted by a proportional scaling (mean to 50, threshold masking 0.8) for the individual global differences in cerebral glucose metabolism. For voxel-wise comparisons, t-test for independent samples was used. Voxel-wise correlations were performed to assess the relationship between changes in rMRGlu and changes in individual cognitive performance within each group. Because we would have liked to avoid &#x0201c;voodoo correlations&#x0201d; we did not correlate memory performance with metabolic rates within clusters showing significant rMRGlu differences between both groups <xref rid="pone.0061234-Vul1" ref-type="bibr">[92]</xref>. Significance threshold was set at p&#x0003c;0.005 (uncorrected, cluster level &#x0003e;25 voxels). Statistical maps were projected on an MRI T1 structural image template provided by SPM5.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Dr. Irene Daum and Dr. Reinhard Heun for earlier comments to the present data and their advice. The authors would like to express their gratitude to the staff of the Department of Nuclear Medicine of the University of Bonn supporting the study and to Lea M. Hulka for critical comments to the manuscript. None of the authors reported biomedical financial interests or potential conflicts of interest with respect to the present study.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0061234-Christophersen1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Christophersen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Amphetamine designer drugs-an overview and epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett</source>
<volume>112&#x02013;113</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Sumnall1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sumnall</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jerome</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The varieties of ecstatic experience: an exploration of the subjective experiences of ecstasy</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>670</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>682</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16401654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-European1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction (EMCDDA)</collab> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Annual report on the state of the drugs problem in Europe</article-title>. <source>Lisbon: European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction</source>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-United1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC) (2012) World Drug Report 2012. Vienna: United Nations.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Rudnick1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rudnick</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>The molecular mechanism of "ecstasy" [3,4-methylenedioxy-methamphetamine (MDMA)]: serotonin transporters are targets for MDMA-induced serotonin release</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>1817</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1821</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1347426</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Green1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mechan</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Shea</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colado</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The pharmacology and clinical pharmacology of 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, "ecstasy")</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Rev</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>508</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12869661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Hagino1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hagino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takamatsu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iwamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Effects of MDMA on Extracellular Dopamine and Serotonin Levels in Mice Lacking Dopamine and/or Serotonin Transporters</article-title>. <source>Curr Neuropharmacol</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21886569</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Anneken1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Anneken</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gudelsky</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>MDMA produces a delayed and sustained increase in the extracellular concentration of glutamate in the rat hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1022</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1027</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22842073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Parrott1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Parrott</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Cortisol and 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine: neurohormonal aspects of bioenergetic stress in ecstasy users</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology</source>
<volume>60</volume>: <fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19893332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Lyles1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lyles</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cadet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, Ecstasy) neurotoxicity: cellular and molecular mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Brain Res Rev</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>168</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12738056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Steinkellner1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Steinkellner</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freissmuth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sitte</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The ugly side of amphetamines: short- and long-term toxicity of 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, 'Ecstasy'), methamphetamine and D-amphetamine</article-title>. <source>Biol Chem</source>
<volume>392</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ali1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newport</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scallet</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Binienda</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Oral administration of 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA) produces selective serotonergic depletion in the nonhuman primate</article-title>. <source>Neurotoxicol Teratol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7685472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Hatzidimitriou1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hatzidimitriou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Altered serotonin innervation patterns in the forebrain of monkeys treated with (+/&#x02212;)3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine seven years previously: factors influencing abnormal recovery</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>5096</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10366642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Insel1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Insel</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johannessen</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Souza</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine ("ecstasy") selectively destroys brain serotonin terminals in rhesus monkeys</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
<volume>249</volume>: <fpage>713</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>720</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2471824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Scheffel1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Scheffel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finley</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dannals</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>In vivo detection of short- and long-term MDMA neurotoxicity&#x02013;a positron emission tomography study in the living baboon brain</article-title>. <source>Synapse</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9593108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Wilson1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molliver</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Distinct morphologic classes of serotonergic axons in primates exhibit differential vulnerability to the psychotropic drug 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>137</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2761687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-McCann1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ridenour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaham</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Serotonin neurotoxicity after (+/&#x02212;)3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA; "Ecstasy"): a controlled study in humans</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7517677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ricaurte1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finnegan</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Langston</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Aminergic metabolites in cerebrospinal fluid of humans previously exposed to MDMA: preliminary observations</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>600</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708; discussion 708&#x02013;610</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1701292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Bhattachary1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bhattachary</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Recreational use of 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA) or 'ecstasy': evidence for cognitive impairment</article-title>. <source>Psychol Med</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>658</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11352367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Fox1"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toplis</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parrott</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Auditory verbal learning in drug-free Ecstasy polydrug users</article-title>. <source>Hum Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12404541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-GouzoulisMayfrank1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gouzoulis-Mayfrank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thimm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rezk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hensen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Memory impairment suggests hippocampal dysfunction in abstinent ecstasy users</article-title>. <source>Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>827</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Rodgers1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Cognitive performance amongst recreational users of "ecstasy"</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>151</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10958112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Wareing1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wareing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Verbal working memory deficits in current and previous users of MDMA</article-title>. <source>Hum Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>234</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15181650</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Wareing2"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wareing</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fisk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Visuo-spatial working memory deficits in current and former users of MDMA ('ecstasy')</article-title>. <source>Hum Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15641126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-McCann2"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mertl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eligulashvili</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Cognitive performance in (+/&#x02212;) 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, "ecstasy") users: a controlled study</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10367560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Morgan1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Memory deficits associated with recreational use of "ecstasy" (MDMA)</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9952062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Quednow1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Quednow</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jessen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daum</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Memory deficits in abstinent MDMA (ecstasy) users: neuropsychological evidence of frontal dysfunction</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16574711</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Bolla1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bolla</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Memory impairment in abstinent MDMA ("Ecstasy") users</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1532</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9855498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Croft1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klugman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baldeweg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruzelier</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Electrophysiological evidence of serotonergic impairment in long-term MDMA ("ecstasy") users</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>1687</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1692</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11579003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Quednow2"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Quednow</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoenig</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Prepulse inhibition and habituation of acoustic startle response in male MDMA ('ecstasy') users, cannabis users, and healthy controls</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>982</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14970829</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Tuchtenhagen1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tuchtenhagen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gobbele</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>High intensity dependence of auditory evoked dipole source activity indicates decreased serotonergic activity in abstinent ecstasy (MDMA) users</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>617</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10788760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Obrocki1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Obrocki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaterlein</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomasius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Ecstasy&#x02013;long-term effects on the human central nervous system revealed by positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>188</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Buchert1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obrocki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomasius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaterlein</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Long-term effects of 'ecstasy' abuse on the human brain studied by FDG PET</article-title>. <source>Nucl Med Commun</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>897</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11473208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Obrocki2"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Obrocki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmoldt</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andresen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Specific neurotoxicity of chronic use of ecstasy</article-title>. <source>Toxicol Lett</source>
<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12052669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-MorenoLopez1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Moreno-Lopez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fernandez-Serrano</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez-Rio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez-Fernandez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Neural correlates of the severity of cocaine, heroin, alcohol, MDMA and cannabis use in polysubstance abusers: a resting-PET brain metabolism study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e39830</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22768136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Buchert2"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomasius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Ecstasy-induced reduction of the availability of the brain serotonin transporter as revealed by [11C](+)McN5652-PET and the multi-linear reference tissue model: loss of transporters or artifact of tracer kinetic modelling?</article-title>
<source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>628</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>634</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17092972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Buchert3"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomasius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nebeling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obrocki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Long-term effects of "ecstasy" use on serotonin transporters of the brain investigated by PET</article-title>. <source>J Nucl Med</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12621003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Buchert4"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buchert</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomasius</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilke</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nebeling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A voxel-based PET investigation of the long-term effects of "Ecstasy" consumption on brain serotonin transporters</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry</source>
<volume>161</volume>: <fpage>1181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15229049</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Kish1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lerch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Decreased cerebral cortical serotonin transporter binding in ecstasy users: a positron emission tomography/[(11)C]DASB and structural brain imaging study</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1797</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20483717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-McCann3"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scheffel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dannals</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Positron emission tomographic evidence of toxic effect of MDMA ("Ecstasy") on brain serotonin neurons in human beings</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>352</volume>: <fpage>1433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1437</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9807990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-McCann4"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>UD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seckin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenblatt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Quantitative PET studies of the serotonin transporter in MDMA users and controls using [11C]McN5652 and [11C]DASB</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15841106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Erritzoe1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Erritzoe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frokjaer</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holst</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christoffersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>In vivo imaging of cerebral serotonin transporter and serotonin(2A) receptor binding in 3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA or "ecstasy") and hallucinogen users</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>562</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>576</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21646575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Selvaraj1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Selvaraj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhagwagar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Brain serotonin transporter binding in former users of MDMA ('ecstasy')</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<volume>194</volume>: <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19336788</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Reneman1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Reneman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Bruin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lavalaye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feenstra</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The acute and chronic effects of MDMA ("ecstasy") on cortical 5-HT2A receptors in rat and human brain</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11850153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-DiIorio1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Di Iorio</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blackford</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evidence for Chronically Altered Serotonin Function in the Cerebral Cortex of Female 3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine Polydrug Users</article-title>. <source>Arch Gen Psychiatry</source>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Urban1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Girgis</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kegeles</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Sustained recreational use of ecstasy is associated with altered pre and postsynaptic markers of serotonin transmission in neocortical areas: a PET study with [(1)(1)C]DASB and [(1)(1)C]MDL 100907</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1473</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22353758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Fox2"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parrott</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Neuropsychological evidence of a relatively selective profile of temporal dysfunction in drug-free MDMA ("ecstasy") polydrug users</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>162</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12110998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Becker1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koester</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kabbasch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Memory-related hippocampal functioning in ecstasy and amphetamine users: A prospective fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Daumann1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Daumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fischermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heekeren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henke</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Memory-related hippocampal dysfunction in poly-drug ecstasy (3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine) users</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>180</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>611</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15372137</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Daumann2"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Daumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Fischermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heekeren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gouzoulis-Mayfrank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Neural mechanisms of working memory in ecstasy (MDMA) users who continue or discontinue ecstasy and amphetamine use: evidence from an 18-month longitudinal functional magnetic resonance imaging study</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
<volume>56</volume>: <fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>355</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15336517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Jacobsen1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mencl</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pugh</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skudlarski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krystal</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Preliminary evidence of hippocampal dysfunction in adolescent MDMA ("ecstasy") users: possible relationship to neurotoxic effects</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>173</volume>: <fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>390</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14647960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Moeller1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Moeller</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narayana</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Functional MRI study of working memory in MDMA users</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>177</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15221201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Daumann3"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Daumann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fimm</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willmes</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thron</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gouzoulis-Mayfrank</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Cerebral activation in abstinent ecstasy (MDMA) users during a working memory task: a functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) study</article-title>. <source>Brain Res Cogn Brain Res</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>487</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12706227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Roberts1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nestor</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garavan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Learning and memory deficits in ecstasy users and their neural correlates during a face-learning task</article-title>. <source>Brain Res</source>
<volume>1292</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19631624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Quednow3"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Quednow</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>KU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoppe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Westheide</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Elevated impulsivity and impaired decision-making cognition in heavy users of MDMA ("Ecstasy")</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>189</volume>: <fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>530</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16425060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Valdes1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Valdes</surname><given-names>IH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinberg</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narayana</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dougherty</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Impulsivity and BOLD fMRI activation in MDMA users and healthy control subjects</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res</source>
<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16890410</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Kalechstein1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Kalechstein AD, De La Garza R, 2nd, Mahoney JJ, 3rd, Fantegrossi WE, Newton TF</collab> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>MDMA use and neurocognition: a meta-analytic review</article-title>. <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
<volume>189</volume>: <fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17082969</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Behrens1"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johansen-Berg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wheeler-Kingshott</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Non-invasive mapping of connections between human thalamus and cortex using diffusion imaging</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>750</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>757</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12808459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-deWin1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>de Win</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booij</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reneman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schilt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Neurotoxic effects of ecstasy on the thalamus</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<volume>193</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18827290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Hampel1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hampel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teipel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pogarell</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>In vivo imaging of region and cell type specific neocortical neurodegeneration in Alzheimer's disease. Perspectives of MRI derived corpus callosum measurement for mapping disease progression and effects of therapy. Evidence from studies with MRI, EEG and PET</article-title>. <source>J Neural Transm</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>837</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12111472</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Kew1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kew</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Passingham</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frackowiak</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Cortical function in progressive lower motor neuron disorders and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: a comparative PET study</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8208409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Millien1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Millien</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blaizot</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giffard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mezenge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Insausti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Brain glucose hypometabolism after perirhinal lesions in baboons: implications for Alzheimer disease and aging</article-title>. <source>J Cereb Blood Flow Metab</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Dzietko1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dzietko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sifringer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klaus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Endesfelder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brait</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Neurotoxic effects of MDMA (ecstasy) on the developing rodent brain</article-title>. <source>Dev Neurosci</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20616555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ricaurte2"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forno</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeLanney</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>(+/&#x02212;)3,4-Methylenedioxymethamphetamine selectively damages central serotonergic neurons in nonhuman primates</article-title>. <source>Jama</source>
<volume>260</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2454332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Rosenberg1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">Rosenberg NL (1995) Basic principles of clinical neurotoxicology. In: Chang LW, Slikker W, Jr., editors. Neurotoxicology-Approaches and methods: Academic press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Helmstaedter1"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Helmstaedter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lendt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Verbaler Lern- und Merkf&#x000e4;higkeitstest, Manual</article-title>. <source>G&#x000f6;ttingen: Beltz</source>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Baddeley1"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Baddeley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Working memory: looking back and looking forward</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>829</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14523382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Alexander1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stuss</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fansabedian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>California Verbal Learning Test: performance by patients with focal frontal and non-frontal lesions</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<volume>126</volume>: <fpage>1493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12764068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ranganath1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Esposito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Prefrontal activity associated with working memory and episodic long-term memory</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>378</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12457762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Kuypers1"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kuypers</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wingen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinecke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Formisano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramaekers</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MDMA intoxication and verbal memory performance: a placebo-controlled pharmaco-MRI study</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>1053</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1061</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Aggleton1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Aggleton</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Episodic memory, amnesia, and the hippocampal-anterior thalamic axis</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Sci</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>444; discussion 444&#x02013;489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11301518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Tulving1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tulving</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nyberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lepage</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Positron emission tomography correlations in and beyond medial temporal lobes</article-title>. <source>Hippocampus</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10088902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Buckner1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews-Hanna</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schacter</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The brain's default network: anatomy, function, and relevance to disease</article-title>. <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
<volume>1124</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18400922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Niendam1"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Niendam</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glahn</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Meta-analytic evidence for a superordinate cognitive control network subserving diverse executive functions</article-title>. <source>Cogn Affect Behav Neurosci</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22282036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Fischer1"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatzidimitriou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wlos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Reorganization of ascending 5-HT axon projections in animals previously exposed to the recreational drug (+/&#x02212;)3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA, "ecstasy")</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>5476</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5485</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7643196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ricaurte3"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ricaurte</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martello</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martello</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Lasting effects of (+&#x02212;)-3,4-methylenedioxymethamphetamine (MDMA) on central serotonergic neurons in nonhuman primates: neurochemical observations</article-title>. <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
<volume>261</volume>: <fpage>616</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>622</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1374470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Ensslin1"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ensslin</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kovar</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maurer</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Toxicological detection of the designer drug 3,4-methylenedioxyethylamphetamine (MDE, "Eve") and its metabolites in urine by gas chromatography-mass spectrometry and fluorescence polarization immunoassay</article-title>. <source>J Chromatogr B Biomed Appl</source>
<volume>683</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8891915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Stuerenburg1"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stuerenburg</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenkranz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buhmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Plasma concentrations of 5-HT, 5-HIAA, norepinephrine, epinephrine and dopamine in ecstasy users</article-title>. <source>Neuro Endocrinol Lett</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12080289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Curran1"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Curran</surname><given-names>HV</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Is MDMA ('Ecstasy') neurotoxic in humans? An overview of evidence and of methodological problems in research</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology</source>
<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10867554</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Newhouse1"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Newhouse</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dumas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Functional brain imaging of nicotinic effects on higher cognitive processes</article-title>. <source>Biochem Pharmacol</source>
<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>943</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>951</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21684262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Wylie1"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wylie</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tregellas</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Nicotine increases brain functional network efficiency</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22796985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Taffe1"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Taffe</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatzidimitriou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Cognitive performance of MDMA-treated rhesus monkeys: sensitivity to serotonergic challenge</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1005</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12464456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Hoyer1"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hoyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular, pharmacological and functional diversity of 5-HT receptors</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>554</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11888546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Kish2"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kish</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>How strong is the evidence that brain serotonin neurons are damaged in human users of ecstasy?</article-title>
<source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>855</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11888575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Quednow4"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Quednow</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Treyer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hasler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorig</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wyss</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Assessment of serotonin release capacity in the human brain using dexfenfluramine challenge and [18F]altanserin positron emission tomography</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>3922</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3932</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21996132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Lehrl1"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lehrl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Mehrfachwahl-Wortschatz-Intelligenztest: MWT-B</article-title>. <source>Balingen</source>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Rey1"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rey A (1964) L'examen de Clinique en Psychologie. Paris: Presses Universitaire de France.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Delis1"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Delis DC, Kramer J, Kaplan E, Ober BA (1987) California Verbal Learning Test, Adult Verision Manual. San Antonio, TX: Psychological Cooperation.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Forrester1"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geffen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Performance measures of 7- to 15-year-old children on the Auditory Verbal Learning Test</article-title>. <source>The Clinical Neuropsychologist</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Green2"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Green DM, Swets JA (1966) Signal Detection Theory and Psychophysics. London: J. Wiley.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Bartenstein1"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bartenstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asenbaum</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Catafau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halldin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>European Association of Nuclear Medicine procedure guidelines for brain imaging using [(18)F]FDG</article-title>. <source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>BP43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12436498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0061234-Vul1"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vul</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pashler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Voodoo and circularity errors</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>948</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22270348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>