<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Neurol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-2295</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6277635</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2018.01009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Non-pharmacological Approaches for Headaches in Young Age: An Updated Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/560334/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grazzi</surname><given-names>Licia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/548274/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>Emanuela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>Domenico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raggi</surname><given-names>Alberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/616367/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grignani</surname><given-names>Eleonora</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Psychology, University of Memphis</institution>, <addr-line>Memphis, TN</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Neuroalgology Division, Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Neurologico Carlo Besta</institution>, <addr-line>Milan</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Neurology, Public Health and Disability Unit, Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Neurologico Carlo Besta, Neurology</institution>, <addr-line>Milan</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Massimiliano Valeriani, Bambino Ges&#x000f9; Ospedale Pediatrico (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Marco Carotenuto, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi della Campania &#x0201c;Luigi Vanvitelli&#x0201d;, Italy; Laura Papetti, Bambino Ges&#x000f9; Ospedale Pediatrico (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Frank Andrasik <email>fndrasik@memphis.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Headache Medicine and Facial Pain, a section of the journal Frontiers in Neurology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1009</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 Andrasik, Grazzi, Sansone, D'Amico, Raggi and Grignani.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Andrasik, Grazzi, Sansone, D'Amico, Raggi and Grignani</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Headache disorders are common in children and adolescents. Most of the studies on non-pharmacological treatments have however been carried out on adults. In this review we provide information on recent studies examining non-pharmacological approaches for managing headache in children and adolescents. Our search of SCOPUS for primary studies conducted between January 2010 and July 2018 uncovered 11 controlled studies, mostly addressing behavioral approaches, in which a total of 613 patients with a diagnosis of primary headache, and average age 10.2&#x02013;15.7 years (30&#x02013;89% females) were recruited. Non-pharmacological treatments were shown to produce sizeable effects on the classical primary endpoint, i.e., headache frequency, with reductions from baseline ranging between 34 and 78%. Among commonly reported secondary endpoints, particularly disability, quality of life, depression and anxiety, marked improvements were noted as well. Taken as a whole, our findings suggest that non-pharmacological treatments constitute a valid option for the prevention of primary headaches in young age. Future research with higher-quality studies is needed. Particular attention needs to be given to studies that randomize patients to condition, blind researchers in charge of evaluating treatment outcomes, routinely include headache frequency as the primary endpoint, include adequate-length follow-up, address changes in biomarkers of disease and other possible mediators of outcome, and that employ predictive models to enhance the level of evidence for these approaches.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>cognitive-behavioral therapy</kwd><kwd>biofeedback</kwd><kwd>mindfulness</kwd><kwd>transcranial magnetic stimulation</kwd><kwd>migraine</kwd><kwd>tension-type headache</kwd><kwd>disability</kwd><kwd>depression</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="47"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="5898"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Headache disorders are common in children and adolescents, affecting up to 88% of the pediatric and adolescent population, with chronic headache types impacting up to 6% (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Headache can result in significant disability, including missed school days and limitations in extracurricular activities, such as social events with peers, family gatherings, and sports. Pharmacological treatment for acute episodes typically include non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), analgesics, and triptans. As with adults, appropriate administration is needed in order to be effective, with specific attention being given to providing information about the risk for medication overuse headache (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Among preventive drugs, antiepileptics such as topiramate, are considered as first-line treatment (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>), and several drugs used in the prevention of migraine in adults are commonly prescribed for children (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Side effects of particular relevance for children and adolescents include weight loss or weight gain, paresthesias, cognitive slowing, and sleepiness. Caution is warranted in adolescent females in particular due to the elevated risk of developing polycystic ovarian syndrome as well as possible teratogenic effects of many of these compounds. Drug treatment, however, is not always needed, and prophylactic treatment is not considered the first line treatment in the vast majority of cases (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In recent years, attention has been increasingly paid to non-pharmacological treatments of headache disorders, chiefly those that are cognitive, behavioral, or psychophysiological in nature, but with some attention to non-invasive neurostimulation (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Overall, significant benefits, typically ranging from 35 to 50%, have been reported for the above-mentioned treatments with respect to reductions in headache frequency. However, most of the published studies on non-pharmacological treatments have been carried out on adults, and more recent literature reviews have not focused extensively on young headache patients. The aim of the present review is to help fill this gap by providing updated information on more recent investigations of non-pharmacological approaches to the treatment of headache in children and adolescents.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Search strategy</title><p>We performed a comprehensive search on SCOPUS covering the period January 2010&#x02013;July 2018 to identify primary research papers reporting either randomized clinical trials (RCTs) or observational studies that addressed non-pharmacological approaches for headaches disorders in children and adolescents. The following combinations of key-words were searched within the titles, abstracts, or key-words provided:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>headache OR &#x0201c;tension type headache&#x0201d; OR migraine OR &#x0201c;chronic tension type headache&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;chronic migraine&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;medication overuse headache.&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>young OR adolesc<sup>*</sup> OR juvenile.</p></list-item><list-item><p>&#x0201c;cognitive behavio<sup>*</sup> therapy&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;acceptance and commitment therapy&#x0201d; OR ACT OR mindfulness OR biofeedback OR &#x0201c;relaxation training&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;lifestyle modification<sup>*</sup>&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;complementary alternative medicine&#x0201d; OR neuromodulation OR neurostimulation OR &#x0201c;single pulse transcranial magnetic stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;transcutaneous supraorbital nerve stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;non-invasive vagal nerve stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;caloric vestibular stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;sphenopalatine ganglion stimulation&#x0201d; OR &#x0201c;occipital nerve stimulation.&#x0201d;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Our search was limited to original studies, published in English language peer-reviewed journals, and filtered by the following subject areas: Medicine, Neurosciences, Health Profession, Pharmacology, Toxicology and Pharmaceutics, Biochemistry, Genetics and Molecular Biology and Psychology. Finally, we filtered for other key-words clearly not germane to our topic (the detailed search strategy is included in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Supplementary Materials</xref>).</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria for articles selected</title><p>We specifically searched for clinical trials and observational studies, either cross-sectional or longitudinal, and excluded reviews, commentaries, letters to the editors, editorials, qualitative studies, case reports and small case series (&#x0003c; 10 subjects).</p><p>To be included papers needed to provide sufficient information to extract the following: impact of non-pharmacological treatment on headache frequency or other outcomes, such as disability or quality of life, as assessed by patient-reported outcomes measures (PROMs) and/or parent report. Studies further had to focus on the primary headache disorders of migraine or tension-type headache. Studies drawing from populations that included other types of headache disorders (mixed disorders), or wherein the presence of headache was addressed chiefly as a symptom in the context of other general medical conditions were excluded. Finally, studies that included both adolescents and young adults were excluded if the findings were reported in aggregate and it was not possible to disentangle the outcomes for the adolescents or if the average age of the sample suggested that the study was predominantly carried out in a population of adults.</p></sec><sec><title>Paper selection and data extraction</title><p>Selected abstracts were screened by a single researcher (EG) and, in order to ensure quality and consistency of data extraction, 20% of the abstracts along with the full texts were randomly selected for a second evaluation conducted by another reviewer (AR or ES) who was blind to the initial decision. We determined at the outset if agreement rates were below 70%, each of the double-checked abstract or manuscript would be re-reviewed by the two researchers to arrive at a final decision by consensus (however, as will be seen below, this did not surface as a problem).</p><p>Extracted information included the kind of non-pharmacological approach employed, broadly defined in terms of Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT), a mindfulness-based approache, Biofeedback (BFT) treatment, Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS) and Multimodal treatment. We also recorded the main characteristics of selected studies, which included sample size, percentage of females, mean age, headache frequency at baseline and at follow-up, percent reduction and, when available, clinical significance of outcomes. We converted reported values for headache frequency to conform to a standard, comparable monthly period when authors described it differently (e.g., on a 3-month basis).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The initial search returned 427 records. Following abstract screening and full text assessment, 11 publications were selected for inclusion in this review (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The rate of agreement between reviewers was 99.5% at the abstract check, and 100% at full-text check. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows the PRISMA flow diagram of our search process. Table <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">1</xref> presents a summary of the main outcome of the publications included in this review.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flowchart of papers' selection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneur-09-01009-g0001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Main characteristics and main outcomes of the included studies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ID</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Treatment</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Control</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Headache type</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Sample size (% W)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Age</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Baseline HA freq&#x02014;FU freq</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>% reduction (sig.)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Main results</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Powers et al. (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT + Amitriptyline</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache education + Amitriptyline</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (80%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.4&#x02013;6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;71.9%(<sup>**</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT determined significant reduction in headache frequency and improvements in migraine-related disability.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rapoff et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical therapy (as prescribed for usual clinical practice)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (88%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.7&#x02013;7.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;48.2% (ns)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT determined improvements in post-intervention headache severity and in 3-months post-intervention QoL.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hickman et al. (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache education</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (81.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nr&#x02014;nr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT determined significant improvements in headache disability, anxiety, depression and healthy lifestyle beliefs.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Law et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Internet-delivered CBT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specialized headache treatment (medical, physical, psychological)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (EM, TTH, both, other)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (81.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24&#x02013;15.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;35.8% (<sup>**</sup>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT determined significant headache reduction and improvements on headache pain intensity, activity limitations, depressive symptoms and parent protective behaviors.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sharma et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical therapy (as prescribed for usual clinical practice)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (Primary headache)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (47.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nr&#x02014;nr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CBT determined significant improvements on headache severity, clinician-rated overall anxiety and state and trait anxiety.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tornoe and Skov (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB + RT</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (TTH/CTTH)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (88.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1&#x02013;11.1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;41.88% (<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB determined significant headache frequency reduction.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blume et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (Primary headache)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (69.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x02013;8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;42.9% (<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>**</sup></xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB determined improvements in headache frequency and severity.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shiri et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mixed (CTTH, CM)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (30%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x02014;nr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BFB significantly improved ratings of pain, daily functioning and quality of life.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hesse et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mind</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recurrent head</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (100%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.6&#x02014;nr</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mindfulness determined improvements in depression symptoms, pain acceptance and in parents-rated physical health-related quality of life.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irwin et al. (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (66.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.3&#x02013;8.8</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;33.8% (<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN1"><sup>*</sup></xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TMS determined improvements in headache frequency, acute medication use and headache-related disability.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prezekop et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multimodal treatment</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical prophylaxis (Amitriptyline or Gabapentin)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CTTH</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (80.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3&#x02013;4.9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;78% (<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN2"><sup>**</sup></xref>)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multimodal treatment determined improvements in headache frequency, pain intensity, general health, pain restriction and number of bilateral tender points.</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significance was reported as</p><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p>p &#x0003c; 0.05;</p></fn><fn id="TN2"><label>**</label><p><italic>p &#x0003c; 0.001; ns, not significant; nr, not reported</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Across the studies, 613 participants with a diagnosis of primary headache and average age ranging between 10.2 and 15.7 years were recruited. Patients were mostly females, ranging on average between 30 and 88.9%, with one study including females only (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Six RCTs involved samples of patients with different primary headaches; two studies involved patients with chronic migraine, one with episodic migraine, one with chronic tension type headache, one describing patients only as &#x0201c;chronic headache,&#x0201d; and one addressing &#x0201c;recurrent headache.&#x0201d;</p><p>Five papers consisted of single group studies, while the remaining six were RCTs in which a given non-pharmacologic treatment was compared with either treatment as usual (TAU) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), headache education (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), education plus amitriptyline (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), amitriptyline or gabapentin (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The majority of the studies evaluated the effects of CBT (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Three studies included BFB treatment (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The remaining three studies evaluated mindfulness (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), single-pulse TMS (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and a multimodal treatment (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><sec><title>Studies on CBT</title><p>Five RCTs assessed CBT, comparing it to education (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), TAU (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) or amitriptyline plus education (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Two of these studies focused on adolescents experiencing different forms of primary headache (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), whereas the other three trials evaluated CBT in patients with episodic migraine (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), chronic migraine (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) or &#x0201c;chronic headache&#x0201d; (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) alone. In all studies, CBT sessions were delivered weekly, for periods varying between 4 and 12 weeks.</p><p>CBT yielded significant reductions in headache frequency that ranged between 35.8 and 71.9% in two studies (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Although Rapoff and colleagues did not report a statistically significant reduction in headache frequency, the magnitude of improvement was sizeable 47.9%. Two trials did not report on change in headache frequency (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>Three of the above-mentioned studies (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) reported significant reductions in disability that ranged between 11.8 and 88.1%, as measured by the PedMIDAS. Other studies noted improvements in other secondary outcomes measured by PROMs investigating pain intensity (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), quality of life (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), and parent protective behaviors, which include all parents' responses that, on one hand serve to reinforce pain complaints through increased parental attention and presence and, on the other hand, inappropriately lessen pain complaints by permitting children and adolescent to escape or avoid unwanted responsibilities or roles (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Furthermore, the two studies that did not report on headache frequency focused their attention on other aspects that are often associated with headache, chiefly symptoms of anxiety and depression. The first of these two studies (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>) evaluated the effects of a CBT intervention that focused on improving mental health overall (i.e., decrease perceived stress, anxiety and depression, while strengthening beliefs in ability to manage pain and to engage in a healthier lifestyle) and providing education about identifying and managing headache triggers. This 7-week treatment was compared to an education program of the same duration that focused on potential headache triggers (i.e., lifestyle, environmental, medication, hormonal, and dietary triggers) and headache hygiene measures (i.e., regular sleep and eating habits, moderate exercise, good hydration, and avoidance of caffeine, ethyl alcohol and other drugs). CBT produced significant reductions for symptoms of anxiety (11.3%) and depression (13.9%), as well as improvements with regards to headache disability and healthy lifestyle beliefs, when compared to headache education alone. In the second study, Sharma et al. (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) enrolled adolescents diagnosed as migraine or tension type headache, with comorbid anxiety disorders, who were randomized to either a transdiagnostic group CBT or a TAU control group. The intervention consisted of 12 weekly sessions that focused on identification of shared mechanisms across disorders, psychoeducation about headache and anxiety, cognitive restructuring, and stress management techniques. Adolescents within the CBT group showed significant improvements on headache severity and anxiety as assessed by clinical evaluations and PROMs.</p></sec><sec><title>Studies on BFB treatment</title><p>Three single group outcome studies investigated various forms of BFB. The first study (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) included a sample of children with frequent or chronic tension-type headache who underwent 9 sessions of electromyographic biofeedback combined with computer animated relaxation therapy. Between baseline and 3-month follow-up, headache frequency decreased significantly, dropping from 19.1 to 11.1 headache days per month (49.1%). Furthermore, pericranial tenderness was significantly reduced among those who experienced frequent tension-type headache.</p><p>The second study, carried out by Blume et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>), involved children with different types of primary headaches, who underwent an average of 7 hand warming BFB sessions. Between baseline and the last training session, participants showed a significant reduction of 42.9% in headache frequency (decreasing from 14 to 8 headache/days per month). Median headache intensity also decreased significantly from a value of 6 at baseline to 5 at the final visit on a 10-point scale (16.7%).</p><p>Finally, Shiri et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) evaluated the effects of a virtual reality system combined with BFB on a sample of children diagnosed with varied primary headaches. At the beginning of the treatment, participants had their picture taken in various emotional states to which they attached images representing their pain. During the 10 BFB sessions, children were instructed to watch their image and try to relax. Biofeedback yielded significantly improved ratings of pain by 51.9%, daily functioning by 67.4%, and quality of life by 20%. Moreover, the authors reported that most patients seemed to harness their new relaxation skills to relieve headache outside of the laboratory setting.</p></sec><sec><title>Mindfulness-based intervention</title><p>Hesse et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) evaluated a mindfulness-based intervention in a sample composed entirely of female adolescents experiencing &#x0201c;recurrent headaches.&#x0201d; All participants underwent eight 2 h weekly mindfulness sessions and were instructed to practice learned techniques at least once per day. The intervention was tailored to address headache and the resultant related distress by teaching the adolescents to become more mindful of breath and sounds, which was supplemented with didactic lessons and group discussions. Due to the small number of adolescents providing headache daily diaries, no formal analyses of improvements for headache frequency and severity were performed. However, improvements were noted with respect to depression symptoms (21.6% lower) and pain acceptance (22.2% lower). Further, while parent-rated questionnaires showed improved physical health-related quality of life (13.4%), reports by the adolescents did not reveal any meaningful decreases in disability over time. Although by no means definitive, this study suggests that mindfulness can be a feasible and acceptable intervention for adolescents with recurrent headaches.</p></sec><sec><title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS)</title><p>One study investigated the efficacy of single-pulse TMS in adolescents diagnosed with chronic migraine (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). During the 12-week treatment period participants were instructed to apply the device twice daily, administering additional pulses as needed for acute treatment. A significant reduction in headache frequency (33.8%), as assessed by headache diaries, was found when comparing the 28 days prior to treatment (mean of 13.3 days) to the last 28 days of treatment (mean of 8.8 days). Post-treatment data were not provided, so maintenance of effects is unknown. Improvements in headache-related disability as assessed by PedMIDAS were also found, with scores decreasing from 63 &#x000b1; 46 to 27 &#x000b1; 27 (57%).</p></sec><sec><title>Multimodal treatment</title><p>One study assessed the effects of a multimodal treatment in adolescents with chronic tension type headache (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The intervention was compared to a group of patients who received a preventative medication, either amitriptyline or gabapentin. The multimodal treatment group was instructed to practice complementary techniques (mindfulness and qi gong) and received osteopathic manual treatments. At 6-month follow-up, patients showed a 78% decrease in headache frequency that dropped from 22.3 to 4.9 headache days per month. Improvements were also found in secondary outcomes, such as pain intensity (67.2%), general health (67.9%), pain restriction (63%) and number of bilateral tender points (80%).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results of the present literature review showed that various non-pharmacological treatments in populations of young headache patients produced sizeable effects on the primary endpoint, headache frequency, with reductions from baseline ranging between 34 and 78%. These findings are of particular interest as they are comparable to those usually found in trials on pharmacological treatments (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Moreover, many of the approaches herein reviewed produced meaningful effects on other commonly used patient-reported outcomes as well, particularly with respect to disability, quality of life, and symptoms of depression and anxiety.</p><p>The importance of considering non-pharmacological treatments in the array of possible prophylactic treatments in young headache patients lies in several factors. In particular, untoward side effects have not been reported for these procedures when applied with children and adolescents. In the rare instance when such effects have been reported for adults, they are noted to be short-lived and easily overcome (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). This stands in marked contrast to the array of side effects observed in drug prophylaxis, with the most common being sedation or somnolence, dizziness, mood/behavioral changes, constipation, increased appetite, and weight gain (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Second, in recent years these treatments&#x02014;particularly behavioral ones&#x02014;have gained in popularity among adult patients, while conventional pharmacological treatments are being viewed as sometimes ineffective or too expensive (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). It is therefore likely that a similar trend will emerge not only among the parents of child and adolescent patients, but also among the patients themselves. Third, but no less important, non-pharmacological treatments are thought to enable young patients to enhance their abilities to handle pain and cope more effectively with pain episodes absent medications. In the long run, these learned skills may serve to reduce the risk of overusing medication as the adolescents become adults. These mentioned factors&#x02014;together with the results of the present review&#x02014;support the idea that non-pharmacological treatments should no longer be considered only as alternative or complementary to pharmacological treatments for headaches. Rather, they merit inclusion in the array of possible first line treatments for headache disorders, in particular among populations of children and adolescents.</p><p>Although effects are in general pronounced, mechanisms by which non-pharmacological treatments exert their effects has received only scant attention. Results from the present review suggest that, with regard to CBT and Mindfulness-based treatments in particular, headache improvement may be related in part to concurrent improvements in symptoms of anxiety and depression (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In fact, available literature suggests that children and adolescents with headache disorders, and migraine in particular, may have higher symptoms of anxiety and depression when compared to healthy counterparts (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). We emphasize &#x0201c;suggestive&#x0201d; because of the possibility of false positive responses based on screening tools wherein certain scale items overlap some symptoms of depression, anxiety, and migraine (e.g., mood and energy level changes may incur in both premonitory and post-drome phases of migraine and are core symptoms of anxiety and depression). Taken as a whole, the conclusions of the aforementioned literature reviews indicate that the majority of young patients with headache disorders do not show diagnosable psychiatric comorbidities. However, when present, they deserve attention and appropriate treatments to improve patients' prognoses (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Headaches are regarded as bio-behavioral disorders, which means that both dysfunction in several brain areas and behavioral responses to stimuli, such as stress or pain, concur to the maintenance of the disease, which in fact may arise from the complex interaction between biological and psychosocial variables (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The brain of patients with headache, particularly in migraineurs, is hyper-reactive to prolonged repeated stimuli, and altered inter-ictal information processing is associated with limbic system dysfunction (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). Studies specifically examining cognitive processes related to pain modulation in healthy individuals shed light on core brain regions involved in cognitive interventions, such as the prefrontal cortex, the midcingulate cortex, the thalamus, and the amygdala; i.e., the same brain areas which are involved in the cognitive and affective components of pain (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). However, these have to be taken as hypotheses, since the aforementioned studies are derived from populations of healthy adults. With regard to sTMS, it is proposed that the fluctuating magnetic field delivered by the device may induce electrical currents that disrupt cortical spreading depression (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>); i.e., a wave of excitation followed by a wave of inhibition of both neurons and glia, which spreads across the cortical mantle that is purported to be a physiological substrate of migraine with aura (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). It is not associated with side effects, and it is therefore considered a safe treatment for migraine. Among adults, several studies have been carried out on both single-pulse and repetitive TMS (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>), while the data for pediatric populations is&#x02014;to the best of our knowledge&#x02014;confined to the single study included in the present review. Finally, BFB is a bio-behavioral approach through which patients learn to voluntarily modify their bodily reactions via feedback-mediated awareness of physiologic parameters, such as peripheral skin temperature or electromyography (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). It is deemed to act, in part, by reducing cortical excitability and affecting resonance and oscillations of essential feedback loops in the brain (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>) induced by modifications of bodily reactions through feedback-mediated awareness of physiologic parameters.</p><p>The evidence generated by the present review needs to be tempered somewhat due to certain shortcomings in the available studies, all of which need to be addressed in future research in the field of non-pharmacological treatments for pediatric headache in young patients. Many of the results herein reported have in fact been derived from single group open-label outcome studies, which preclude us from addressing comparative efficacy of these treatments. The inability to implement double-blinding for behavioral treatments remains a contentious issue for some. Although this concern cannot be addressed fully, rigor can be enhanced by randomizing participants to study and control or comparison groups and blinding those in charge of selecting, assigning, and evaluating treatment outcomes. With studies on non-invasive neurostimulation, sham procedures can be employed to enable double-blinding. Also, headache frequency was not always employed as the primary endpoint, which is specified as critical in all existing trial guidelines. Two studies reported only descriptive baseline information on headache frequency, while two studies did not report frequency at all, thus relying on measures that are traditionally employed as secondary endpoints, such as disability or quality of life. Duration of follow-up is another critical element, as most of the studies reviewed herein that reported data collection beyond the end of treatment did so only for a few months (e.g., around 3&#x02013;4). This leaves us unable to draw any meaningful conclusions about stability of effects over the long term. Finally, future studies need to examine factors that mediate and/or are associated with positive outcomes. This can be accomplished in a number of ways, such as addressing changes in biomarkers associated with non-pharmacological approaches, based on neuroimaging and biological assays, and developing predictive models. In fact patient selection is of paramount importance in pediatric populations, and thus future studies should encompass a wide spectrum of clinical, psychosocial and biological indicators, in order to identify which are the most relevant patient features that are associated with positive clinical changes.</p><p>Our search was confined to SCOPUS because its search engine is noted to be wide ranging and journals within it are indexed from both medical and social science fields. Further, great care was taken to employ quality control measures aimed to reduce the possibility that relevant papers were excluded. Nonetheless, we cannot be certain that all relevant articles were included in our review process. Given our resultant small sample size, overlooking just a few salient articles may have altered our conclusions. Nutraceuticals, another prominent area of non-pharmacological treatments, were not included in the present review because an extensive literature review of this domain was published at the time we launched our search (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). This more recent review confirmed the results of previous current reviews (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>); i.e., that few studies exist, most are of low quality, and, consequently, the evidence generated thus far remains sparse.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our review on the use of non-pharmacological approaches in young patients with primary headaches showed that these treatments produced sizeable effects on headache frequency, with reductions from baseline ranging between 34 and 78%, which in fact is comparable to that obtained when treating patients with pharmacological compounds. When reported, these treatments led to positive outcomes in various secondary endpoints as well.</p><p>Our findings reinforce the conclusions expressed by authors of other recent literature reviews (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). We share the opinion that preventive drug treatment for headache is not always needed in young headache patients, and that the risk of side effects must always be taken into account. Conversely, clinicians should consider non-pharmacological treatments of headache disorders as a first line strategy in children and adolescents with primary headaches.</p><p>Future studies, incorporating random assignment, relying on headache frequency as the primary endpoint, employing more extended follow-up periods, and assessing possible mechanisms of treatment, such as changes in relevant biomarkers, would help to shore up the existing data base for the overall value of non-pharmacological treatments for children and adolescents experiencing recurrent headache. Determining factors predictive of outcome merits intensive study as well.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>FA, LG, and DD led the initiative and revised the drafted document. ES selected abstracts and revised the drafted document. AR and EG selected abstract, extracted data and drafted the manuscript. All authors approved the final version.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2018.01009/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2018.01009/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seshia</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chronic daily headache in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Curr Pain Headache Rep</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-011-0228-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22102156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22102156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Linde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and disability of headache among Norwegian adolescents: a cross-sectional school-based study</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>1181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102415573512</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25720767?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720767</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langdon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>DiSabella</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pediatric headache: an overview</article-title>. <source>Curr Probl Pediatr Adolesc Health Care</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cppeds.2017.01.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28366491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28366491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Linder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Topiramate for migraine prevention in children: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>1304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4610.2005.00262.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16324162?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16324162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hershey</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentti</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Degrauw</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of amitriptyline in the prophylactic management of childhood headaches</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2000</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1526-4610.2000.00085.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10940092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10940092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Management of children and young people with headache</article-title>. <source>Arch Dis Child Educ Pract Edu</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>102</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/archdischild-2016-311803</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27998893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27998893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanteri-Minet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Valade</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Geraud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Revised French guidelines for the diagnosis and management of migraine in adults and children</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1129-2377-15-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24400971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24400971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raggi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grignani</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Grazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral approaches for primary headaches: recent advances</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>913</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.13337</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29802634?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29802634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rains</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Penzien</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrory</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavioral headache treatment: History, review of the empirical literature, and methodological critique</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>S92</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4610.2005.4502003.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15921506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15921506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maasumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tepper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>New treatments for headache</article-title>. <source>Neurol Sci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>38</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 1</issue>):<fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-017-2910-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28527051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28527051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoenen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Magis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Noninvasive neurostimulation methods for migraine therapy: the available evidence</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102416636022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27026674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27026674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashikar-Zuck</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>LeCates</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Cognitive behavioral therapy plus amitriptyline for chronic migraine in children and adolescents: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Assoc</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>310</volume>:<fpage>2622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2013.282533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rapoff</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Connelly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bickel</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hershey</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JR.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Headstrong intervention for pediatric migraine headache: a randomized clinical trial</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>12</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1129-2377-15-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24580721</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hickman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Melnyk</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized controlled trial of the acceptability, feasibility, and preliminary effects of a cognitive behavioral skills building intervention in adolescents with chronic daily headaches: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Pediatr Health Care</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pedhc.2014.05.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25017938?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25017938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Law</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Beals-Erickson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Claar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Palermo</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pilot randomized controlled trial of internet-delivered cognitive-behavioral treatment for pediatric headache</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1410</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.12635</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26316194?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26316194</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Efficacy of transdiagnostic cognitive-behavioral group therapy for anxiety disorders and headache in adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Anxiety Disord</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>78</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.janxdis.2016.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27856068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27856068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tornoe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Computer animated relaxation therapy in children between 7 and 13 years with tension-type headache: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10484-011-9173-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22080435?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blume</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuner</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Biofeedback therapy for pediatric headache: factors associated with response</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>1377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4610.2012.02215.x.</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22804229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22804229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shiri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Feintuch</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pustilnik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Geffen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A virtual reality system combined with biofeedback for treating pediatric chronic headache&#x02013;a pilot study</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/pme.12083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23659372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hesse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy-Overfelt</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mindfulness-based intervention for adolescents with recurrent headaches: a pilot feasibility study</article-title>. <source>Evid Based Compl Alt Med</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>508958</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/508958</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26798398?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26798398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Qubty</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Patniyot</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goadsby</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation for migraine prevention in adolescents: a pilot open label study</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>58</volume>:<fpage>724</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.13284</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29528485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29528485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Przekop</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Przekop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haviland</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multimodal compared to pharmacologic treatments for chronic tension-type headache in adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Bodyw Mov Ther</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbmt.2015.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27814849?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27814849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kacperski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hershey</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Preventive drugs in childhood and adolescent migraine</article-title>. <source>Curr Pain Headache Rep.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>422</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-014-0422-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24760491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24760491</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papetti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Spalice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicita</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paolino</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Castaldo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Iannetti</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Migraine treatment in developmental age: guidelines update</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10194-010-0205-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16841370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20349201</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Monastra</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Problems associated with relaxation procedures and biofeedback and guidelines for management</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> editors. <source>Biofeedback</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>). p. <fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertisch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Buettner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use among adults with migraines/severe headaches</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>1087</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4610.2011.01917.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21649654?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21649654</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schachter</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Complementary and alternative medicine use among US adults with common neurological conditions</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>257</volume>:<fpage>1822</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-010-5616-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20535493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20535493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabela</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Attanasio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanchard</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenblum</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological functioning of children who have recurrent migraine</article-title>. <source>Pain</source> (<year>1988</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 3405619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3405619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qubty</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological and behavioral issues in the management of migraine in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Curr Pain Headache Rep</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-016-0597-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27896587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27896587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Comorbid psychological conditions in pediatric headache</article-title>. <source>Semin Pediatr Neurol</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.spen.2016.01.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27017025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27017025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychiatric comorbidity and paediatric migraine: examining the evidence</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WCO.0000000000000192</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25923126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25923126</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellini</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Arruda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cescut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saulle</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Persico</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carotenuto</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Headache and comorbidity in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>79</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1129-2377-14-79</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24063537</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waldie</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical and psychological correlates of primary headache in young adulthood: a 26 year longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>72</volume>:<fpage>86</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.72.1.86</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11784831?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11784831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Flor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Turk</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An expanded view of psychological aspects in head pain: the biopsychosocial model</article-title>. <source>Neurol Sci</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>26</volume> (<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>):<fpage>S87</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-005-0416-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15926029?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15926029</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Lorenzo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Serrao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parisi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pathophysiological targets for non-pharmacological treatment of migraine</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>1103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102415620908</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26637237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26637237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flor</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychological pain interventions and neurophysiology: implications for a mechanism-based approach</article-title>. <source>Am Psychol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0035254</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24547804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24547804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Shields</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transcranial magnetic stimulation: basic principles and clinical applications in migraine</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.13002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28028801?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28028801</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tfelt-Hansen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>History of migraine with aura and cortical spreading depression from 1941 and onwards</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>780</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-2982.2009.02015.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19740119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19740119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinsella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Giffin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipscombe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Weatherall</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Single-pulse transcranial magnetic stimulation (sTMS) for the acute treatment of migraine: evaluation of outcome data for the UK post market pilot program</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s10194-015-0535-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodick</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Silberstein</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Aurora</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlman</surname><given-names>SH.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Single-pulse transcranial magnetic stimulation for acute treatment of migraine with aura: a randomised, double-blind, parallel-group, sham-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(10)70054-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20206581</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhoi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>High-rate repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation in migraine prophylaxis: a randomized, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source>J Neurol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>260</volume>:<fpage>2793</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>801</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00415-013-7072-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23963471?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23963471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teepker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000f6;tzel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmesfeld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mylius</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Haag</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Low-frequency rTMS of the vertex in the prophylactic treatment of migraine</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2010</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-2982.2009.01911.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19515124</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Definitions of biofeedback and applied psychophysiology</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> editors. Biofeedback. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name> (<year>2003</year>). p. <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eddie</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic processes in regulation and some implications for biofeedback and biobehavioral interventions</article-title>. <source>Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10484-013-9217-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23572244?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23572244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The evidence for the role of nutraceuticals in the management of pediatric migraine: a review</article-title>. <source>Curr Pain Headache Rep</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11916-018-0692-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29619575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29619575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sangermani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Boncimino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The use of nutraceutics in children's and adolescent's headache</article-title>. <source>Neurol Sci</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>38</volume> (<issue>Suppl 1</issue>):<fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>124</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10072-017-2896-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28527085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28527085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkateswaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nutraceuticals in the prophylaxis of pediatric migraine: Evidence-based review and recommendations</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102413519512</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24443395?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24443395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>