<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4603896</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26461064</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-24629</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Nurse-Led Medicines' Monitoring for Patients with Dementia in Care Homes: A Pragmatic Cohort Stepped Wedge Cluster Randomised Trial</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Nurse-Led Medicines' Monitoring: A Stepped RCT</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gabe-Walters</surname><given-names>Marie Ellenor</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>Alan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Humphreys</surname><given-names>Ioan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Newson</surname><given-names>Louise</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>Sherrill</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>Michael S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>College of Human and Health Sciences, Swansea University, Swansea, Wales</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>College of Medicine, Swansea University, Swansea, Wales</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Briel</surname><given-names>Matthias</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University Hospital Basel, SWITZERLAND</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: SJ MEG AW IH LN SS MSD. Performed the experiments: SJ MEG LN SS. Analyzed the data: SJ AW. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SJ AW. Wrote the paper: SJ MEG AW IH LN SS MSD. Collected data: SJ MEG LN SS. Prepared the data: MEG.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>m.gabe@swansea.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>e0140203</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 Jordan et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jordan et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0140203.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>People with dementia are susceptible to adverse drug reactions (ADRs). However, they are not always closely monitored for potential problems relating to their medicines: structured nurse-led ADR Profiles have the potential to address this care gap. We aimed to assess the number and nature of clinical problems identified and addressed and changes in prescribing following introduction of nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Design</title><p>Pragmatic cohort stepped-wedge cluster Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) of structured nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring <italic>versus</italic> usual care.</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Setting</title><p>Five UK private sector care homes</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Participants</title><p>41 service users, taking at least one antipsychotic, antidepressant or anti-epileptic medicine.</p></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Intervention</title><p>Nurses completed the West Wales ADR (WWADR) Profile for Mental Health Medicines with each participant according to trial step.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Outcomes</title><p>Problems addressed and changes in medicines prescribed.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Data Collection and Analysis</title><p>Information was collected from participants&#x02019; notes before randomisation and after each of five monthly trial steps. The impact of the Profile on problems found, actions taken and reduction in mental health medicines was explored in multivariate analyses, accounting for data collection step and site.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Results</title><p>Five of 10 sites and 43 of 49 service users approached participated. Profile administration increased the number of problems addressed from a mean of 6.02 [SD 2.92] to 9.86 [4.48], effect size 3.84, 95% CI 2.57&#x02013;4.11, P &#x0003c;0.001. For example, pain was more likely to be treated (adjusted Odds Ratio [aOR] 3.84, 1.78&#x02013;8.30), and more patients attended dentists and opticians (aOR 52.76 [11.80&#x02013;235.90] and 5.12 [1.45&#x02013;18.03] respectively). Profile use was associated with reduction in mental health medicines (aOR 4.45, 1.15&#x02013;17.22).</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The WWADR Profile for Mental Health Medicines can improve the quality and safety of care, and warrants further investigation as a strategy to mitigate the known adverse effects of prescribed medicines.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Trial Registration</title><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.isrctn.com/ISRCTN48133332">ISRCTN 48133332</ext-link>
</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded and supported by the Wales School for Primary Care Research, National Institute for Social Care and Health Research, Cardiff (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wspcr.ac.uk/">http://www.wspcr.ac.uk/</ext-link>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="9"/><page-count count="27"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>As per patient privacy, underlying data are not publically shared, however, the West Wales ADR Monitoring Profile for Mental Health Medicines and the dataset, in IBM spss, are available from the authors on request at <email>m.gabe@swansea.ac.uk</email></meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>As per patient privacy, underlying data are not publically shared, however, the West Wales ADR Monitoring Profile for Mental Health Medicines and the dataset, in IBM spss, are available from the authors on request at <email>m.gabe@swansea.ac.uk</email></p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec011"><title>Introduction</title><p>The adverse effects of prescribed medicines are a public health problem, in the UK[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and worldwide[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Adverse drug reactions (ADRs)7 are responsible for: 20.8% (60/290) of preventable emergency re-admissions within one year of discharge[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]; 4&#x02013;6% of UK hospital bed occupancy[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]; 10% (68/678) hospitalisations in US Veterans&#x02019; Affairs Medical Centres[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]; 3.7% hospital admissions globally[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]; an increasing number of UK hospital admissions[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]; &#x000a3;1&#x02013;2.5bn NHS costs annually[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and ~$30bn expenditure each year in the USA[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Although preventable ADRs account for 5&#x02013;8% of all hospital admissions[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], adverse consequences of untreated conditions are equally common in primary care[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Enhanced patient monitoring might prevent many of these problems[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], and our nurse-led intervention has improved care in several clinical settings[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>We focus on three key medicine groups: antipsychotics, anti-epileptics, and antidepressants, which are often prescribed to people living with dementia, either for the management of associated behavioural and psychological symptoms or the frequently accompanying co-morbid conditions of depression and epilepsy. However there are concerns relating to the use of these medicines because of their side-effect profiles. Whether to manage symptoms of dementia or co-morbidities, 25&#x02013;50% of people with dementia receive antipsychotics[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]; one third of care home residents receive antidepressants[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]; and 10&#x02013;20% of people with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease require anti-epileptics[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Consequently, many older people, particularly those with dementia, are vulnerable to the adverse effects of mental health medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], as evidenced by current prescribing trends[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The Protean ADRs attributed to mental health medicines include worsening cognitive impairment, aggression/ restlessness, sedation, falls, bleeding, and changes in cardiovascular and gastro-intestinal function, as detailed on the WWADR Profile[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>). There is particular concern over the use of antipsychotic medication in people living with dementia, with only modest evidence to suggest clinical improvement but increasing risk of adverse health outcomes and mortality[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>Despite widespread acknowledgment of the &#x02018;ADR problem&#x02019;[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], no recommendations on implementation of medicines&#x02019; monitoring procedures are offered. While the UK&#x02019;s National Institute for Health and Care Excellence (NICE) [<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] specify parameters for monitoring, neither they nor leading reviews[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] nor reports[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] offer monitoring strategies. Written information, while not harmful, is not well regarded by service users, and on its own is insufficient[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, some primary care physicians undertake medication review only if offered suitable financial incentives, including upfront payment of &#x000a3;350[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], and evidence from pharmacist-led interventions is equivocal[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] and described as &#x02018;low quality&#x02019;[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] or uncertain[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Accordingly, our West Wales ADR (WWADR) Profiles are designed to use an alternative link in the &#x02018;medication chain&#x02019;, and to be completed by nurses, who are usually the professionals with the most intimate knowledge of patients. The Profiles aim to minimize ADRs without compromising the beneficial effects of medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]&#x02013;congruent with recent &#x02018;calls to action&#x02019;[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]&#x02014;and promote guideline adherence[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. However, the WWADR Profile for Mental Health medicines has not been tested in clinical trials</p><p>We aimed to assess 1) clinical impact 2) potential cost impact and 3) any harms of nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring using the WWADR Profile for Mental Health Medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Our objectives were to test whether, at individual participant level, introduction of the Profile affected: the number and nature of problems identified and addressed; prescribing; dementia severity; potential service costs and harms.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec012"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec013"><title>Design</title><p>In this cohort stepped wedge cluster randomised trial (SW-CRT), five sites (care homes) were randomised to five sequential steps or time points. There were equal numbers of observations with and without the Profile over the six months of the trial. The cohort SW-CRT design strengthens the traditional cluster randomised controlled trial (RCT): all participants receive the intervention, reducing &#x02018;resentful demoralisation&#x02019;; at each step, sites who receive the intervention act as cross-sectional controls for those who had not; each participant acts as their own longitudinal control, allowing &#x02018;before and after&#x02019; comparison[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; and institution level adoption of the Profile simulates a policy-level intervention. Because all participants cross-over to the intervention by the end of the trial, cohort SW-CRTs are recommended for testing patient safety interventions[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], likely to be beneficial[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], and unlikely to cause harm. (The CONSORT checklist is appended [<xref rid="pone.0140203.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 CONSORT Checklist</xref>]) [<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The authors confirm that all ongoing and related trials for this intervention are registered (ISRCTN 48133332). Prior to participant recruitment in May, we recruited and trained the nurses involved in the project.</p><p>The SW Wales NHS Research Ethics committee (REC) approved the study (reference: 13/WA/0067, 10th April 2013). The protocol is available (<xref rid="pone.0140203.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Protocol</xref>).</p><sec id="sec014"><title>Participants</title><p>Recruitment and follow-up of participants was undertaken May to October 2013 in five sites with 181 service users. The sites were dispersed across South West Wales and run by different private sector organisations. In all sites, prescription and administration of all medicines were documented on paper-based medicines&#x02019; administration record (MAR) charts, which were the responsibility of qualified nurses. Prescriptions were issued by primary care practitioners and consultant-led secondary care services. Medicines were dispensed by community pharmacists in original packaging. Each site had its own record keeping format. Patient records, including medication administration records, were regularly inspected to ensure they met the standards of the Care and Social Services Inspectorate Wales (CSSIW). In care homes, medication records include preparations for minor ailments, which are normally purchased by ambulatory service users, and not necessarily recorded.</p><p>Individual participants&#x02019; inclusion criteria were: resident at the site; currently taking antipsychotics and/or anti-epileptics and/or antidepressants; willing and able to give informed, signed consent themselves, or where capacity was lacking, a guardian or consultee was willing to give informed, verbal assent to review of documentation. We excluded those: aged &#x0003c;18 years; not well enough to participate, according to the clinical judgement of their nurses.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Intervention</title><p>The West Wales ADR Profile for Mental Health Medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] was introduced into the five sites at staggered monthly intervals or steps, for completion with all eligible participants. Once the Profile and guidelines had been introduced, and nurses trained (by SJ, MG), nurses were asked to re-administer it every step as part of usual care. From previous work[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], we anticipated that Profile completion would take 15&#x02013;25 minutes.</p><p>The Profile aims to: alleviate under-reporting of adverse effects of prescribed medicines, facilitate shared decision-making with service users and within the multi-disciplinary team[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>], and identify problems that merit attention irrespective of aetiology. The Profile contains a structured template of 82 items to be completed over several interviews, if needed[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], with comprehensive guidelines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], to ensure unified recording of all information pertinent to potential adverse effects of medicines commonly prescribed for mental health conditions[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> Appendix). The profile was developed for administration during routine nursing care[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>], incorporating ADRs documented in formularies[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], and manufacturers&#x02019; literature. Inter-rater reliability for the items&#x02019; kappa values ranged 0.44&#x02013;1.00, with observational items generally having lower values[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was the number and nature of problems found and addressed, described under &#x02018;clinical impact&#x02019; in &#x02018;data collection&#x02019;, below. Secondary outcomes were changes in individual problems, prescribing, disease severity, and potential costs and harms of the intervention.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Sample size</title><p>In our feasibility before and after study[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] a mean of 3.0 [SD 5.4] more problems were addressed following administration of the Profile, and the intra-cluster correlation coefficient (ICC) was close to zero. To investigate whether this improvement would be replicated in a larger sample would require a total sample of 28, with 80% power, 5% alpha, two sided[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. With 10 participants in each cluster, an ICC of 0.05, and a design effect of 1.45, we calculated that 41 participants were needed[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. We planned to recruit 50 participants from 5 sites, and anticipated 10% loss to follow up over 6 months.</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Recruitment</title><p>Ten sites (care homes) were approached by the research team. Sites were identified from the list of those working with the University, and telephoned for an appointment to explain the study and request participation pre-randomisation. All service users in participating sites were assessed for eligibility and those meeting the inclusion criteria were approached by their nurses.</p></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Randomisation</title><p>The five sites were randomised by the Swansea Clinical Trials Unit (SCTU) to determine at which of the five steps the Profile would be introduced in each site. Sites were informed one month before introduction of the intervention.</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Data Collection</title><p>Participants&#x02019; records were reviewed pre-intervention and at each of 5 subsequent data collection steps. One month between each step minimised the impact of delayed treatment effects on study power[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. We (MEG, SJ, LN, SS) extracted data from participants&#x02019; case notes to identify compliance with the intervention and obtain information on trial outcomes and objectives:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Clinical impact was measured by:
<list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Total number of problems documented as present and addressed at each data collection step (primary outcome), as interval variables. The presence or absence of each possible ADR and whether it was addressed were noted as binary variables (<xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>The nature of specific benefits of the intervention, including: actions taken to reduce ADRs listed on the Profile (<xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>), such as monitoring vital signs, intake and medicines&#x02019; administration[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], and pain management, based on previous work[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] Pain is particularly important, as effective pain management improves the treatment of behavioural difficulties and agitation in people with dementia in care homes[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Dementia, sedation, antipsychotics and antidepressants are also important risk factors for falls and injuries[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Case reports are included to capture the burden, severity or nature of the problems. The presence or absence of each problem and actions taken to address the problem were captured as binary variables, and the proportion of participant records where these were documented was calculated with participants and steps as the denominator (total 249). Case reports are included to capture the burden, severity and nature of the problems.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Changes in prescription regimens as documented in administration records and referral letters. Numbers, names and doses of medicines prescribed were recorded, and binary variables &#x02018;any change in regimen&#x02019; and &#x02018;reduction of medicines associated with mental health&#x02019; (antipsychotics, antidepressants, anitepileptics, benzodiazepines and antimuscarinics prescribed to manage the adverse effects of antipsychotics) were calculated at each step.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Measures of dementia and illness severity: the Bristol Activities of Daily Living (ADL)[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] scale for functional ability and MOUSEPAD[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] for psychopathology, as total scores recorded by nurses at every data collection step, and treated as interval variables. Increasing scores indicated increased dependency / dementia severity.</p></list-item></list>
</p></list-item><list-item><p>Estimated potential economic costs of delivering the intervention</p></list-item><list-item><p>Evidence that the Profile had harmed or burdened participants as captured in participants&#x02019; records, including adverse event forms, and reports from care providers.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Analysis</title><p>Data were entered into SPSS (version 20, IBM Corp. in Armonk, NY) for main analyses and into R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) for confirmatory analyses. Problems addressed were listed. Analysis was based on participant level data, clustered within sites. Outcome variables were analysed using generalized linear mixed effects models with an indicator of profile use, baseline data on age, number of medicines prescribed, prescription of antipsychotics, antiepileptics, antidepressants and SSRIs, (detailed in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), and data collection step considered as fixed explanatory variables. We considered separate models for each variable of interest. We used normal models for interval variables and binary logistic regression models for binary data. In each model, site was entered as a random effect variable; this formally accommodated the observed ICCs in our data. The effect of the intervention is reported as adjusted mean differences (&#x003b2; for interval variables) or adjusted odds ratios (aOR for binary variables) taken from models which retain statistically significant covariates and factors from the list above. Inferential statistics were confined to composite outcomes (numbers of problem found and addressed, changes in prescribing, measures of illness severity) and examples of the nature of the problems addressed selected for clinical importance (pain, falls, sedation).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Recruitment, Retention, Demographics and Prescription medicines at study entry.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 1</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 2</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 3</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 4</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site 5</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full sample</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Recruitment</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number eligible</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number starting trial</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Retention</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number completing</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Demographics</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number female</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age: mean [SD] in years</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.60 [7.89]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69 [12.14]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.40 [6.99]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.90 [6.49]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.00 [9.65]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.7 [11.00]</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age: median [25<sup>th</sup>&#x02013;75<sup>th</sup> centile]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5 [65.5&#x02013;80.75]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 [60.25&#x02013;83.25]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 [82&#x02013;92.5]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87 [81&#x02013;91.25]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.5 [71.5&#x02013;88.5]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80 [67&#x02013;88]</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range (min-max)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63&#x02013;84</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#x02013;88</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76&#x02013;95</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75&#x02013;96</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66&#x02013;94</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58&#x02013;96</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number registered for nursing care<xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Prescribed medicines</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD] number of medicines<xref rid="t001fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>/ participant</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8 [3.4]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1 [3.9]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.6 [1.1]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.1 [4.2]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 [3.1]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.3[3.7]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median [25<sup>th</sup>&#x02013;75<sup>th</sup> centile] number of medicines/participant</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 [4&#x02013;9.3]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 [9&#x02013;13.3]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 [8.5&#x02013;10.5]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 [6.5&#x02013;11.8]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5 [7.5&#x02013;13.5]</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 [7&#x02013;11]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range (min-max)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;19</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;19</td></tr><tr><td colspan="7" align="justify" rowspan="1">Number of participants prescribed:</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipsychotics</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidepressants (not SSRIs)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antiepileptics</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSRIs</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>* Categorisation follows a needs assessment. Service users are assessed by NHS nurses and designated as needing nursing care or residential care. Assessments are usually based on the Royal College of Nursing&#x02019;s (2004) &#x02018;Nursing assessment and Older People An RCN Toolkit&#x02019;. London, RCN: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcn.org.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0010/78616/002310.pdf">http://www.rcn.org.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0010/78616/002310.pdf</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>
<bold>**</bold> Any combination preparations were counted as a single item. Enumerating the active ingredients of each product would have been impractical, particularly for antacids and multivitamins.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Some problems could not be addressed within the month between data collection steps, most particularly visits to opticians and dentists, where NHS access can take several weeks. To account for the delayed effects of treatment, we analysed data on opticians&#x02019; and dentists&#x02019; visits from first and last collection steps, thus effectively undertaking &#x02018;before and after&#x02019; analyses of numbers accessing these services within the last year; we retained all other aspects of the modelling strategy, including a random effects variable for site. We undertook standard model and residual diagnostics where appropriate; presentation of the analyses reflects joint decisions by two authors. Case vignettes are presented for illustration.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>Ethics</title><p>The study was explained to all potential participants and, where possible, their families, supplemented by written information, in English and Welsh. Residents&#x02019; or consultees&#x02019; consent for researchers to review participants&#x02019; notes for information directly relevant to medicines&#x02019; use was sought by qualified nurses, who were familiar with the Mental Capacity Act (2005)[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>] and employed by the site. Since this was a cluster RCT[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], and the research only involved excerpting non-identifiable data from records, where the participant lacked capacity, the REC considered it appropriate for qualified site staff to take verbal consent/ assent, witnessed by a signatory outside the research team[7:16,68:34]. Participants&#x02019; General Practitioners (GPs) were informed of the project by letter. Usual standard care was delivered throughout. To cover the time spent in recruiting participants and administering the measures of functioning and dementia severity, sites received honoraria. Honoraria were not intended to cover administration of the Profile, as the questions posed were those that should be asked in routine care.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Findings</title><p>Five of 10 sites declined to participate; &#x02018;pressure of work&#x02019; was the only explanation offered. Of the 181 service users, 49 met inclusion criteria, and 43 consented to participate. In care home 5, 2 joined late. Nurses indicated that all participants lacked capacity to consent, and consent was obtained from consultees. We retained 41 of the 43 service users: one died, and one did not return from hospital, all before introduction of the Profile. Recruitment is summarized in <xref rid="pone.0140203.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, and retention in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p><fig id="pone.0140203.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Numbers in the analysis.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0140203.g001"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Patient monitoring: number of participants with documentation of each problem.</title><p>2 participants joined late and 2 were lost to the study.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="justify" rowspan="1">Step 1 baseline no Profiles n = 41</th><th colspan="3" align="justify" rowspan="1">Step 6 all participants use Profile n = 41</th></tr><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acceptable ranges<xref rid="t002fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem n(%)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No problem n(%)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not monitored n(%)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem n(%)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No problem n(%)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not monitored n(%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Vital signs</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55&#x02013;90bpm</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (68.3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (31.7)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (73.2)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (22.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rhythm</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No irregularity</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (97.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21 (51.2)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (46.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BP&#x02013; 2 position for postural hypotension</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Systolic drops &#x0003c;20mmHg or 10% on standing</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (19.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (56.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (24.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (17.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (61.0)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (22.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change of &#x0003c;2.4kg in 1 month</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 (46.3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (48.8)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (41.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (53.7)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girth</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;88cms in women, &#x0003c;102cms. in men</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (100)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (34.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (56.1)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.8 &#x000b1; 0.4&#x000b0;C</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (9.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (75.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (7.3)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (43.9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (48.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen saturation</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;97%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (24.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (43.9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (31.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Intake</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluids</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;1.2L + 1L taken within solid food</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (34.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (63.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (17.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (80.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missed meals</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1 meal unfinished / day</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (41.5)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (43.9)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (34.2)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (61)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (4.9)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Medicines&#x02019; administration</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missed doses</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;2 doses of prescribed medicines missed over any period of 7 days in the last month (including refusal)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (12.2)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (85.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (85.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular administration</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular medication taken at same time each day</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (14.6)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (85.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (95.1)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (2.4)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>* Guidelines appended to the Profile offered definitions of acceptable ranges of measurement and standards. Guidelines are available on request.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>At trial entry, 27/43 (62.8%) participants were receiving residential care, and 16 nursing care; 25/43 (58.1%) were female. Participants&#x02019; ages ranged 58&#x02013;96, mean 78.7 [SD 11.00], median 80 [IQR 67&#x02013;88].</p><p>Of the 43 participants, 39 had a recorded primary diagnosis of dementia (including alcohol-related, vascular, Alzheimer&#x02019;s, fronto-temporal), two were diagnosed with Korsakoff&#x02019;s syndrome, and two with depression, but not dementia. A diagnosis of depression was recorded for 7 participants (five with co-morbid depression where primary diagnosis was dementia), and 27 were prescribed antidepressants. Prescribing patterns were not uniform in the 5 sites: more participants were prescribed antiepileptics in site 2; site 5 used more SSRIs and fewer antipsychotics (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Participants were prescribed between 2 and 19 medicines, (median 9 [<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], mean 9.3 [SD 3.7]), including treatments for physical health conditions.</p><p>Profile completion and all cross-over to Profile use was as scheduled. Laboratory test results were often unavailable, as they were held by participants&#x02019; GPs. Monitoring of vital signs, food and fluid intake and medicines&#x02019; administration increased on introduction of the Profile, and was sustained at the close of the trial. Before Profile introduction, fluid and food intake and medicines&#x02019; administration were monitored for ~50% participants; this rose to &#x0003e;95% of participants when all sites used the Profile. However, compliance with vital signs&#x02019; monitoring was incomplete, particularly for heart rhythm, girth and temperature (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Some nurses reported insufficient time to complete physiological measurements. Nine participants were unable to stand, precluding measurement of standing BP.</p><sec id="sec024"><title>1. Clinical impact</title><sec id="sec025"><title>a. Problems found and addressed</title><p>More problems were found and actions taken when the Profile was used (Tables <xref rid="pone.0140203.t003" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t004" ref-type="table">4</xref>). More problems were found than were addressed. Most problems were actioned more frequently with than without the Profile, particularly balance/ co-ordination, cognitive decline, violence, aggression, mood fluctuations, behaviour problems, restlessness, confusion, apathy, hallucinations, sedation, headache, hearing problems, hypersalivation, emesis, missed meals, inadequate fluid intake, vision problems, pain and missed medicines; the exceptions were changes in weight, insomnia and bowel control. Typically, nurses modified care plans and made referrals (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). In some cases, problems such as incontinence, were long-standing and considered intractable. The sharp and sustained increase in problem detection at first use of the Profile in all sites (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) was not reflected in actions taken to address problems in all sites: in sites 2,4 and 5 the mean number of problems addressed more than doubled, whereas little change was seen in site 1, and there was a slight decrease in site 3 (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Total number of problems found per participant at each step and in each site.</title><p>Bold text indicates roll-out of medicines&#x02019; monitoring and Profile administration 1 month before these data collection points (occasions when researchers extracted data from participants&#x02019; records). n = number of service users in the site. One participant from site 4 passed away between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. One participant from site 5 was hospitalised between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. Participants joined site 5 at steps 2 and 3. Problems explored are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> and on the Profile, <xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 appendix</xref>. Fuller versions of these tables, including medians and 25<sup>th</sup> = 75<sup>th</sup> centiles are in <xref rid="pone.0140203.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> Tables.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Total number of problems found</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 3.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 5.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 6.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.38 [2.00]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.78 [1.92]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.50 [2.32]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.70 [3.65]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.40 [3.89]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16.50 [6.59]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1&#x02013;24</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.10 [3.81]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.20 [2.49]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00 [2.63]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56 [2.30]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>18.33 [7.57]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>19.11[6.79]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7&#x02013;27</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x02013;5</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20 [4.09]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60 [2.30]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80 [4.32]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.60 [2.07]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9.40 [1.14]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.20 [2.39]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8&#x02013;13</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8&#x02013;11</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9&#x02013;15</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.13 [3.72]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.38 [3.58]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>15.75 [6.94]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.75 [5.90]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.88 [6.31]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>14.38 [5.73]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5&#x02013;28</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5&#x02013;24</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5&#x02013;22</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9&#x02013;28</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.30 [2.21]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>17.30 [6.08]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>17.30 [6.09]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>17.00 [5.25]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>16.50 [5.19]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>17.10 [4.61]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10&#x02013;25</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;25</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;26</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5&#x02013;23</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;23</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Total number of problems addressed per participant at each step in each site.</title><p>Bold text indicates roll-out of medicines&#x02019; monitoring and Profile administration 1 month before these data collection points (occasions when researchers extracted data from participants&#x02019; records). n = number of service users in the site. One participant from site 4 passed away between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. One participant from site 5 was hospitalised between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. Participants joined site 5 at steps 2 and 3. Problems explored are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> and on the Profile, <xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 appendix</xref>. Fuller versions of these tables, including medians and 25<sup>th</sup> = 75<sup>th</sup> centiles are in <xref rid="pone.0140203.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2</xref> tables.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Total number of problems addressed</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 3.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 5.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 6.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.25 [1.67]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.89 [1.90]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30 [2.41]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 [2.83]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.40 [2.22]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.70[4.97]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>91&#x02013;21</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.50 [3.44]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.90 [2.47]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.60 [2.27]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.44 [2.24]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.00 [4.61]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.78 [4.68]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;19</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;19</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00 [2.92]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80 [1.92]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00 [4.18]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4.60 [1.34]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4.60 [1.52]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6.20 [2.17]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;6</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;7</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0&#x02013;6</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25 [3.37]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 [3.12]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.50 [4.38]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8.88 [4.61]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7.88 [5.17]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.13 [5.19]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;18</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;17</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;16</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4&#x02013;22</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1:</bold> n</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.30 [2.63]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8.60 [2.99]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9.80 [3.62]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.10 [3.41]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.80 [4.57]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.70[4.72]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5&#x02013;14</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;14</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4&#x02013;16</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3&#x02013;18</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4&#x02013;20</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Problems addressed with and without the Profile: total numbers and examples.</title><p>Visits to dentists and opticians were compared &#x02018;before and after&#x02019; (see analysis and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). ADLs&#x02014;activities of daily living.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t005g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problem</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Using Profile -124 data collection points</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Without the Profile&#x02014;125 data collection points</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Examples of Typical actions</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heart rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP informed</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irregular rhythm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None when identified</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BP</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily recordings. GP informed.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight / BMI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to encourage/ discourage intake.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Girth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan for weight loss</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional blankets offered</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oxygen sats</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP contacted</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ECG</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 recording, no problems</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand tremor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans for Parkinson&#x02019;s and carpal tunnel</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tongue tremor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No actions</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feet shuffling</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans to address risk of falls</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abnormal movements</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans and medication</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posture abnormal</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">occupational therapy referral</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gait abnormal on walking</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">occupational therapy referral</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Balance abnormal/ co-ordination poor &#x00026; interferes with ADLs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans for staff to assist with mobility and address risk of falling</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding or bruising</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Charting and monitoring. Care plan for polyps.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Feeling the cold</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Extra blankets</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cognitive decline</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans for staff to offer assistance</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Convulsions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan updated. Specialist referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-harm</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan updated</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Violence</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reports to mental health team</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aggression</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported to mental health team, and medication to be continued.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irritability</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to improve explanations. Linked to constipation and UTI.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mood fluctuations</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans to reassurance and encourage. Medication review and changes.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agitation, anxiety, nervousness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to reduce anxiety with music and reassurance. Medical review.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behaviour problems e.g. &#x02018;sexualised behaviour&#x02019;</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans to offer reassurance. Mental health review.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Restlessness or pacing</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health team to review patient and /or medicines.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hyperactivity</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan modified.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Panic attacks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan for management.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Confusion</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan for orientation, GP or mental health referral. MSU for analysis</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">apathy, low energy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encourage intake. GP review.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hallucinations, vivid dreams</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to monitor and reassure. Mental health review. UTI treatment.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sleep problems/ insomnia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to deal with wakefulness.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sedation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral. Omission of mid-day sedation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diszziness</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk of falls assessed. BP monitored.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falls</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans for assistance, hoists, lighting at night, mobilising. GP referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Headache, migraine</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Analgesia</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tinnitus/hearing problems</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Encouraged to wear hearing aid. Syringing.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tingling/pins &#x00026; needles</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Referred to doctor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urination</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Continence management. Care plan for retention management. Medical review.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UTI</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antibiotics</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproductive system e.g. polyps, behaviour change</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral and directed management</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chest pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Short of breath</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Managed as asthma or chest infection</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypersalivation/</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Monitored for chest infection. Hyoscine patch.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea / vomiting</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP or dietician referral. PRN medicines.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Appetite/ taste changes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dietician referral. Care plan for assistance with feeding.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bowel control/ diarrhoea</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans for incontinence. Stool charts.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constipation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plans to monitor. Laxatives.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rash (+/- itching)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Creams applied. GP referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swelling/ oedema / pressure areas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waterlow scores, GP referral</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sweating / pressure areas</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enhanced skin care in care plan</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Injection site e.g. pain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No injections</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Missing any meals or leaving them unfinished more than once a day</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to monitor or for soft diet or frequent small meals or offer alternatives e.g. milk. Dietician referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02018;Snacking&#x02019; or eating between meals</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low fat diet.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking 1 pint or more of milk or soya milk per day. This includes milk added to cereal &#x00026; hot drinks</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Milk drinks to be offered between meals. Soya offered.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vitamin D intake adequate (time in sunlight, eats oily fish)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diet updated.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eating fruit or vegetables every day</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to encourage</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drinking more than 2 litres, or 6&#x02013;8 cups, per day. This includes water, tea, coffee or squash</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to encourage and monitor</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are drinks sugar free?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Access to sugar-free drinks</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swallowing difficulties</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SALT referral, assistance with eating.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indigestion or heartburn</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral. Medication.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Problems with teeth or dentures</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouth care. Dental referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry mouth</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mouth care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Halitosis</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dental referral</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vision problems or dry eyes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Optician referral, gel for dry eyes, large print</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is sunscreen available?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not used</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Is it applied evenly?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not used</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dark glasses worn in bright sunlight?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Available</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hair loss</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral for scalp problems</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acne or <italic>Herpes simplex</italic> reactivation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not noted</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Any pain? e.g. joint pain, headache</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Care plan to monitor non-verbal clues and pain charts. Analgesia. Dental referral.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regular medication taken at the same time each day</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not actioned.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">More than 2 doses of prescribed medication missed over any period of seven days in the last month?</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GP referral. Medicines changed to liquid formulations.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>In adjusted analyses, more problems were found (adjusted mean difference 9.06 [95% CI 7.95&#x02013;10.16]), and addressed (adjusted mean difference 3.34 [2.57&#x02013;4.11]) when the Profile was used. These increases were also associated with older age and higher number of prescription medicines at baseline. Number of problems addressed varied with trial step, and was significantly lower in steps 2&#x02013;5, when Profile use and other factors were accounted (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t006</object-id><label>Table 6</label><caption><title>Profile Effect on selected outcomes: adjusted analyses.</title><p>Notes: D = raw, observed (unadjusted) difference in the same units as the variable; &#x003b2; = &#x003b2; coefficient of profile effect or effect size in the same units as variable; OR = raw (unadjusted odds ratio); aOR = adjusted Odds Ratio, exponent of &#x003b2;. ADL = activities of daily living. n represents the number of data collection points.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t006g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without profile</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">With profile</th><th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Profile Effect</th><th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">95% CI for Adjusted Effect</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICC<xref rid="t006fn002" ref-type="table-fn">**</xref>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significant covariates</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P values</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted effect, parameters, &#x003b2; or aOR (95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Primary outcomes</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adjusted<xref rid="t006fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lower</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Upper</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total Problems</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 1.82 (0.51&#x02013;3.13)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Found</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = -1.24 (-2.36&#x02013;-0.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (sd)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.52(6.36)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30(3.18)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.81(5.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D = 8.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 9.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 0.16 (0.06&#x02013;0.27)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[n]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[249]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[125]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[124]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of medicines prescribed<xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 0.36 (0.13&#x02013;0.60)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Total Problems</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = -2.08 (-3.02&#x02013;1.14)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Addressed</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = -1.04 (-1.96&#x02013;-0.12)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (sd)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.93(4.23)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02(2.92)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.86(4.48)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D = 3.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 3.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = -2.45 (-3.34&#x02013;1.52)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[n]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[249]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[125]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[n = 124]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 5</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = -1.72 (-2.67&#x02013;0.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 0.14 (0.05&#x02013;0.22)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of medicines prescribed<xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 0.26 (0.08&#x02013;0.45)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Secondary outcomes</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Mental health Medicines Reduction</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18/208(8.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/84(3.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/124(12.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 3.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 4.45(P = 0.03)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of medicines prescribed<xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 1.17 (1.01&#x02013;1.35)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>MOUSEPAD</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (sd)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.53(6.47)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.31(6.90)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.76(6.04)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D = 0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antipsychotics at</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 4.22 (0.37&#x02013;8.07)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[n]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[249]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[125]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[124]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">baseline</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Bristol (ADL) Score</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean (sd)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.13(14.48)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.81(14.52)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.48(14.11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D = 4.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2; = 1.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[n]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[249]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[125]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[124]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.06)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Examples of nature of problems addressed</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Falls Action</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34/125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32/124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 0.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 0.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(27.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.407)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Falls</bold> Documented</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66/249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 0.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 0.62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">none</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(26.5%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(28.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(25.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.22)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pain Actions</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79/249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24/125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55/124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 3.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 3.84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 0.33 (0.11&#x02013;1.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion(%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(31.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(19.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(44.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of medicines prescribed<xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 1.23 (1.06&#x02013;1.43)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Pain Documented</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80/249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25/125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55/124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 3.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 3.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 0.32 (0.11&#x02013;0.96)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(32.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(20.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(44.4%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of medicines prescribed<xref rid="t006fn003" ref-type="table-fn">&#x02020;</xref>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 1.23 (1.07&#x02013;1.43)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Sedation Documented</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/125</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28/124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 4.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 8.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 1.08 (1.01&#x02013;1.16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(14.1%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(5.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(22.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Before and after analyses</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Optician Visit</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64/82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27/41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37/41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 4.796</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 5.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(78.0%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(65.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(90.2%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P = 0.01)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Dentist Visit</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35/82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31/41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR = 28.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aOR = 52.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235.90</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r = 0.122</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(42.7%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9.8%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(75.6%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(P&#x0003c;0.001)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t006fn001"><p>* adjusted for Step, age, number of medicines at baseline, antipsychotics, antiepileptics, antidepressants and SSRIs at baseline;</p></fn><fn id="t006fn002"><p>** ICC, intracluster correlation coefficient, based on raw data;</p></fn><fn id="t006fn003"><p>&#x02020; number of medicines recorded as prescribed at baseline.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec026"><title>b. Benefits</title><p>The Profile affected the care of most, but not all, participants. We identified clinical impact and specific examples, guided by previous work[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Some actions related to direct intervention to manage symptoms, such as referral for GI symptoms (P20, <xref rid="pone.0140203.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>) or increased pain relief, whilst others related to health promotion, for example changes to diet and mouth care. These items were important to address some of the nuanced effects of ADRs. The intervention increased visits to dentists and opticians. At baseline, 4 had visited dentists and 27 opticians, within the last 12 months. By the final step, this had increased to 31 and 37, in association with Profile use (aOR 52.76 [11.80&#x02013;235.90] and 5.12 [1.45&#x02013;18.03] respectively). The importance of this is illustrated by P2 (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t007</object-id><label>Table 7</label><caption><title>Case Reports of benefits of Profile use.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t007g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Participant number</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theme</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Report</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigating poor intake</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A lady in her mid 90s with a diagnosis of mild to moderate dementia was prescribed: ranitidine, aspirin, furosemide, simvastatin, levothyroxine, zopiclone, ramipril, sodium valproate as Epilim<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>. On the second use of the Profile, abdominal pain was identified as a possible cause of irregular dietary/ food intake. This was followed up with the GP, and the participant was investigated for gastro-intestinal ulceration.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Investigating poor intake</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A gentleman of in his mid 70s with a diagnosis of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, ischaemic heart disease, and arthritis had no record of problems with dietary intake or dentists&#x02019; visits before the Profile was introduced. On first use, the Profile identified dental problems, poor intake and missed or unfinished meals. A dental appointment was then arranged, and the dentist needed to extract a decayed tooth. On subsequent assessments, meals were no longer missed, fruit and milk intake had improved and sugary drinks were no longer used.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P19</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognising ADRs</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A lady in her late 80s with a diagnosis of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease was prescribed mirtazapine, lactulose, senna, diazepam, aspirin, omeprazole, folic acid, alendronic acid, vitamin D supplements as Calcichew D3 forte<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>, simvastatin, and risperidone as needed. Initial monitoring (Step 4) indicated several problems including: cognitive decline, violence, aggression, agitation, hallucinations, risk of falls, problems with dentures, and pain. The nursing team were proactive in discontinuing risperidone, and violence, aggression, agitation, hallucinations, falls, denture problems and pain resolved. One month later, the potential problem of falls was incorporated into the personalised care plans for the first time, triggering discontinuation of diazepam.</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recognising ADRs</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A lady in her late 80s, diagnosed with dementia was prescribed hyoscine as needed, oxazepam, carbamazepine, omeprazole, levomepromazine, senna, magnesium hydroxide, and paracetamol. At first administration of the Profile (Step 3), she was noted to be aggressive, restless, confused, sedated and agitated. In accordance with Profile guidelines, hyoscine had been discontinued by Step 4. By the end of the study, aggression, restlessness and sedation were no longer recorded as problematic. The potential for falls was recorded on the Profile, but not elsewhere in the records.</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Eleven participants reported falls in the first step of data collection, and six in the final step. Profile use did not alter reporting and addressing falls (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>), but more care plans were put in place to address problems with balance (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><p>Nurses were more likely to document and treat pain when using the Profile. At baseline, 11/41 participants had their pain status documented; this increased to 40/41 in the last step. Fewer participants reported being in pain: 9 and 4 respectively. Without the Profile 1/41 participants received new analgesia; with the Profile this increased to 9/41, and ranged from transdermal fentanyl to liquid paracetamol. Use of the Profile increased pain-related documentation and actions (aOR 3.45 [1.63&#x02013;7.30] and 3.84 [1.78&#x02013;8.30] and 1.80&#x02013;7.78) (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). Similar large increases in actions taken were seen for problems with balance, cognitive decline, irritability, mood fluctuations, behaviour problems, restlessness, confusion, apathy, hallucinations, sedation, headache, emesis, missed meals, fluid intake, vision problems, and missed medicines. There was little change in actions for weight and girth combined, aggression, falls, and incontinence. Other problems were less frequent (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><p>The Profile allowed relatively unusual problems to be identified and addressed. Examples included: a new hearing problem (P9), which resolved on ear syringing; nausea (P12), which resolved when the daily dose of lactulose was divided; difficulties with urination which triggered a prescription for tamsulosin (P33); identification of gastro-intestinal ulceration (P20, <xref rid="pone.0140203.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec027"><title>c. Prescription changes</title><p>Neither medication reviews nor documentation of ADRs were located in patients&#x02019; documentation. Introduction of the Profile did not influence the total numbers of medicines prescribed, due in part to the increase in analgesia, above, and there was a small increase over time (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t008" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref>). The baseline differences between the sites did not reach statistical significance. Although there were no overall changes in total medicines prescribed, the numbers of participants with any change increased throughout the trial (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t009" ref-type="table">Table 9</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t008</object-id><label>Table 8</label><caption><title>Number of prescribed medicines in each step for each site.</title><p>Bold text indicates roll-out of medicines&#x02019; monitoring and Profile administration 1 month before these data collection points (occasions when researchers extracted data from participants&#x02019; records). n = number of service users in the site. One participant from site 4 passed away between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. One participant from site 5 was hospitalised between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. Participants joined site 5 at steps 2 and 3. Problems explored are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> and on the Profile, <xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>. Fuller versions of these tables, including medians and 25<sup>th</sup> = 75<sup>th</sup> centiles are in <xref rid="pone.0140203.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 table</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t008g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t008"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Number of prescribed medicines</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 3.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 5.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 6.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5:</bold> Sum (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>115 (9)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.63[3.07]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.67 [3.16]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.90 [3.28]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.67 [2.92]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.00 [3.12]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>12.78[40.6]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7&#x02013;16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;19</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4:</bold> Sum (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>98 (9)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>101 (9)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.10 [4.23]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.30 [4.24]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60 [3.95]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.22 [4.30]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.89 [4.83]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.22 [4.06]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4&#x02013;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;21</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7&#x02013;18</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3:</bold> Sum (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>50 (5)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>49 (5)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>49 (5)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60 [1.14]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00 [2.00]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.80 [1.79]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.00 [1.23]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9.80 [1.30]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>9.80 [1.30]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8&#x02013;12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8&#x02013;11</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8&#x02013;11</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8&#x02013;11</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2:</bold> Sum (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (8)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>89 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>88 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>85 (8)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>89 (8)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.13 [3.91]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.13 [4.29]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.13 [3.56]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.00 [3.21]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>10.63 [3.29]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>11.13 [3.56]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6&#x02013;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;18</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;17</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;17</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6&#x02013;18</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1:</bold> Sum (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>72 (10)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>72 (10)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>71 (10)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>70 (10)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>84 (10)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean [SD]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.80 [3.36]</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7.20 [3.33]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7.20 [3.49]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7.10 [3.35]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7.00 [3.50]</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8.40 [3.98]</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Full range</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2&#x02013;13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;13</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;13</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;13</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;14</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2&#x02013;14</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0140203.t009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.t009</object-id><label>Table 9</label><caption><title>Numbers of participants with any change made to any of their prescribed medications at each step in each site.</title><p>Bold text indicates roll-out of medicines&#x02019; monitoring and Profile administration 1 month before these data collection points (occasions when researchers extracted data from participants&#x02019; records). n = number of service users in the site. One participant from site 4 passed away between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. One participant from site 5 was hospitalised between steps 3 &#x00026; 4. Participants joined site 5 at steps 2 and 3. Problems explored are listed in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref> and on the Profile, <xref rid="pone.0140203.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Appendix</xref>. Fuller versions of these tables, including medians and 25<sup>th</sup> = 75<sup>th</sup> centiles are in <xref rid="pone.0140203.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0140203.t009g" xlink:href="pone.0140203.t009"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</th><th colspan="6" align="center" rowspan="1">Number with changes to prescribed medicines</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 1.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 2.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 3.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 4.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 5.</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Step 6.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5:</bold> n/N (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/9 (11%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/10 (10%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/9 (78%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/9 (78%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6/9 (67%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4:</bold> n/N (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/10 (30%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5/10 (50%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/9 (67%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>7/9 (78%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>8/9 (89%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3:</bold> n/N (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5 (20%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/5 (20%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3/5 (60%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1/5 (20%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4/5 (80%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2:</bold> n/N (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/8(25%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5/8 (63%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6/8 (75%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4/8 (50%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>5/8 (63%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1:</bold> n/N (%)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1/10 (10%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4/10 (40%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>3/10 (30%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>4/10 (40%)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>6/10 (60%)</bold>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>During the trial there were 18 reductions in mental health medicines affecting 12 service users: 10 while using the Profile, 1 without the Profile, and 1 both with and without. (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref> contains two examples). Reduction in participants&#x02019; mental health medicines was associated with Profile use (aOR 4.45 [1.15&#x02013;17.22]) and the number of prescription medicines at baseline (aOR 1.17 [1.01&#x02013;1.35} per medicine) (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p><p>At baseline, 3/41 participants had sedation levels documented, and recording was complete by the final step. Three participants had their sedatives reduced (trazodone, lorazepam, risperidone).</p></sec><sec id="sec028"><title>d. Functional status and dementia severity</title><p>By the end of the study, Bristol ADL scores and the MOUSEPAD measure of dementia behavioural and psychological symptoms had deteriorated slightly. Changes were not statistically significantly associated with Profile use: Deterioration in dementia severity was associated with antipsychotic prescription at baseline (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec029"><title>2. Potential Costs</title><p>The direct cost of Profile administration was typically 15&#x02013;30 minutes time from band 5 nurses, the starting point for newly registered qualified nurses, an estimated &#x000a3;20.50 ($31.5, &#x020ac;28.2), based on salary costs of &#x000a3;41 per hour[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Some nurses needed an hour to read through the guidelines carefully before first administration, and administration times ranged 10&#x02013;60 minutes, costing &#x000a3;7&#x02013;41 ($10.8&#x02013;63.0, &#x020ac;9.6&#x02013;56.4). Administration times were shorter when nurses had familiarised themselves with the appended guidelines. Addressing problems or care deficits identified by the Profile entailed indirect costs: for example, referrals and visits to opticians and dentist increased in association with the intervention. A visit to the community dentist is estimated to cost &#x000a3;115 ($176.7, &#x020ac;158.2) and an optician &#x000a3;21 ($32.3, &#x020ac;28.9)[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Some prescribing changed, but no changes in high cost medicines were observed.</p><p>Potential savings were identified. Improved vision, following opticians&#x02019; input, combined with reduction of medicines such as diazepam and antipsychotics, which are associated with dizziness, falls and fractures[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>], could lead to savings by reducing falls. The costs of pain, sedation, poor oral hygiene and poor eyesight, and their amelioration, are hard to quantify, but may affect Health Related Quality of Life.</p></sec><sec id="sec030"><title>3. Harms</title><p>Implementation of the WWADR Profile was neither observed nor reported to be directly harmful, and Bristol ADL and MOUSEPAD scores did not deteriorate significantly. The research entailed no more than minimal risk, defined as clinical examination and record review[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]: the Profile has been freely available in the public domain since 2004[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and all questions and observations are of a nature that should be pursued under routine care. The time taken identifying and responding to problems may have distracted nurses from other tasks, but prioritisation of actions was at the discretion of the multidisciplinary team. Medicines were changed in response to needs identified. Neither participants nor their families reported negatively on the amount of time spent in completing the WWADR Profile. At recruitment, pressure of existing work was cited by nurse managers, acting as gatekeepers, as their reason for non-participation; without further information from sites not involved, it is difficult to explore how this might relate to the 30 minutes needed to administer the Profile.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec031"><title>Discussion</title><p>To our knowledge, no previous trials have tested nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring interventions in a cohort stepped wedge cluster RCT. Our intervention increased the numbers of problems identified and addressed, improved pain management, and reduced prescriptions of mental health medicines. We identified potential to augment quality and safety of care and reduce costs.</p><sec id="sec032"><title>Strengths and Limitations</title><p>
<bold>Generalisability</bold> of findings is supported by consistency across the majority of trial sites, low attrition, and with earlier work[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], with the <italic>caveats</italic> that those too ill to undergo measurements of vital signs were excluded, and all sites had pre-existing contact with the University and were in an area of the European Union (EU) where GDP is 75% below the community average[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. The site (3) with the lowest recruitment and oldest participants (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) addressed fewer problems but changed more medicines than others (Tables <xref rid="pone.0140203.t004" ref-type="table">4</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t009" ref-type="table">9</xref>), and completion of some items relied on nurses&#x02019; intimate knowledge of participants who lacked the cognitive ability to understand questions, suggesting that clinical gains may vary between settings. International transferability of findings rests with readers&#x02019; interpretations. Prescribing patterns, including number of medicines prescribed (median 9, range 2&#x02013;19) reflects previous reports[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]. The 50% recruitment rate for sites warrants cautious generalisation of findings to care homes feeling too pressurised to participate in research. Any association with nurses&#x02019; self-reported lack of confidence in medicines&#x02019; management[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] or the requirement for the Profile to be administered is uncertain. Volunteer[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>] and selection[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] bias within sites was minimised by the high participation rate. This was attributed to the REC&#x02019;s support for witnessed verbal assent to participation, in accordance with the Ottawa statement[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], to avoid overburdening participants&#x02019; relatives, many of whom were frail and elderly[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p><p>Nursing work that is unrecorded is regarded as incomplete or &#x02018;not done&#x02019;[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. However, some observations and actions, particularly vital signs (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), were <bold>incompletely documented</bold>, despite the known risk of hypotension associated with antipsychotics[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>] and antidepressants[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]., and communications&#x02019; systems did not facilitate transfer of laboratory results. However, care homes&#x02019; records are regularly inspected by licensing authorities (CSSIW), ensuring that all medicines administered are fully and accurately recorded. We think it unlikely that social desirability responses or the Hawthorne[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>] effect would have affected nurses&#x02019; completion of documentation unevenly across trial sites and steps.</p><p>We acknowledge the potential for &#x0201c;<bold>exposure suspicion bias</bold>&#x0201d; [80:55] to increase the numbers of problems recorded. Conversely, some problems, such as poor balance or gait may be overlooked or accepted as integral to participants&#x02019; conditions. Such &#x0201c;entrapment by prior expectations&#x0201d; [81:38] may affect profiling of ADRs[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], but is likely to have been consistent throughout the trial. We anticipated some fluctuations in recording over time, because signs and symptoms change. For example, bruises appear, eating patterns alter, and if people become dehydrated, due to changes in temperature, intake or infection, drug elimination decreases, worsening any ADRs.</p><p>
<bold>Blinding</bold> during administration, data capture and outcome assessment in non-pharmacological[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref082" ref-type="bibr">82</xref>], cluster[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>] or pragmatic trials may be impossible[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref083" ref-type="bibr">83</xref>], increasing risk of bias[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>], in line with observers&#x02019; expectations[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Nurses and some, but not all, participants were aware of administration of the Profile. The presence of the Profiles in the notes precluded blinding during data collection, and the obvious increase in problem detection with the Profile (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>) was apparent to data analysts. Detection bias of outcomes was minimised, but not removed, by a pre-arranged data collection template and the low subjectivity of outcome data extracted from standardised documentation, such as medicines&#x02019; administration records or nutrition assessments[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Systematic review indicates that some 3% unblinded assessments are likely to be misclassified[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], which would not materially affect interpretation of our findings.</p><p>
<bold>Contamination</bold> by subconscious transfer of aspects of an intervention to controls may dilute its effects[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. Introduction of the study before implementation may have sensitised staff to medicines&#x02019; management, and medicine changes increased before use of the Profile in sites 4 &#x00026; 5 (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). The sites were unlikely to have discussed the trial as they were geographically dispersed and all nurses worked at only one site.</p><p>
<bold>Global outcome measures</bold> may be better suited to population comparisons than clinical trials, as they appear to be insufficiently sensitive to prescription changes[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>], and subtle but important improvements, such as increased oral hygiene and analgesia. Therefore, interventions to optimize prescribing, identification and resolution of medication-related problems or pain may not influence scores on global outcome measures[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. While nurse-led and pharmacist-led interventions improve prescribing[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>], mainly in patients not receiving specialist care[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>], they may not change global outcome measures[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>]. Although care improved, for example by reducing prescribing of sedatives and increasing administration of analgesia, global measures did not. Scores for activity of daily living (Bristol ADL) and psychopathology (MOUSEPAD) remained unchanged; however, participants were suffering from dementia, which would normally deteriorate over 5&#x02013;6 months. The ambivalence between auditable processes of care, such as medication administration[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] and global outcomes, such as levels of functioning, reflects the inconsistency in the links between the processes and outcomes of care.</p><p>The risks of <bold>multiple testing</bold> were balanced against the benefits of formalising the significance of observed differences. We did not apply statistical tests to all items that could have been actioned, and the observed differences (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>) should be considered together with the formal analyses presented in <xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec033"><title>Addressing the ADR Problem</title><sec id="sec034"><title>1. Clinical gains</title><p>Dose titration for people with dementia is challenging: medicating the neuropsychiatric symptoms of dementia is of uncertain benefit[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>], and antipsychotics are not recommended unless other measures have failed and then only for short-term administration[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Routine administration of a structured, standardised instrument was a low risk strategy to facilitate medication titration and compensate for any under-ascertainment of ADRs or under-treatment due to patients&#x02019; impaired communication. It was also successful in enhancing care planning to address nursing needs, such as poor fluid intake, missed meals and behaviour problems[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>] (Tables <xref rid="pone.0140203.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p>Some 15% of older adults in the UK are prescribed at least 1 potentially inappropriate medicine[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>], and medicines&#x02019; management is crucial to the optimisation of long-term conditions and avoidance of harm. However, many ADRs are subtle and ill-defined, and signs and symptoms, such as cognitive impairment[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>] or impaired continence[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], may resemble pre-existing conditions or ageing or dehydration. Their aetiology is often multifactorial or uncertain[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]: for example, cognitive impairment may reduce fluid intake[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>], exacerbating urinary symptoms and constipation[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>], which are also ADRs to antidepressants, benzodiazepines and antipsychotics[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Determination of aetiology for each problem or assessment of appropriateness of prescribing is outside the remit of the Profile. For example: xerostomia warrants nursing or dental interventions whether due to dehydration, antipsychotics, SSRIs, AEDs, benzodiazepines or anti-muscarinics; similarly, confusion should be brought to the attention of prescribers whether due to dementia, or caused or exacerbated by cardiovascular agents, antipsychotics, SSRIs, AEDs, benzodiazepines or anti-muscarinics[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Rather, by addressing the diverse problems vulnerable to exacerbation by prescribed medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>], the Profile works towards incremental optimisation of health. In view of the paucity of the evidence base on potential adverse drug reactions[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>], to optimise clinical gain, the Profile makes a thorough and detailed check for potential medication-related harms, risking over-ascertainment, rather than overlooking potentially treatable problems of equivocal aetiology. Interpretation of such inclusivity rests with readers. The diversity of problems identified and addressed suggests there may be some merit in compiling a single Profile of problems ahead of physician or pharmacist review.</p><p>Previously, introduction of nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring expedited the recognition and treatment of unsuspected problems, such as orthostatic hypotension, coupled beats, hypertension, constipation, and inadequate diet[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], need for medication review, immunisations[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], suboptimal oral care, pain and sedation[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Including a question on pain in a comprehensive profile improved pain management, as did administration of purposive instruments[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>]. Similarly, pharmacist-led medicines&#x02019; review yielded greater clinical gains by treating previously unrecognised symptoms than discontinuing inappropriate medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec035"><title>2. Costs</title><p>Additional healthcare needs emanating from medicines&#x02019; mismanagement cost the USA $213bn (8% of total healthcare spend) in 2012, mainly due to an additional 10m hospitalisations[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref115" ref-type="bibr">115</xref>]. Inappropriate prescribing to those aged &#x02265;70 in Northern Ireland in 2009/2010 cost &#x020ac;6,098,419, 5.38% of overall pharmaceutical expenditure[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref116" ref-type="bibr">116</xref>]. Pharmacist review made a non-significant difference to nursing home residents&#x02019; healthcare costs[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref117" ref-type="bibr">117</xref>], and was ineffective in older people in the community[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Our Profile was easy to administer and addressed the problems of incomplete documentation (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), non-adherence (Tables <xref rid="pone.0140203.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">5</xref>), errors, inappropriate prescribing (Tables <xref rid="pone.0140203.t006" ref-type="table">6</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0140203.t009" ref-type="table">9</xref>) and mismanagement cheaply (~&#x000a3;20). The Profile increased nurses&#x02019; workloads: not only was time needed for completion with participants, but also for contacting prescribers, reviewing care plans, arranging GP, dental and optician appointments, to the benefit of participants. Whilst the results of the monitoring affected prescribing and referrals, this was within the context of standard NHS care, and these additional NHS costs were not direct results of the monitoring. We did not have the resources to estimate the costs or savings for each participant.</p></sec><sec id="sec036"><title>3. Harms</title><p>Medicines&#x02019; monitoring and review are reported not to cause harm[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>], and the additional care plans and referrals reported had no risk attached (<xref rid="pone.0140203.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Profiles should neither duplicate existing documentation nor increase professionals&#x02019; bureaucratic burden[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref118" ref-type="bibr">118</xref>], but there is merit in a single instrument to identify, communicate and address problems. Where nurses undertake tasks outside traditional nursing roles, time and educational preparation[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>] are perceived barriers. Any change needs to be seen as beneficial, resourced and achievable[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. To allay concerns regarding the necessary investment in time and learning, the clinical effectiveness of ADR profiles in identifying and ameliorating the burdens of treatment should be demonstrated[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref119" ref-type="bibr">119</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec037"><title>A Strategy worth exploring</title><p>Neither guidelines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] nor literature reviews[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] offer consensus or structures for identifying and addressing medicine-related harm and adverse events. Further research into increased nursing vigilance and improved systems for actively monitoring patients for known adverse effects of prescribed medicines is warranted[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>], and monitoring profiles are ideal[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref123" ref-type="bibr">123</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0140203.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). Profiles do not replace clinical knowledge and experience: they juxtapose information on signs and symptoms with therapeutic regimens in a succinct, formal assessment, and suggest solutions to problems potentially related to prescribed medicines[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref124" ref-type="bibr">124</xref>]. Our Profile augments professionals&#x02019; and patients&#x02019; awareness of ADRs[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref125" ref-type="bibr">125</xref>], and would mitigate public bodies&#x02019; concerns over iatrogenesis[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref126" ref-type="bibr">126</xref>] and under-reporting of ADRs[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref127" ref-type="bibr">127</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref128" ref-type="bibr">128</xref>]. Adoption would expedite: pain management[662,124], proactive and prompt sharing of complete prescribing information during patient transfer[35:77], and recommendations from inquiries into health care failings. These include: enhanced transparency; inter-disciplinary teamwork[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]; informing patients of their medicines&#x02019; adverse effects[3:418]; easily accessible and systematic recording of routine observations[3:129]; frequent checking to minimize medication errors[3:1613]; a &#x0201c;zero tolerance&#x0201d; approach to the improper administration of sedation and medicines[3:111,4:34]; comprehensive education initiatives in medication management[4:R8]; monitoring food and fluid intake[3:111,4:R4].</p><fig id="pone.0140203.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0140203.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>The medication chain.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0140203.g002"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec038"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Nurse-led medicines&#x02019; monitoring improved some aspects of care, including prescribing and pain management, and focused attention on participants&#x02019; reports of adverse events[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref129" ref-type="bibr">129</xref>]. The intervention is feasible[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], low cost, low risk and, when operationalized, convenient for service users and professionals, and offers potential for cost savings and increased quality and safety of care. However, larger, multicentre trials are needed to examine long-term effects of structured medicines&#x02019; monitoring on clinical outcomes[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref130" ref-type="bibr">130</xref>], nurses&#x02019; workloads, and bridging the gap between patients and prescribers (<xref rid="pone.0140203.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>)[<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref120" ref-type="bibr">120</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0140203.ref122" ref-type="bibr">122</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec039"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s001"><label>S1 Appendix</label><caption><title>West Wales Adverse Drug Reaction profile for medicines in mental health v. IX.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s002"><label>S2 Appendix</label><caption><title>The West Wales Adverse Drug Reaction (WWADR) Profile for Mental Health Medicines: template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) checklist.</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s003"><label>S1 CONSORT Checklist</label><caption><title>CONSORT 2010 checklist of information to include when reporting a cluster randomised trial (Campbell et al 2012).</title><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s004"><label>S1 Protocol</label><caption><title>Protocol for the study.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s004.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s005"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>Total number of problems found per participant at each step and in each site.</title><p>This is the S1 table legend reporting descriptive data in full.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s005.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s006"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Total number of actions taken per participant at each step in each site.</title><p>This is the S2 table legend reporting descriptive data in full.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s006.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0140203.s007"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>Number of prescribed medicines in each step for each site.</title><p>This is the S3 table legend reporting descriptive data in full.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0140203.s007.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors are grateful to Mr. Jonathon Bidmead, service user representative, staff and service users in the five care homes, Ian Russell, Professor of Clinical Trials, Director, Swansea Clinical Trials Unit, and Claire Boucher, librarian.</p><p>
<bold>Collaborators:</bold> Robert Colgate, FRCPsych. Consultant Psychiatrist for Older People, Princess of Wales Hospital, Bridgend, Priya Rangappagowda, University Hospital, Llandough, Cardiff, Melanie Storey, Swansea Clinical Trials Unit, Gerwyn Panes, Department of Nursing, Swansea University, Aldo Picek, Fieldbay Ltd, Swansea, SA7 9LA, were involved in establishing the project and liaison with clinical areas.</p></ack><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ADLs</term><def><p>Activities of daily living</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AIMS</term><def><p>Abnormal Involuntary Movements Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BMI</term><def><p>Body mass index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BNF</term><def><p>British National Formulary</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BP</term><def><p>Blood pressure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CNS</term><def><p>Central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPK</term><def><p>Creatine phosphokinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ECG</term><def><p>Electrocardiograph</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FBC</term><def><p>Full blood count</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GP</term><def><p>General practitioner</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LFTs</term><def><p>Liver function tests</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RBC</term><def><p>Red blood cell</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFTs</term><def><p>Thyroid function tests</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTI</term><def><p>Urinary tract infection</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0140203.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>National Patient Safety Agency (NPSA)</collab>. <chapter-title>Safety in doses: medication safety incidents in the NHS</chapter-title>
<source>National Patient Safety Agency</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<year>2007</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Committee of Public Accounts</collab>. <source>A Safer Place for Patients: Learning to Improve Patient Safety</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Stationery Office</publisher-name>, <year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Francis R. Report of the Mid Staffordshire NHS Foundation Trust Public Inquiry: Executive Summary. (Online). Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.midstaffspublicinquiry.com/report">http://www.midstaffspublicinquiry.com/report</ext-link> Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Andrews J, Butler M. Trusted to Care An independent Review of the Princess of Wales Hospital and Neath Port Talbot Hospital at Abertawe Bro Morgannwg University Health Board People, Dementia Services Development Centre, the People Organisation. 2014. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dhss/publications/140512trustedtocareen.pdf">http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dhss/publications/140512trustedtocareen.pdf</ext-link> Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kyriacos</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Medicines&#x02019; Management: a public health problem on nursing&#x02019;s agenda</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing Management</source>. <year>2014</year>; <volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jonm.12238</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24754749?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24754749</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnstone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adverse events and nurse-led medication monitoring</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing Management</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21507109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">International Conference on Harmonisation (ICH) ICH Harmonised Tripartite Guideline for Good Clinical Practice. Institute of Clinical Research, Marlow, Buckinghamshire. 1996. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ich.org/fileadmin/Public_Web_Site/ICH_Products/Guidelines/Efficacy/E6/E6_R1_Guideline.pdf">http://www.ich.org/fileadmin/Public_Web_Site/ICH_Products/Guidelines/Efficacy/E6/E6_R1_Guideline.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mottram</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rowe</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pirmohamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Emergency re-admissions to hospital due to adverse drug reactions within 1 year of the index admission</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>. <year>2010</year>; <volume>70</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>749</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2125.2010.03751.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21039769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21039769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pirmohamed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>James</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meakin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adverse drug reactions as cause of admission to hospital: prospective analysis of 18 820 patients</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>329</volume>(<issue>7456</issue>), <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15231615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15231615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Marcum</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amuan</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanlon</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aspinall</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Prevalence of unplanned hospitalizations caused by adverse drug reactions in older veterans</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Geriatric Society</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>60</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03772.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slavenburg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Royal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pipe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lucassen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Which drugs cause preventable admissions to hospital? A systematic review</article-title>. <source>Bristish Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>63</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jen</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bottle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Molokhia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aylin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Ten-year trends in hospital admissions for adverse drug reactions in England 1999&#x02013;2009</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine</source>.<year>2010</year>; <volume>103</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1258/jrsm.2010.100113</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Frontier Economic</collab>. <source>Exploring the costs of unsafe care in the NHS: a report prepared for the department of health, Frontier Economics</source>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<year>2014</year> Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.frontier-economics.com/documents/2014/10/exploring-the-costs-of-unsafe-care-in-the-nhs-frontier-report-2-2-2-2.pdf">http://www.frontier-economics.com/documents/2014/10/exploring-the-costs-of-unsafe-care-in-the-nhs-frontier-report-2-2-2-2.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cutroneo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trifir&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Clinical and economic burden of adverse drug reactions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Pharmacology and Pharmacotherapeutics</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>4</volume> (<issue>Suppl1</issue>), <fpage>S73</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24347988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>NICE Medicines &#x00026; Prescribing Centre</collab>. <chapter-title>Medicines optimisation: the safe and effective use of medicines to enable the best possible outcomes</chapter-title>
<source>NICE guideline 5</source>. <publisher-loc>NICE, London</publisher-loc>
<year>2015</year> Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng5/evidence/full-guideline-6775454">http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/ng5/evidence/full-guideline-6775454</ext-link> Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hakkarainen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andersson Sundell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petzold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>H&#x000e4;gg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prevalence and perceived preventability of self-reported adverse drug events-a population-based survey of 7099 adults</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>e73166</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073166</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24023828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24023828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murff</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adverse drug events occurring following hospital discharge</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Internal Medicine</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>20</volume>(<issue>4</issue>) pp.<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15857487?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15857487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gurwitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Judge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rochon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrold</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cadoret</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The incidence of adverse drug events in two large academic long-term care facilities</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Medicine</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>118</volume>, <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 15745723?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15745723</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alldred</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spoor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interventions to optimise prescribing for older people in care homes</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>
<year>2013</year>; <issue>Issue 2</issue> Art. No.: <fpage>CD009095</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD009095.pub2</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23450597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schiff</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Covinsky</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name>. <source>Beyond the prescription: medication monitoring and adverse drug events in older adults</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>59</volume>(<issue>8</issue>) pp. <fpage>1513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Detz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sarkar</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>. <article-title>Signal and noise: applying a laboratory trigger tool to identify adverse drug events among primary care patients</article-title>. <source>BMJ Qual Saf</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>21</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>670</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjqs-2011-000643</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22626736?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22626736</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Managing Adverse Drug Reactions: An Orphan Task. Developing nurse-administered evaluation checklists</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>: <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tunnicliffe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Minimising Side Effects: The clinical impact of nurse-administered &#x02018;side effects&#x02019; checklists</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>37</volume>;<issue>2</issue>:<fpage>155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11851783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11851783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Newson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snelgrove</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Panes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Picek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Medication Monitoring for People with Dementia in Care Homes: the Feasibility and Clinical Impact of Nurse-led monitoring</article-title>. <source>The Scientific World Journal</source>, <volume>vol. 2014</volume>, Article ID 843621, <fpage>11</fpage> pages, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/843621</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gabe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Medication monitoring in a nurse-led respiratory outpatient clinic: pragmatic randomised trial of the West Wales Adverse Drug Reaction Profile</article-title>. <source>PLOS One</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>) <fpage>e96682</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0096682</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24798210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24798210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Banerjee S. The use of antipsychotic medication for people with dementia: time for action. A report for the Minister of State for Care Services. An Independent |Report commissioned for the Department of Health, London 2009. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dh.gov.uk/prod_consum_dh/groups/dh_digitalassets/documents/digitalasset/dh_108302.pdf">http://www.dh.gov.uk/prod_consum_dh/groups/dh_digitalassets/documents/digitalasset/dh_108302.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Child</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maidment</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <article-title>A pharmacy led program to review anti-psychotic prescribing for people with dementia</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>155</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-244X-12-155</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23006528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23006528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alessi-Severini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Metge</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prescribing of psychotropic medications to the elderly population of a Canadian province: a retrospective study using administrative databases</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source>, <year>2013</year>;<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>e168</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.168</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24109553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24109553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>DeWilde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antidepressant prescribing in older primary care patients in community and care home settings in England and Wales</article-title>. <source>J Am Med Dir Assoc</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jamda.2010.09.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21450211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21450211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stefan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Epilepsy in the elderly: facts and challenges</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>124</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2010.01464.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21143593?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Laroche</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perault-Pochat</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ingrand</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreft-Jais</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castot-Villepelet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adverse drug reactions in patients with Alzheimer's disease and related dementia in France: a national multicentre cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source>. <year>2013</year>
<month>9</month>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>952</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pds.3471</pub-id> Epub 2013 Jun 24.
<?supplied-pmid 23794320?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23794320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gallini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrieu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donohue</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oumouhou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lapeyre-Mestre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardette</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>. <article-title>Trends in use of antipsychotics in elderly patients with dementia: Impact of national safety warnings</article-title>. <source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source>. <volume>2014</volume>
<month>1</month>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2013.09.003</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FDA. Information for Healthcare Professionals: Conventional Antipsychotics. 2008. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/PostmarketDrugSafetyInformationforPatientsandProviders/ucm124830.htm">http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/PostmarketDrugSafetyInformationforPatientsandProviders/ucm124830.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>British National Formulary</collab>. <source>BNF number 69</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>British Medical Association and the Royal Pharmaceutical Society of Great Britain</publisher-name>
<year>2015</year>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NICE. Psychosis and Schizophrenia in adults: treatment and interventions management of schizophrenia in primary and secondary care (update). Clinical Practice Guideline no. 178. Centre for Clinical Practice. Commissioned by NICE. 2014. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg178/resources/cg178-psychosis-and-schizophrenia-in-adults-full-guideline3">http://www.nice.org.uk/guidance/cg178/resources/cg178-psychosis-and-schizophrenia-in-adults-full-guideline3</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blenkinsopp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A systematic review of quantitative and qualitative research on the role and effectiveness of written information available to patients about individual medicines</article-title>. <source>Health Technol Assess</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>iii</fpage>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17280623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17280623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nicolson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knapp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spoor</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Written information about individual medicines for consumers</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2009</year>;(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>CD002104</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD002104.pub3</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19370575?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19370575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guthrie</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dreischulte</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Developing a complex intervention to improve prescribing safety in primary care: mixed methods feasibility and optimisation pilot study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>e004153</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004153</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24448848?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24448848</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>RESPECT Trial Team</collab>. <article-title>Effectiveness of shared pharmaceutical care for older patients: RESPECT trial findings</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Br J Gen Pract</italic></source>
<year>2009</year>; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3399/bjgp09X473295</pub-id> (abridged text, in print: <italic>Br J Gen Pract</italic> 2010; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>14</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Forsetlund</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eike</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gjerberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vist</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of interventions to reduce potentially inappropriate use of drugs in nursing homes: a systematic review of randomised controlled trials</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatr</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2318-11-16</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21496345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21496345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Desborough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodyer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loke</surname><given-names>YK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Does pharmacist-led medication review help to reduce hospital admissions and deaths in older people? A systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>303</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 18093253?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18093253</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pointon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Monitoring adverse drug reactions: scales, profiles, and checklists</article-title>. <source>International nursing review</source>, <year>2004</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15530161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15530161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bakerjian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <source>CMS national partnership to improve dementia care in nursing homes Geriatric Nursing</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Woertman</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Hoop</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moerbeek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zuidema</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gerritsen</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Teerenstra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Stepped wedge designs could reduce the required sample size in cluster randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>7</issue>) <fpage>752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>758</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2013.01.009</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23523551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23523551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lilford</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The stepped wedge trial design: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMC Medical Research Methodology</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 17092344?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17092344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Keriel-Gascou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buchet-Poyau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Duclos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rabilloud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Figon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Evaluation of an interactive program for preventing adverse drug events in primary care: study protocol of the InPAct cluster randomised stepped wedge trial</article-title>. <source>Implementation Science</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>69</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1748-5908-8-69</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23782470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23782470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mdege</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Man</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taylor Nee Brown</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Systematic review of stepped wedge cluster randomized trials shows that design is particularly used to evaluate interventions during routine implementation</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>936</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.12.003</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21411284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21411284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Piaggio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elbourne</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <collab>CONSORT Group</collab>. <article-title>Consort 2010 statement: extension to cluster randomised trials</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>345</volume>:<fpage>e5661</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e5661</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22951546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22951546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Quality Forum MCC Measurement Framework Final Report, Washington DC. 2012. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.qualityforum.org/Publications/2012/05/MCC_Measurement_Framework_Final_Report.aspx">http://www.qualityforum.org/Publications/2012/05/MCC_Measurement_Framework_Final_Report.aspx</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Medication management: an exploratory study into the role of Community Mental Health Nurses</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>. <year>1999</year>:<volume>29</volume>:<issue>5</issue>: <fpage>1068</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 10320489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10320489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Adverse drug reactions: managing the risk</article-title>. <source>Journal of Nursing Management</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>17</volume>; <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2834.2009.00977.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19416420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <source>The Prescription Drug Guide for Nurses</source>. <publisher-name>Open University Press, McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Maidenhead</publisher-loc>
<year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paton</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kapur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <source>The Maudsley Prescribing Guidelines</source>, <edition>11th Edition</edition>, <publisher-name>Wiley Blackwell</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
<year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Uitenbroek</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>"SISA-Binomial" (Simple Interactive Statistical Analysis)</article-title>. <year>1997</year>
<source>SISA</source>. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://home.clara.net/sisa/sampshlp.htm">http://home.clara.net/sisa/sampshlp.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Killip</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahfoud</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>What Is an Intracluster Correlation Coeffi cient? Crucial Concepts for Primary Care Researchers</article-title>. <source>Annals of Family Medicine</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>08</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 15209195?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15209195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hussey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Design and analysis of stepped wedge cluster randomized trials</article-title>. <source>Contemp Clin Trials</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16829207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16829207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Husebo</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sandvik</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>OB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aarsland</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Efficacy of treating pain to reduce behavioural disturbances in residents of nursing homes with dementia: cluster randomised clinical trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>343</volume>:<fpage>d4065</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.d4065</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21765198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21765198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>French</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spehar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Foulis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Outpatient Medications and Hip Fractures in the US: A National Veterans Study</article-title>. <source>Drugs and Aging</source>. <volume>Vol. 22</volume>(<issue>10</issue>) pp. <fpage>877</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>885</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>van Doorn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruber-Baldini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hebel</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Port</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baumgarten</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Dementia as a risk factor for falls and fall injuries among nursing home residents</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Journal of the American Geriatrics Society</italic></source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>1213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1218</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12919232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>S&#x000f8;rensen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Schizophrenia, antipsychotics and risk of hip fracture: a population-based analysis</article-title>. <source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2013.04.002</pub-id> Epub 2013 May 1. .<?supplied-pmid 23642346?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23642346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mielke</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leoutsakos</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lyketsos</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rabins</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The association of psychotropic medication use with the cognitive, functional, and neuropsychiatric trajectory of Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>International journal of geriatric psychiatry</source>, <year>2012</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1248</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1257</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.3769</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22374884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22374884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Passmore</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Pain in care home residents with dementia: an exploration of frequency, prescribing and relatives' perspectives</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gps.4111</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24733695?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24733695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilcock</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of activities of daily living in dementia: development of the Bristol Activities of Daily Living Scale</article-title>. <source>Age and Ageing</source>
<year>1996</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>120</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8670538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8670538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Manchester and Oxford Universities Scale for the Psychopathological Assessment of Dementia (MOUSEPAD)</article-title>. <source>The British Journal of Psychiatry</source>, <year>1996</year>;<volume>169</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>307</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8879715?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8879715</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Act, Mental Capacity. The Stationery Office. 2005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Weijer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grimshaw</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McRae</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brehaut</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Ottawa Ethics of Cluster Randomized Trials Consensus Group. The Ottawa Statement on the Ethical Design and Conduct of Cluster Randomized Trials</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e1001346</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23185138</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Diazordaz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slowther</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eldridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Consent processes in cluster-randomised trials in residential facilities for older adults: a systematic review of reporting practices and proposed guidelines</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>7</issue>). pii: <fpage>e003057</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2013-003057</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23836761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23836761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Council of International Organisations of Medical Sciences (CIOMS). International Ethical Guidelines for Biomedical Research Involving Human Subjects. Published in Geneva, Switzerland. 2002. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cioms.ch/publications/layout_guide2002.pdf">http://www.cioms.ch/publications/layout_guide2002.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Curtis L PSSRU (Personal Social Services Research Unit) Unit Costs 2013. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pssru.ac.uk/project-pages/unit-costs/2013/">http://www.pssru.ac.uk/project-pages/unit-costs/2013/</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">NHS Reference Costs 2012/2013. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/nhs-reference-costs-2012-to-2013">https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/nhs-reference-costs-2012-to-2013</ext-link> Accessed 5 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enges&#x000e6;ter</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ranhoff</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunskaar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruths</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk of hip fracture among older people using anxiolytic and hypnotic drugs: a nationwide prospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>7</month>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>873</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-014-1684-z</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24810612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24810612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Commission. Objective 1: Supporting development in less prosperous regions. 2008. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/regional_policy/archive/objective1/index_en.htm">http://ec.europa.eu/regional_policy/archive/objective1/index_en.htm</ext-link> Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alldred</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jesson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Care homes' use of medicines study: prevalence, causes and potential harm of medication errors in care homes for older people</article-title>. <source>Qual Saf Health Care</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/qshc.2009.034231</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19812095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812095</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessing Educational Effectiveness: The impact of a specialist course on the delivery of care</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>
<year>1999</year>;<volume>30</volume>:<issue>4</issue>:<fpage>796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>807</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10520091?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10520091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garauova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Volunteer Bias in Recruitment, Retention, and Blood Sample Donation in a Randomised Controlled Trial Involving Mothers and Their Children at Six Months and Two Years: A Longitudinal Analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>7</issue>): <fpage>e67912</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 23874465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23874465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Puffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Torgerson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence for risk of bias in cluster randomised trials: review of recent trials published in three general medical journals</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>327</volume>(<issue>7418</issue>):<fpage>785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14525877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14525877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McIntosh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stellenberg</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>. <source>Effect of a staffing strategy based on voluntary increase in working hours on quality of patient care in a hospital in KwaZulu-Natal Curations</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>:(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>1 1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2</lpage> 0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Atypical antipsychotic drugs and the risk for acute kidney injury and other adverse outcomes in older adults: a population-based cohort study</article-title>. <source>Ann Intern Med</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>161</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>242</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M13-2796</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25133360?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25133360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Roethlisberger</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dickson</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <source>Management and the Worker</source>. <publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, Massachusetts</publisher-loc>
<year>1939</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Bias in analytic research</article-title>. <source>Journal of Chronic Diseases</source>, <year>1979</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">447779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Sackett</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guyatt</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <source>Clinical Epidemiology: A Basic Science For Clinical Medicine</source>, <edition>2nd ed</edition>
<publisher-name>Little, Brown</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>
<year>1991</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ravaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <collab>CONSORT Group</collab>. <article-title>Extending the CONSORT Statement to Randomized Trials of Nonpharmacological Treatment: Explanation and Elaboration</article-title>. <source>Annals of Internal Medicine</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>148</volume>: <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>309</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 18283207?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18283207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zwarenstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Treweek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gagnier</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tunis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Improving the reporting of pragmatic trials: an extension of the CONSORT statement</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>337</volume>: <fpage>a2390</fpage> pp. <fpage>1223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.a2390</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19001484?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19001484</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hr&#x000f3;bjartsson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tendal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hilden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Observer bias in randomised clinical trials with binary outcomes: systematic review of trials with both blinded and non-blinded outcome assessors</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>344</volume>: <fpage>e1119</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.e1119</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22371859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22371859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Teachers' expectancies: Determinants of pupils' IQ gains</article-title>. <source>Psychological Reports</source>, <year>1963</year>;<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>118</lpage>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>JPT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sterne</surname><given-names>JAC</given-names></name>. (editors). <chapter-title>Assessing risk of bias in included studies</chapter-title> Chapter 8 In: <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>J.P.T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. (editors). <source>Cochrane Handbook for Systematic Reviews of Interventions Version 5.1.0 (updated March 2011)</source>. <publisher-name>The Cochrane Collaboration</publisher-name>, <year>2011</year> Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cochrane-handbook.org">www.cochrane-handbook.org</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <source>The Lancet handbook of essential concepts in clinical research</source>. <publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
<year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Keogh-Brown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bachmann</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shepstone</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Contamination in trials of education interventions</article-title>. <source>Health technology Assessment</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>43</issue>): <fpage>iii</fpage>, <fpage>ix</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>107</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17935683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17935683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lundh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Medication review in hospitalised patients to reduce morbidity and mortality</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>28</volume>;<issue>2</issue>:<fpage>CD008986</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pacini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Home-based medication review in older people: is it cost effective?</article-title>
<source>Pharmacoeconomics</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17249858?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17249858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bosboom</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alfonso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use of Potentially Harmful Medications and Health-Related Quality of Life among People with Dementia Living in Residential Aged Care Facilities</article-title>. <source>Dement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000342172</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23277778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zermansky</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alldred</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petty</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raynor</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freemantle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eastaugh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Clinical medication review by a pharmacist of elderly people living in care homes&#x02014;randomised controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Age and ageing</source>, <year>2006</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>591</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16905764?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16905764</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerse</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardwell</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interventions to improve the appropriate use of polypharmacy for older people</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>, <year>2012</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>5</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Viswanathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kahwati</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golin</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blalock</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coker-Schwimmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Posey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Medication Therapy Management Interventions in Outpatient Settings: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2014</year>; <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.5841</pub-id> [Epub ahead of print]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Watson-Wolfe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galik</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klinedinst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>Application of the Antipsychotic Use in Dementia Assessment audit tool to facilitate appropriate antipsychotic use in long term care residents with dementia</article-title>. <source>Geriatric Nursing</source>, <year>2014</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gerinurse.2013.09.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24139205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24139205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nkansah</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mostovetsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chheng</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Effect of outpatient pharmacists' non-dispensing roles on patient outcomes and prescribing patterns</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>;(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>CD000336</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD000336.pub2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20614422?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20614422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Topinkov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baeyens</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lanq</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evidence-based strategies for the optimization of pharmacotherapy in older people</article-title>. <source>Drugs Aging</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11632400-000000000-00000</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22642782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22642782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref098"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lapane</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Daiello</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feinberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effect of a pharmacist-led multicomponent intervention focusing on the medication monitoring phase to prevent potential adverse drug events in nursing homes</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03418.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21649623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21649623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref099"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Arditi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>R&#x000e8;ge-Walther</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wyatt</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Durieux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burnand</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Computer-generated reminders delivered on paper to healthcare professionals; effects on professional practice and health care outcomes</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews</source>
<year>2012</year>; <issue>Issue 12</issue> Art. No.: <fpage>CD001175</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/14651858.CD001175.pub3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23235578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vigen</surname><given-names>CLP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>RSE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sultzer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Cognitive effects of atypical antipsychotic medications in patients with Alzheimer's Disease: Outcomes From CATIE-AD</article-title>. <source>The American Journal of Psychiatry</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>168</volume>(<issue>8</issue>)pp.<fpage>831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>839</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2011.08121844</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21572163?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref101"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brisbin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rapoport</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Pharmacological treatments for neuropsychiatric symptoms of dementia in long-term care: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>International Psychogeriatrics</source>, <year>2013</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>02</issue>), <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23083438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref102"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>American Geriatrics Society Beers Criteria Update Expert Panel</collab>. <article-title>American Geriatrics Society updated Beers Criteria for potentially inappropriate medication use in older adults</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>616</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2012.03923.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22376048?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22376048</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref103"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Murray-Thomas</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shatapathy</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motsko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Risk of mortality (including sudden cardiac death) and major cardiovascular events in atypical and typical antipsychotic users: a study with the general practice research database</article-title>. <source>Cardiovasc Psychiatry Neurol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>247486</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/247486</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24455199?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24455199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref104"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Corbett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ballard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Don&#x02019;t use antipsychotics routinely to treat agitation and aggression in people with dementia</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2014</year>;<volume>349</volume>; <fpage>g6420</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g6420</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25368388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25368388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref105"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motterlini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padmanabhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cahir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Potentially inappropriate prescribing among older people in the United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>BMC Geriatr</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>72</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2318-14-72</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24919523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24919523</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref106"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maserejian</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steers</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKinlay</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Are commonly used psychoactive medications associated with lower urinary tract symptoms?</article-title>
<source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-011-1170-9</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22138718?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22138718</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref107"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Maughan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Hydration, morbidity, and mortality in vulnerable populations</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>70</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue>:<fpage>S152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1753-4887.2012.00531.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23121352?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23121352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref108"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Manz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wentz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The importance of good hydration for the prevention of chronic diseases</article-title>. <source>Nutrition reviews</source>, <year>2005</year>;<volume>63</volume>(<issue>s1</issue>), <fpage>S2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16028566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref109"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Aronson</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>. (ed.) <source>Meyler's Side Effects of Drugs: The International Encyclopaedia of Adverse Drug Reactions and Interactions</source>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
<year>2006</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref110"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Golder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Loke</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Search strategies to identify information on adverse effects: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Medical Library Association</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>2</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3163/1536-5050.97.2.004</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19404498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19404498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref111"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tsang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lynd</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Inadequate statistical power to detect clinically significant differences in adverse event rates in randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of Clinical Epidemiology</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>609</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2008.08.005</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19013761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19013761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref112"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zorzela</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pilkington</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartling</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joffe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Quality of reporting in systematic reviews of adverse events: systematic review</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>f7668</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.f7668</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24401468?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24401468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref113"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pieper</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Dalen-Kok</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Francke</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Steen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scherder</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huseb&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Interventions targeting pain or behaviour in dementia: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Ageing Res Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arr.2013.05.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23727161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23727161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref114"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moriarty</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cousins</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cahir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Motterlini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Prevalence of potentially inappropriate prescribing and prescribing omissions in older Irish adults: findings from The Irish LongituDinal Study on Ageing study (TILDA)</article-title>. <source>Eur J Clin Pharmacol</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>5</month>;<volume>70</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-014-1651-8</pub-id> Epub 2014 Feb 4.
<?supplied-pmid 24493365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24493365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref115"><label>115</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valkova</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <source>Avoidable costs in US Healthcare</source>. <publisher-name>IMS Institute for Healthcare Informatics</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Parsippany, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>
<year>2013</year> Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.imshealth.com/deployedfiles/imshealth/Global/Content/Corporate/IMS%2520Institute/RUOM-2013/IHII_Responsible_Use_Medicines_2013.pdf&#x00026;chrome=true">https://docs.google.com/gview?url=http://www.imshealth.com/deployedfiles/imshealth/Global/Content/Corporate/IMS%2520Institute/RUOM-2013/IHII_Responsible_Use_Medicines_2013.pdf&#x00026;chrome=true</ext-link>. Accessed 4 June 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref116"><label>116</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fahey</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cahir</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x02019;Reilly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Potentially inappropriate prescribing and cost outcomes for older people: a cross-sectional study using the Northern Ireland Enhanced Prescribing Database</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</source>, <year>2012</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1433</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-012-1249-y</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22447297?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22447297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref117"><label>117</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cardwell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lapane</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crealey</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>. <article-title>A cluster randomized controlled trial of an adapted U.S. model of pharmaceutical care for nursing home residents in Northern Ireland (Fleetwood Northern Ireland study): a cost-effectiveness analysis</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2011.03354.x</pub-id> Epub 2011 Mar 31. .<?supplied-pmid 21453379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21453379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref118"><label>118</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Review of Health and Social Care Burdens</collab>. <source>Lifting the Burdens Task Force</source>. <publisher-name>Local Government Association</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
<year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref119"><label>119</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ginsburg</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berta</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tregunno</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The relationship between organizational leadership for safety and learning from patient safety events</article-title>. <source>Health Service Research</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>),<fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>632</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref120"><label>120</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Co-ordinating Council for Medication Error Reporting and Prevention. The First Ten Years &#x0201c;Defining the Problem and Developing Solutions&#x0201d;. United States Pharmacopia, Rockville, Maryland. 2005. Available: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nccmerp.org/pdf/reportFinal2005-11-29.pdf">http://www.nccmerp.org/pdf/reportFinal2005-11-29.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 8 May 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref121"><label>121</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wightman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Audit of antipsychotic prescribing in dementia: Cambridgeshire results and lessons learnt</article-title>. <source>Psychiatria Danubina</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>S126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 21894119?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21894119</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref122"><label>122</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wee</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Psychotropic drug-induced falls in older people: a review of interventions aimed at reducing the problem</article-title>. <source>Drugs Aging</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11598420-000000000-00000</pub-id>
.<?supplied-pmid 22191720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22191720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref123"><label>123</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Connolly</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oluwole</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macken</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Monitoring and documentation of side effects from depot antipsychotic medication: an interdisciplinary audit of practice in a regional mental health service</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Ment Health Nurs</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>14</volume>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2850.2011.01807.x</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref124"><label>124</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Better reporting of interventions: template for intervention description and replication (TIDieR) checklist and guide</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>g1687</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g1687</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24609605?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24609605</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref125"><label>125</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Riker</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Setter</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Polypharmacy in older adults at home: what it is and what to do about it-implications for home healthcare and hospice, part 2</article-title>. <source>Home Healthcare Nurse</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>65</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>; quiz 78&#x02013;9. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/NHH.0b013e31827f43b2</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23385171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23385171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref126"><label>126</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Audit Commission</collab>. <source>A Spoonful of Sugar: Medicines Management in NHS Hospitals</source>. <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>The Stationery Office</publisher-name>
<year>2001</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref127"><label>127</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hazell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shakir</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Under-reporting of adverse drug reactions: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Drug Safety</source>
<year>2006</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>
<?supplied-pmid 16689555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689555</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref128"><label>128</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Heeley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Layton</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilton</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shakir</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Prescription-event monitoring and reporting of adverse drug reactions</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>358</volume>(<issue>9296</issue>):<fpage>1872</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11741629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11741629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref129"><label>129</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Onder</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Cammen</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petrovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Somers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rajkumar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Strategies to reduce the risk of iatrogenic illness in complex older adults</article-title>. <source>Age Ageing</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>284</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ageing/aft038</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23537588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23537588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0140203.ref130"><label>130</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McKibbon</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lokker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Handler</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dolovich</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x02019;Reily</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The effectiveness of integrated health information technologies across the phases of medication management: a systematic review of randomized controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association</source>
<year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/amiajnl-2011-000304</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21852412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21852412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>