<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Complement Altern Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Complementary and Alternative Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6882</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5996544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2236</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12906-018-2236-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effect of neuromuscular taping on musculoskeletal disorders secondary to the use of aromatase inhibitors in breast cancer survivors: a pragmatic randomised clinical trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Conejo</surname><given-names>Inmaculada</given-names></name><address><email>inmaconejo@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>Bella</given-names></name><address><email>bella.pajares@fundacionimabis.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alba</surname><given-names>Emilio</given-names></name><address><email>ealbac@uma.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8880-4315</contrib-id><name><surname>Cuesta-Vargas</surname><given-names>Antonio Ignacio</given-names></name><address><email>acuesta.var@gmail.com</email><email>acuesta@uma.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 7828</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10215.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Physiotherapy, Faculty of Health Science, </institution><institution>University of M&#x000e1;laga, </institution></institution-wrap>M&#x000e1;laga, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452525.1</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>Carlos Haya Regional University Hospital, IBIMA, </institution></institution-wrap>M&#x000e1;laga, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2298 7828</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10215.37</institution-id><institution>Department of Physiotherapy, IBIMA, </institution><institution>University of M&#x000e1;laga, </institution></institution-wrap>M&#x000e1;laga, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000089150953</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.1024.7</institution-id><institution>School of Clinical Science, Faculty of Health, </institution><institution>Queensland University of Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Kelvin Grove, Australia </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>180</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Aromatase inhibitors reduce breast cancer recurrence rates in postmenopausal women by about 30% compared with tamoxifen while treatments differ. Unfortunately, nearly half of women taking AIs report AI-associated arthralgia (AIA), leading to therapy abandon in on third of patients, which could lead to cancer recurrence. The purpose of the current study was to evaluate the effectiveness of Neuromuscular Taping (NMT) in the treatment of AIA in women who have been treated of BC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study included 40&#x000a0;BC survivors receiving endocrine therapy (either AIs or TMX) from Hospital Universitario Virgen de la Victoria (M&#x000e1;laga, Spain) suffered from AIA. Patients were randomized to one of the two groups that made this pilot study: A. Placebo intervention B. Real NMT. Clinical data were collected from medical history, grip strength, algometry measured, questionnaires and VAS scale. There have been three interventions prior to the completion of the study, 5&#x000a0;weeks later. The primary objective of this pilot study was to achieve an improvement of pain by 20% decrease of VAS.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Significant differences in measures of VAS (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009), global health status/QoL (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.005), fatigue (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01) and pain (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04) were observed post intervention with NMT.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">An intervention by NMT to MSCM under treatment with AIs improves their subjective sensation of pain. In addition, this taping had an impact on variables related to the quality of life. This pilot study may be the basis for others to support the use of NMT for the treatment of AIAs, thereby improving their well-being and reducing the dropout rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Trial registration</title><p id="Par5"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clinicaltrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link> Identifier: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT02406794">NCT02406794</ext-link>. Registered on 2 April 2015 Retrospectively registered.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Breast cancer</kwd><kwd>Hormonal therapy</kwd><kwd>Aromatase inhibitors</kwd><kwd>Estrogen deprivation</kwd><kwd>Myalgia</kwd><kwd>Arthralgia</kwd><kwd>Carpal tunnel syndrome</kwd><kwd>Visual analogue scale</kwd><kwd>Pressure pain threshold</kwd><kwd>Neuromuscular taping</kwd><kwd>Kinesio taping</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par29">Breast cancer (BC) is the most common cancer in women and the leading cause of death among middle-aged women in developed countries. The latest available estimation, for 2012, is that there would be 1.671.149 new cases worldwide and 521.907 deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In Spain, the most frequently diagnosed tumor is BC (25,215 new cases), mortality was only of 6.075 patients, so its prevalence at 5&#x000a0;years is 104.210 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Both factors, the increase in the number of new cases and lower mortality, due to recent scientific advances in screening, diagnosis and treatment, result in a higher prevalence of BC and an increase in the number of breast cancer survivors (BCS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par30">Aromatase inhibitors (AIs) interrupt the conversion of androgens to estrogens in postmenopausal women, thus able to reduce circulating estrogen levels to about 1/10th of normal levels. Currently, the most widely used in clinical practice are the third generation aromatase inhibitors (exemestane, anastrozole and letrozole). AIs improve outcomes in the adjuvant treatment of postmenopausal women with hormone receptor positive (HR+) BC compared with tamoxifen decreasing the risk of recurrence (20&#x02013;36%) and decreasing 10-year breast cancer mortality (12.1% vs. 14.2% RR 0&#x000b7;85, 0&#x000b7;75&#x02013;0&#x000b7;96; 2p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0&#x000b7;009) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">TMX induced more gynecological and thromboembolic side effects, however patients receiving AIs have a higher incidence of osteoporosis, bone fractures and musculoskeletal symptoms, particularly pain and stiffness in the joints [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. These co-morbidities associated with AIs compromises survivors&#x02019; quality of life and leads to non-compliance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par32">Is important to consider that to achieve the same benefits of adjuvant endocrine therapy in clinical practice as those observed in clinical trial settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], long-term compliance with treatment is required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par33">Adjuvant endocrine therapy is associated with poor compliance rates compared with chemotherapy and radiotherapy. Retrospective analyses indicate prescription-controlled adherence rates of 80% for tamoxifen and 69% for anastrozole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par34">The worst figures are found in those survivors who underwent both types of hormone therapy (from one form of therapy to the other), with dropout rates of 31.3% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Induced AIs musculoskeletal toxicity may be the cause of this lower persistence rate and possibly reduced efficacy.</p><p id="Par35">To analyze the problem of musculoskeletal disorders associated with the use of IAs, it is important to begin by correctly define these disorders, and thus have objective criteria for diagnosis. In general, these usually have joint pain that is localized mainly in the wrists, hands and knees symmetrically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The Intergroup Exemestane Study (IES) performed retrospective studies which concluded that the occurrence of carpal tunnel syndrome (CTS) cases was higher in those patients who were treated with exemestane (2,8%) than in those who taking TMX as hormonal therapy (0,6%). The 69% of cases that manifest this syndrome, underwent surgical release, underwent surgical release [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The ATAC (Arimidex and Tamoxifen, alone or in combination) trial analysed the natural history of patients who presented with CTS during adjuvant treatment for breast cancer. CTS were reported in 2,6% of the participant in the anastrozole arm, compared with 0.7% in the tamoxifen arm, although the symptoms were mild or moderate in intensity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Other symptoms such as morning stiffness, myalgia, tenosinovial changes and decreased grip strength were also found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Occurrence of carpal tunnel syndrome and any musculoskeletal events can serve as biomarkers of treatment effectiveness, because the estrogenic reduction is a mechanism of action for both, antitumor effect and development of endocrine treatment-induced symptoms. So much so that musculoskeletal symptoms, including CTS, was associated with improved disease-free survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. A recent meta-analysis found no difference in anti-tumor efficacy between the three AIs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], and for this reason it would be interesting to know the side effects caused by each of them with prescriptive purposes.</p><p id="Par36">Despite high prevalence of the arthralgia, which often accompanies the AIs medicine, the way this compromises their quality of life and leads to non-compliance; very little is known about what causes this difficult problem. Clearly, it is important informing the patient before therapy that joint pain is a very common side effect, and thus better tolerate the problem. Once symptoms debuting have been used therapies such as acupuncture to combat them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In clinical practice are often used nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) for improving musculoskeletal disorders and even get some relief, they are not exempt from a number of side effects. There are some particularly interesting NSAIDs (COX-2 selective inhibitor), but are known to alter the regulation of aromatase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and have potentially dangerous side effects, which means they are not recommended for routine treatment of AIs effects secondary. The ATAC trial showed that obese women (body mass index [BMI]&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;30&#x000a0;kg/m2) had more joint symptoms than women with a BMI of 25&#x02013;30&#x000a0;kg / m2 or those with a BMI &#x0003c;&#x02009;25&#x000a0;kg/m2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], so another excellent intervention for these women would be weight loss. Some studies have shown the effectiveness of an intervention based on the practice of yoga in reducing musculoskeletal symptoms such as general pain, muscle pain and overall physical discomfort [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Other study focused on changes in rheumatological symptoms, such as morning stiffness, joint pain and grip strength and they found that a short course of low-dose prednisone showed promising potential as an effective treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In a retrospective study about the usefulness of diuretics and bisphosphonates for managing arthralgia produced by hormone therapy, the study concluded that these drugs reduced the discomfort caused by the joint pains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. A recent meta-analysis published by Yang et al. reported that pharmacological approaches, acupuncture, and relaxation techniques showed moderate to large effects on pain, whereas nutritional supplementation and physical exercise had no significant effects on it [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. It can therefore be concluded that there is no established, effective treatment for this difficult problem which affects up to half of women on AI therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">Neuromuscular Taping (NMT) has become an increasingly popular technique in recent years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and is mainly used in various areas of sports performance and/or rehabilitation. Kinesiology taping with elastic tape is a new therapeutic method indicated for the relief of pain, neuromuscular rehabilitation, musculoskeletal upheavals and related to sports injuries. The elastic characteristics of Kinesiology tape allow extending from a minimum of 120% to a maximum of 170% of its original length, after which recedes again at its original length [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The Neuromuscular Taping has achieved excellent results in decreased pain, increased functional abilities and in reducing edema [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. This new technique of taping has demonstrated efficacy in the acute treatment of sports lesions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], muscle disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>], has achieved improvement of balance and functional activities in neurological patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], achieve better sensorimotor synchronization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] reducing swelling and postoperative pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and reducing lymphedema as a additional measure to the Complex Decongestive Therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], although the edema reduction of multilayered bandages is better [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Nevertheless, no studies have researched its use for the treatment of musculoskeletal disorders in BCS, and its impact on the pressure pain threshold (PPT) or on VAS. The purpose of this study was assessing the effect of an intervention by NMT in the subjective sensation of pain in these patients.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Design and participants</title><p id="Par38">The present study is a randomized controlled clinical trial conforming to Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) guidelines. This pragmatic randomized study was carried out with a sample of 40 patients who had been treated from BC with third generation AIs, and came to consultation with her oncologist at the University Hospital Virgen de la Victoria (M&#x000e1;laga, Spain). Patients were recruited from May 2016 to September 2016, two days each week, through convenience sampling. All patients gave their informed consent for the study. The trial had ethical approval of the Ethics Committee of the Provincial Investigation Malaga (Ministry of Health Andalusian Health Service, Spain). They were respected the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Inclusion criteria were: (a) higher 18&#x000a0;years old; (b) have suffered from primary breast cancer confirmed histologically (I-IIIA); (c) have completed primary carcinoma treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy); (d) be subjected to hormonal therapy as adjuvant therapy to the process by AIs (exemestane, anastrozole, letrozole); (e) present a functional status according to WHO from 0 (asymptomatic, complete and ambulatory activity) or 1 (symptomatic but completely ambulatory, strenuous physical activity restricted but able to perform sedentary gentle activities); (f) correctly understand Spanish; (g) show their approval by signing the informed consent; (h) participants must have submitted attributable to AIs musculoskeletal disorders (i) the painkillers were prescibed to the patients following the usual care from guidelines in both arms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Intervention</title><p id="Par39">For this trial we have used data obtained between May 2016 and September 2016. All recruited participants were surveyed by the same trained interviewer, completing a data collection sheet about various sociodemographic and anthropometric variables. Partients as well filled self-report questionnaires about their mental state, their profile of mood state (POMS), fatigue evaluation (Quickpiper) and quality of life (EORTC QLQ-C30). After completion, we used a pressure algometer to assess their PPT and an analog dynamometer to measure grip strength of both hands. Then we used the VAS scale to evaluate their pain and three functional questionnaires were filled: Spine Functional Index (SFI), Upper Limb Functional Index (ULFI) and Backache Disability Index (BADIX). After that, participants went to nursing consultation, where it was extracted a blood sample. Each participant was then randomly assigned to one of the two groups that made this pilot study. Group A-Intervention Group: Real NMT over the areas in which they manifested pain. Group B-Placebo group: Sham NMT in the painful areas without any therapeutic technique.</p><p id="Par40">The user received an envelope which contained a number, one or two, to determine which group would be part. The first group (A) received a decalogue of health advice (general, to lead an active lifestyle), drawn from the best available evidence, and was applied several strips of neuromuscular taping over the areas in which they manifested pain (cervical, lumbosacral, both or wrist-forearm). The physiotherapist who performed the tapping was always the same, had the proper certification for application and counted on 10&#x000a0;years of experience in this technique. The material used for this trial (Cure Tape&#x000ae;, Fysiotape BV Netherlands. Medical Device Class A, registration number NL/CA01/04&#x02013;07434) is waterproof, breathable and adhesive. Its composition is latex-free and has elasticity of 130&#x02013;140%. 5&#x000a0;cm wide tape. The color blue was used (0.51&#x000a0;mm thickness and density 440.56&#x000a0;kg/m3).</p><p id="Par41">Depending on the participant symptoms, the taping were placed on four possible locations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>):<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par42">Carpal Tunnel.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par43">Lumbar and cervical if morning stiffness.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par44">Lumbar bandage.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par45">Cervical bandage.</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Different applications of NMT; 1, Application for carpal tunnel syndrome. 2, Application for cervical pain. 3, Application for lower back pain. 4, Sham application for carpal tunnel syndrome. 5, Sham application for cervical pain. 6, Sham application for lower back pain</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2236_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par46">When the participant presented CTS diagnosed properly, a possible application involves placing two strips. The first helps relax the long palmar muscle using a 5 cms. Wide strip cut into an &#x0201c;X&#x0201d; shape. The crossing point was applied in neutral position on the palmar wrist area. The short anchors were placed on the little finger hypothenar region and thenar eminence of the thumb; we ask the participant to perform elbow extension, forearm supination and hand dorsiflexion, and then apply the functional strips surrounding the entire muscle belly, to the medial epicondyle of the humerus. The second strip is placed with a technique to increase the space in the wrist, for which we use a strip of 5 cms. Wide cut into an &#x0201c;I&#x0201d; shape. During laying on wrist, this is held in neutral position. The base is applied without tension from the front side of the radius, on the back of the wrist toward the front side of the ulna. Dorsally, a 50% stretch of was used to apply. There will be a gap between the base and the anchor. There will be a clearance between the base and the anchor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p><p id="Par47">In the case of localized lower back pain, this was the TNM technique used: two blue 5 cms. Wide strips cut into an &#x0201c;I&#x0201d; shape, without traction were applied from the origin of the lumbar erector spinae (iliocostalislumborum) to its insertion, to relax it. The base of the strip was applied to the sacral region (at the S1) in the neutral position. Then the participant was asked to take the spine into flexion and for each functional strip with slight lateral flexion; the tape was then used on one side paravertebrally on muscle belly in the direction of the cranium. The same procedure was then applied to the other side [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par48">In cases where the pain was located in the cervical area, the participant received a standardized therapeutic TNM application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. The first strip was a blue Y-strip (a 5 cms. Wide base strip cut into two 2,5 cms. tails) placed over the posterior cervical extensor muscles and applied from the insertion to origin without tension. The participant was placed in a sitting position and each tail of the strip was applied with her neck in a position of cervical flexion and heterolateral slight rotation. The laying direction was from the first dorsal vertebrae (T1-T2) toward cranial, to the upper-cervical region. Then we use a technique to relax the supraspinatus muscle. For this we utilized two 5 cms. Wide strips cut into an &#x0201c;I&#x0201d; shape that were applied without tension from the head of the humerus to the medial border of the scapula. For placement of functional strips we ask the participant to take the arm into adduction, and scapular girdle in detraction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Participants were explained that they should keep the application for 7&#x000a0;days.</p><p id="Par49">The second group (B) was also given the decalogue of healthy tips and were applied a sham NMT that were placed in the painful areas without any therapeutic technique. The material and color of sham strips was the same, but these were more narrow (1.25 cms. wide) and shorter. They also were placed with the patient in neutral position, without utilizing muscle or increase space tecchnique used in the experimental group. After the taping intervention, we register again algometry, VAS and dynamometry. Both groups were called again to repeat all evaluations and reapply tape to 7&#x000a0;days. This process of data collection was carried out again at 5&#x000a0;weeks of the start of the study, along with the second and final blood extraction.</p><p id="Par50">The purpose of this intervention was to improve participants pain, through the reduction by 20% of the values of their visual analogue scale (VAS) at various points, to relieve symptoms and reduce AIs therapy dropouts.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Measurements</title><p id="Par51">Medical and demographic information brought us information about their age, marital status, education level, anthropometric data, surgery and complementary treatments for BC. All these variables will be collected only once, on the first visit, prior to randomization. Plasma proteins.</p><p id="Par52">Plasma proteins associated with arthralgia, cancer&#x02013;related fatigue and insomnia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], such a C-reactive protein (CRP) and creatine kinase (CK) were analysed by proteomic analysis. To perform this analysis was used a surface-enhanced laser desorption/ionization, a mass spectrometry (MS) technique, followed by further sample processing using one-dimensional gels and trypsin digest for protein identification using liquid chromatography and database searching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">Pain threshold pressure (PPT) is described as the minimum amount of pressure with which an initial feeling of pressure switches to pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">Dynamometer.This strength evaluation has been previously used to measure the loss of strength in BCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], including cases where patients are undergoing hormone therapy with AIs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Patient-report outcomes</title><p id="Par55">Profile of Mood States (POMS). This questionnaire completed by patients is used frequently for the study of BCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par56">QuickPIPER. Questionnaire utilized to determine the degree of fatigue and it phenotype. The test-retest reliability of this tool is very good (<italic>r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.947, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par57">EORTC QLQ-C30. It is a specific questionnaire to assess quality of life (QoL) of patients diagnosed with cancer. In some trials, QoL was further defined by specific impacts such as physical functioning. Also it serves to evaluate symptoms (most often pain) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</p><p id="Par58">Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). It is a tool that was designed in order to allow a subjective assessment of pain. Previous studies have shown that this scale has adequate psychometric properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par59">Spine functional Index (SFI-Sp). In this pilot study we have used the Spanish version (SFI-Sp), because it has proven to be a valid and reliable measure of the spinal region result [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">Upper Limbs Functioal Index (ULFI-Sp). This trial used the Spanish version (ULFI-Sp). This quiz has proven useful for evaluating patients with disorders of the upper extremities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par61">Backache Disability Index (BADIX). This index contains a score of five movements of the trunk in an upright position that translate into back pain index (BAI) and a register of &#x0201c;morning stiffness in the back&#x0201d; (MBS). Their sum gives the BADIX [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] and appears to be a valid and reliable tool for the evaluation of morning stiffness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Sample size</title><p id="Par62">Version 3.1&#x000a0;G Power was used to estimate sample size. A minimum of 78 subjects per group will be needed &#x0201c;a priori&#x0201d; to have sufficient statistical power (80%), alpha error (0.05) and size 0.4 effect on the visual analog pain scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Statistical treatment</title><p id="Par63">For analysis of the results it was developed a database using information gathered from participants notebooks, algometers, dynamometers and self-administered questionnaires (QuickPIPER, POMS, quality of life, VAS, SFI, ULFI and BADIX). Once intervention phase, descriptive statistics was performed with measures of central tendency and dispersion of the study variables. After this became an inferential analysis between the outcome variables in both groups. The means and a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to asses differences between groups as well as the <italic>p</italic> value. The mean differences between the self-reported questionnaires as part of the intra-group analysis were examined. Finally t student and asymptotic significance was used to investigate the relationships between these variables at different study times. The means and a one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to asses differences between groups as well as the p value. The mean differences between the self-reported questionnaires as part of the intra-group analysis were examined. Finally t student and asymptotic significance was used to investigate the relationships between these variables at different study times. SPSS version 15.0&#x000a0;V for Windows.7 was used for data analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Demographic and clinical data (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>)</title><p id="Par64">A total of 40 postmenopausal BCS, with a mean age of 66,30&#x000a0;years (50&#x02013;82), enrolled and underwent baseline evaluation between May and September 2016. Both, the experimental and control groups had 20 participants. Women were married (47,5%), had primary/secondary level education (40%) and only 22,5% were employed. If we look at the data that inform us whether the body mass had a healthy value observed that 75% were overweight, mean waist circumference was 97,63 cms. and the hip, 110.19 cms. Most women had stage II BC (40%), and received both radiation and chemoterapy (47,5%) as adyuvant treatment after surgery. Respect to hormone therapy, 9 (22,5%) women had taken Tamoxifen prior to AIs, whereas the remaining 31 (77,5%) had only taken AIs. Additionally, the most common AI was Letrozol - Femara &#x000ae;, 57,5% of the participants were taken it and the mean duration of treatment at the time of starting the intervention 17.40&#x000a0;months. None patient received physiotherapy treatment. If we value comorbidities present at the time the study began, besides the pain at different levels ((cervical (82.5%), shoulder (85%), lumbar (75%)and hands/wrist (62.5%)) the most frequent were hypertension (60%) and vascular disorders (57.5%). The ANOVA revealed that groups were not significantly different on age, those related to the assessment of overweight and obesity (weight, height, body mass index, waist perimeter and hip perimeter) and tamoxifen and AIs treatment duration. Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> summarises the patients demographic and clinical data. We compared the means of all outcome variables in the baseline and there were no significant differences in any of them, except BAI (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05), although both groups are not as similar as they were their descriptive characteristics, possibly due to the small sample size. As can be observed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, the groups were similar and comparable at the outset.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Participants Flow Diagram</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2236_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Mean or number (%). Range (Min-Max) and ANOVA of demographic and clinical baseline characteristics of groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Characteristic</th><th/><th colspan="2">Groups</th><th/></tr><tr><th>Total (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;40)</th><th>Experimental (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>Control (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>F <italic>(p)</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Age (yr). mean (Range)</td><td>66.30 (50&#x02013;82)</td><td>67.80 (50&#x02013;82)</td><td>64.80 (54&#x02013;81)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.95 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Marital Status. number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Single</td><td>5 (12.5)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Married</td><td>19 (47.5)</td><td>14 (70)</td><td>5 (25)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Divorced/Separated</td><td>6 (15)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Widow</td><td>10 (25)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Education level. Number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Any study</td><td>11 (27.5)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Primary/ Secondary School</td><td>16 (40)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td>9 (45)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vocational training/ Qualifications</td><td>8 (20)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>5 (25)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;University/ Superior education</td><td>5 (12.5)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Employed. number (%)</td><td>9 (22.5)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Weight (Kg). mean. (Range)*</td><td>72.98 (44&#x02013;130)</td><td>72.71 (53.2&#x02013;97)</td><td>73.25 (44&#x02013;130)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.01 <italic>(0.91)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Height (cm). mean. (Range)*</td><td>159.60 (147&#x02013;171)</td><td>159.25 (148&#x02013;170)</td><td>159.95 (147&#x02013;171)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.11 <italic>(0.74)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Body Mass Index (BMI). mean. (Range)</td><td>28.17 (16.17&#x02013;47.79)</td><td>28.80 (20.70&#x02013;39.91)</td><td>28.62 (16.17&#x02013;47.79)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.01 <italic>(0.92)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Overweight (BMI&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;25). number (%)</td><td>30 (75)</td><td>14 (70)</td><td>16 (80)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Waist perimeter (cm.). mean. (Range)</td><td>97.63 (68&#x02013;147)</td><td>95.80 (75&#x02013;120)</td><td>99.45 (68&#x02013;147)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.69 <italic>(0.41)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Hip perimeter (cm). mean. (Range)</td><td>110.19 (89&#x02013;145)</td><td>111.85 (93&#x02013;130)</td><td>108.53 (89&#x02013;145)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.72 <italic>(0.40)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Tumor grade. Number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Grade I</td><td>8 (20)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Grade II</td><td>16 (40)</td><td>9 (45)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Grade III</td><td>14 (35)</td><td>5 (25)</td><td>9 (45)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Grade IV</td><td>2 (5)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Kind of treatments. Number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Surgery (S)</td><td>3 (7.5)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;S+ Chemotherapy (ChT)</td><td>3 (7.5)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;S+ Radiotherapy (RT)</td><td>15 (37.5)</td><td>10 (50)</td><td>5 (25)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;S+ ChT+ RT</td><td>19 (47.5)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td>12 (60)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Previous Tamoxifen (TMX). number (%)</td><td>9 (22.5)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>TMX treatment duration (mo). mean. (Range)</td><td>4.46 (0&#x02013;32)</td><td>4.30 (0&#x02013;32)</td><td>4.64 (0&#x02013;25)</td><td char="(" align="char">0.01 <italic>(0.91)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Aromatase Inhibitors (AIs). number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anastrozole (Arimidex&#x000ae;)</td><td>12 (30)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td>8 (40)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Letrozole (Femara&#x000ae;)</td><td>23 (57.5)</td><td>14 (70)</td><td>9 (45)</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Exemestane (Aromasin&#x000ae;)</td><td>5 (12.5)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td>3 (15)</td></tr><tr><td>AIs treatment duration (mo). mean. (Range)</td><td>17.40 (2&#x02013;52)</td><td>15.25 (2&#x02013;52)</td><td>19.55 (2&#x02013;44)</td><td char="(" align="char">1.25 <italic>(0.27)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Comorbidities. number (%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cervical pain</td><td>33 (82.5)</td><td>19 (95)</td><td>14 (70)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Shoulder pain</td><td>34 (85)</td><td>18 (90)</td><td>16 (80)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Lumbar pain</td><td>30 (75)</td><td>17 (85)</td><td>13 (65)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Hands/ Wrist pain</td><td>25 (62.5)</td><td>12 (60)</td><td>13 (65)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Hypertension</td><td>24 (60)</td><td>14 (70)</td><td>10 (50)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Heart disease</td><td>8 (20)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td>5 (25)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Circulation problems</td><td>23 (57.5)</td><td>12 (60)</td><td>11 (55)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Thyroid problems</td><td>6 (15)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Stroke</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Diabetes</td><td>5 (12.5)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Gastric/ duodenal ulcer</td><td>1 (2.5)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>1 (5)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Breathing problems</td><td>6 (15)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Parkinson</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cognitive impairment</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td>0 (0)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Migraine/chronic headache</td><td>7 (17.5)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td>3 (15)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vision problems</td><td>13 (32.5)</td><td>7 (35)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Hearing problems</td><td>10 (25)</td><td>6 (30)</td><td>4 (20)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Lymphedema</td><td>4 (10)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td>2 (10)</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Self-reported weight and height</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Mean (CI 95%) and analysis of variance (ANOVA) of baseline, Patient-Reported Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Self-Reported Outcomes</th><th colspan="3">T1: Baseline Evaluation</th></tr><tr><th/><th>Experimental (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>Control (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>ANOVA F(<italic>p</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4">POMS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tension/Anxiety</td><td>9.85 (7.39&#x02013;12.30)</td><td>7.00 (3.87&#x02013;10.12)</td><td>2.25 <italic>(0.14)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Depression/Dejection</td><td>12.90 (7.51&#x02013;18.28)</td><td>9.10 (4.44&#x02013;13.75)</td><td>1.24 <italic>(0.27)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anger/Hostility</td><td>9.50 (5.98&#x02013;13.01)</td><td>8.65 (4.67&#x02013;12.62)</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.73)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vigor/Activity</td><td>24.40 (20.23&#x02013;28.56)</td><td>28.75 (25.34&#x02013;32.15)</td><td>2.86 <italic>(0.09)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue/Inertia</td><td>11.75 (9.51&#x02013;13.98)</td><td>9.20 (7.26&#x02013;11.13)</td><td>3.25 <italic>(0.07)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Confusion/Bewilderment</td><td>8.60 (5.37&#x02013;11.82)</td><td>6.55 (2.91&#x02013;10.18)</td><td>0.77 <italic>(0.38)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;TMD</td><td>128.20 (113.47&#x02013;142.93)</td><td>111.75 (96.55&#x02013;126.95)</td><td>2.64 <italic>(0.11)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">EORTC QLQ-C30</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Global health status/QoL</td><td>53.74 (41.84&#x02013;65.64)</td><td>57.08 (46.77&#x02013;67.38)</td><td>0.19 <italic>(0.66)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Functional scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Physical functioning</td><td>67.61 (56.17&#x02013;79.04)</td><td>76.91 (67.47&#x02013;86.35)</td><td>1.72 <italic>(0.19)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Role functioning</td><td>75.83 (60.75&#x02013;90.90)</td><td>79.16 (64.87&#x02013;93.45)</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.73)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Emotional functioning</td><td>72.56 (59.55&#x02013;85,57)</td><td>79.68 (69.72&#x02013;89.63)</td><td>0.82 <italic>(0.36)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cognitive functioning</td><td>81.66 (69.29&#x02013;94.03)</td><td>79.99 (67.96&#x02013;92.02)</td><td>0.04 <italic>(0.84)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Social functioning</td><td>79.99 (64.68&#x02013;95.30)</td><td>90.83 (83.04&#x02013;98.62)</td><td>1.74 <italic>(0.19)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">Symptoms scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue</td><td>51.07 (40.48&#x02013;61.65)</td><td>40.53 (30.50&#x02013;50.56)</td><td>2.28 <italic>(0.13)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Nausea and vomiting</td><td>0.87 (0.96&#x02013;2.71)</td><td>1.66 (0.73&#x02013;4.06)</td><td>0.29 <italic>(0.59)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Pain</td><td>50.83 (38.31&#x02013;63.35)</td><td>38.33 (27.27&#x02013;49.39)</td><td>2.45 <italic>(0.12)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dyspnoea</td><td>6.66 (&#x02212;4.18&#x02013;17.52)</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;2.84&#x02013;19.50)</td><td>0.05 <italic>(0.82)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Insomnia</td><td>53.33 (37.00&#x02013;69.65)</td><td>44.99 (25.87&#x02013;64.12)</td><td>0.48 <italic>(0.49)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Appetite loss</td><td>14.99 (2.12&#x02013;27.87)</td><td>14.99 (3.15&#x02013;26.84)</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Constipation</td><td>4.99 (&#x02212;2.63&#x02013;12.63)</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;1.63&#x02013;18.29)</td><td>0.30 <italic>(0.58)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Diarrhoea</td><td>11.66 (0.04&#x02013;23.28)</td><td>6.66 (&#x02212;2.93&#x02013;16.28)</td><td>0.48 <italic>(0.49)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Financial difficulties</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;3.93&#x02013;20.60)</td><td>14.99 (2.12&#x02013;27.87)</td><td>0.61 <italic>(0.43)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;VAS</td><td>7.40 (6.82&#x02013;7.98)</td><td>6.65 (5.98&#x02013;7.32)</td><td>3.17 <italic>(0.08)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SFI</td><td>57.40 (49.59&#x02013;65.20)</td><td>56.90 (47.66&#x02013;66.13)</td><td>0.007 <italic>(0.93)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ULFI</td><td>61.80 (53.93&#x02013;69.66)</td><td>69.60 (62.07&#x02013;77.12)</td><td>2.25 <italic>(0.14)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BAI</td><td>0.59 (0.47&#x02013;0.71)</td><td>0.42 (0.28&#x02013;0.55)</td><td>4.07 <italic>(0.05)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;MBS</td><td>0.40 (0.23&#x02013;0.56)</td><td>0.33 (0.21&#x02013;0.44)</td><td>0.53 <italic>(0.46)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BADIX</td><td>0.53 (0.41&#x02013;0.65)</td><td>0.40 (0.28&#x02013;0.51)</td><td>2.93 <italic>(0.09)</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations: POMS</italic> Profile of Mood States, <italic>TMD</italic> Total Emotional Distortion, <italic>EORTC QLQ-C30</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORT) Quality of Life Questionnaire QLQ-C30, <italic>QoL</italic> Quality of Life, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analogue Scale, <italic>SFI</italic> Spine Functional Index, <italic>ULFI</italic> Upper Limb Functional Index, <italic>BAI</italic> Backache Index, <italic>MBS</italic> Morning Stiffness Score, <italic>BADIX</italic> Backache Disability Index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Changes in quality of life (EORTC QLQ-C30), profile of mood states POMS, visual analogue scale (VAS) and functional index (SFI-Sp, ULFI-Sp and BADIX)</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Changes between control and intervention groups</title><sec id="FPar1"><title>Time 1-time 2</title><p id="Par65">In this intergroup analysis we found no differences between the groups a week later the first intervention (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Mean (CI 95%) and analysis of variance (ANOVA) of baseline. 1 and 5&#x000a0;week Patient-Reported Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Self-Reported Outcomes</th><th colspan="3">T2: 1&#x000a0;week Evaluation</th><th colspan="3">T3: 5&#x000a0;week Evaluation</th></tr><tr><th/><th>Experimental (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>Control (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>ANOVA F(<italic>p</italic>)</th><th>Experimental (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>Control (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;20)</th><th>ANOVA F(<italic>p</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7">POMS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tension/Anxiety</td><td>6.05 (3.26&#x02013;8.83)</td><td>6.50 (3.52&#x02013;9.47)</td><td>0.05 <italic>(0.81)</italic></td><td>5.40 (2.77&#x02013;8.02)</td><td>6.50 (3.89&#x02013;9.10)</td><td>0.38 <italic>(0.53)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Depression/Dejection</td><td>8.00 (3.76&#x02013;12.23)</td><td>10.05 (5.26&#x02013;14.83)</td><td>0.45 <italic>(0.50)</italic></td><td>6.35 (2.71&#x02013;9.98)</td><td>9.30 (4.41&#x02013;14.19)</td><td>1.02 <italic>(0.31)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anger/Hostility</td><td>5.40 (3.20&#x02013;7.59)</td><td>5.75 (2.51&#x02013;8.98)</td><td>0.03 <italic>(0.85)</italic></td><td>4.25 (2.51&#x02013;5.98)</td><td>6.60 (2.69&#x02013;10.50)</td><td>1.32 <italic>(0.25)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vigor/Activity</td><td>24.80 (20.46&#x02013;29.13)</td><td>26.70 (23.13&#x02013;30.26)</td><td>0.50 <italic>(0.48)</italic></td><td>28.10 (24.09&#x02013;32.10)</td><td>25.90 (21.85&#x02013;29.94)</td><td>0.65 <italic>(0.42)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue/Inertia</td><td>8.85 (6.49&#x02013;11.20)</td><td>8.75 (6.56&#x02013;10.93)</td><td>0.004 <italic>(0.94)</italic></td><td>6.40 (4.33&#x02013;8.46)</td><td>8.00 (5.76&#x02013;10.23)</td><td>1.21 <italic>(0.27)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Confusion/Bewilderment</td><td>5.95 (3.10&#x02013;8.79)</td><td>7.10 (3.52&#x02013;10.67)</td><td>0.27 <italic>(0.60)</italic></td><td>3.75 (0.84&#x02013;6.65)</td><td>5.00 (1.55&#x02013;8.44)</td><td>0.33 <italic>(0.56)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;TMD</td><td>109.90 (97.14&#x02013;122.66)</td><td>111. 30 (95.33&#x02013;127.27)</td><td>0.02 <italic>(0.88)</italic></td><td>98.05 (85.33&#x02013;110.77)</td><td>109.40 (93.87&#x02013;124.93)</td><td>1.40 <italic>(0.24)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">EORTC QLQ-C30</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Global health status/QoL</td><td>67.49 (59.50&#x02013;75.48)</td><td>63.74 (56.55&#x02013;70.93)</td><td>0.53 <italic>(0.47)</italic></td><td>76.66 (69.66&#x02013;83.66)</td><td>62.91 (56.15&#x02013;69.66)</td><td>8.75 <italic>(0.005)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">Functional scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Physical functioning</td><td>78.68 (69.12&#x02013;88.24)</td><td>74.03 (62.34&#x02013;85.71)</td><td>0.41 <italic>(0.52)</italic></td><td>80.18 (69.45&#x02013;90.90)</td><td>75.03 (63.70&#x02013;86.35)</td><td>0.47 <italic>(0.49)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Role functioning</td><td>85.83 (73.88&#x02013;97.77)</td><td>70.83 (54.85&#x02013;86.81)</td><td>2.47 <italic>(0.12)</italic></td><td>91.66 (82.71&#x02013;100.61)</td><td>79.16 (68.76&#x02013;89.56)</td><td>3.63 <italic>(0.06)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Emotional functioning</td><td>83.78 (75.36&#x02013;92.20)</td><td>77.96 (65.83&#x02013;90.09)</td><td>0.68 <italic>(0.41)</italic></td><td>85.90 (78.35&#x02013;93.45)</td><td>81.36 (71.89&#x02013;90.83)</td><td>0.61 <italic>(0.43)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cognitive functioning</td><td>91.76 (82.02&#x02013;101.30)</td><td>84.99 (73.42&#x02013;96.56)</td><td>0.85 <italic>(0.36)</italic></td><td>92.49 (84.70&#x02013;100.28)</td><td>84.16 (72.71&#x02013;95.61)</td><td>1.58 <italic>(0.21)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Social functioning</td><td>87.49 (74.87&#x02013;100.12)</td><td>86.66 (75.46&#x02013;97.86)</td><td>0.01 <italic>(0.91)</italic></td><td>91.66 (81.70&#x02013;101.63)</td><td>94.99 (89.28&#x02013;100.71)</td><td>0.36 <italic>(0.54)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">Symptoms scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue</td><td>26.62 (18.62&#x02013;34.61)</td><td>37.76 (28.16&#x02013;47.37)</td><td>3.48 <italic>(0.07)</italic></td><td>21.62 (12.46&#x02013;30.78)</td><td>39.42 (28.55&#x02013;50.30)</td><td>6.87 <italic>(0.01)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Nausea and vomiting</td><td>0.00 (0.00&#x02013;0.00)</td><td>0.83 (&#x02212;0.91&#x02013;2.57)</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.32)</italic></td><td>1.66 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.73&#x02013;4.06)</td><td>0.00 (0.00&#x02013;0.00)</td><td>2.11 <italic>(0.15)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Pain</td><td>29.16 (17.88&#x02013;40.44)</td><td>31.66 (20.37&#x02013;42.95)</td><td>0.10 <italic>(0.74)</italic></td><td>19.99 (10.00&#x02013;29.94)</td><td>34.16 (24.20&#x02013;44.11)</td><td>4.41 <italic>(0.04)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dyspnoea</td><td>5.00 (&#x02212;5.46&#x02013;15.46)</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;2.84&#x02013;19.50)</td><td>0.20 <italic>(0.65)</italic></td><td>3.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;3.64&#x02013;10.30)</td><td>4.99 (&#x02212;&#x02009;2.63&#x02013;12.63)</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.73)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Insomnia</td><td>29.99 (14.89&#x02013;45.09)</td><td>29.99 (14.89&#x02013;45.09)</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td><td>23.33 (9.84&#x02013;36.81)</td><td>23.33 (8.92&#x02013;37.73)</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Appetite loss</td><td>11.66 (1.20&#x02013;22.12)</td><td>18.33 (1.95&#x02013;34.71)</td><td>0.51 <italic>(0.47)</italic></td><td>11.66 (1.20&#x02013;22.12)</td><td>14.99 (3.15&#x02013;26.84)</td><td>0.19 <italic>(0.66)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Constipation</td><td>1.66 (&#x02212;1.82&#x02013;5.15)</td><td>9.99 (&#x02212;0.24&#x02013;20.24)</td><td>2.59 <italic>(0.11)</italic></td><td>1.66 (&#x02212;1.82&#x02013;5.15)</td><td>6.66 (&#x02212;2.93&#x02013;16.26)</td><td>1.04 <italic>(0.31)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Diarrhoea</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;0.24&#x02013;16.91)</td><td>4.99 (&#x02212;2.63&#x02013;12.63)</td><td>0.36 <italic>(0.54)</italic></td><td>3.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;1.46&#x02013;8.13)</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;0.24&#x02013;16.91)</td><td>1.13 <italic>(0.29)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Financial difficulties</td><td>3.33 (3.64&#x02013;10.30)</td><td>8.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;1.63&#x02013;18.29)</td><td>0.74 <italic>(0.39)</italic></td><td>3.33 (&#x02212;&#x02009;3.64&#x02013;10.30)</td><td>4.99 (&#x02212;&#x02009;2.63&#x02013;12.63)</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.73)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;VAS</td><td>6.10 (5.44&#x02013;6.76)</td><td>6.15 (5.26&#x02013;7.04)</td><td>0.009 <italic>(0.92)</italic></td><td>4.90 (4.03&#x02013;5.77)</td><td>6.45 (5.65&#x02013;7.25)</td><td>7.56 <italic>(0.009)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SFI</td><td>67.20 (60.36&#x02013;74.03)</td><td>59.80 (53.77&#x02013;65.82)</td><td>2.88 <italic>(0.09)</italic></td><td>66.80 (57.08&#x02013;76.51)</td><td>59.20 (53.41&#x02013;64.98)</td><td>1.97 <italic>(0.16)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ULFI</td><td>72.60 (65.38&#x02013;79.81)</td><td>72.20 (67.36&#x02013;77.03)</td><td>0.009 <italic>(0.92)</italic></td><td>72.40 (62.64&#x02013;82.15)</td><td>70.60 (64.36&#x02013;76.83)</td><td>0.10 <italic>(0.74)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BAI</td><td>0.42 (0.32&#x02013;0.51)</td><td>0.44 (0.31&#x02013;0.57)</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.73)</italic></td><td>0.33 (0.24&#x02013;0.43)</td><td>0.40 (0.27&#x02013;0.56)</td><td>0.83 <italic>(0.36)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;MBS</td><td>0.19 (0.59&#x02013;0.32)</td><td>0.33 (0.19&#x02013;0.46)</td><td>2.46 <italic>(0.12)</italic></td><td>0.17 (0.05&#x02013;0.28)</td><td>0.33 (0.18&#x02013;0.47)</td><td>3.23 <italic>(0.08)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BADIX</td><td>0.35 (0.25&#x02013;0.45)</td><td>0.42 (0.30&#x02013;0.54)</td><td>0.84 <italic>(0.36)</italic></td><td>0.28 (0.19&#x02013;0.37)</td><td>0.39 (0.26&#x02013;0.51)</td><td>2.16 <italic>(0.14)</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations: POMS</italic> Profile of Mood States, <italic>TMD</italic> Total Emotional Distortion, <italic>EORTC QLQ-C30</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORT) Quality of Life Questionnaire QLQ-C30, <italic>QoL</italic> Quality of Life, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analogue Scale, <italic>SFI</italic> Spine Functional Index, <italic>ULFI</italic> Upper Limb Functional Index, <italic>BAI</italic> Backache Index, <italic>MBS</italic> Morning Stiffness Score, <italic>BADIX</italic> Backache Disability Index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Time 1-time 3</title><p id="Par66">Observing the values of ANOVA in T3 (at 5&#x000a0;weeks of the start of the study, after the second intervention), we found significant differences favouring the experimental group with respect to variables related to QoL, as Global health status / QoL (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.005), fatigue (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01) and pain (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04)). Moreover we found significative differences on the visual analogue scale (VAS) (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009). On the other hand, we did not found differneces related to Profile of Moods State (POMS) neither functional index (SFI, ULFI, BAI, MBS o BADIX).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Changes within experimental group</title><sec id="FPar3"><title>Time 1-time 2</title><p id="Par67">When analyzing intra-group variations from the baseline (T1) to the first intervention (T2), in the experimental group we observed that intra-group changes occur early, after the first intervention, in variables such as the state questionnaire (POMS), except for the vigor-activity variable. Intra-group changes occur after the first intervention in several variables relating to the quality of life such as global health status (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002), several functional scales (role (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03), emotional (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.008)), symptoms such as fatigue (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), pain (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) and insomnia (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009). Significatibe differences were observed in the VAS punctuation (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) and at different functional indexes: the spine (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), the upper limb (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) and those that value disability backache (BADIX (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), BAI (0.001) and MBS (0.003)) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Mean and Range T<sub>1</sub> (Baseline). T<sub>2</sub> (1&#x000a0;week after) and T<sub>3</sub> (5&#x000a0;week after); Mean Differences. t-distribution. and <italic>p</italic> values of T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>2</sub> and T<sub>1</sub>- T<sub>3</sub> for within-group change scores in Patient-Reported Outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Self-Reported Outcomes</th><th colspan="7">Experimental</th><th colspan="7">Control</th></tr><tr><th>T<sub>1</sub></th><th>T<sub>2</sub></th><th>T<sub>3</sub></th><th>Mean differences<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>2</sub></th><th>t (<italic>p</italic>) value<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>2</sub></th><th>Mean differences<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>3</sub></th><th>t (<italic>p</italic>) value<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>3</sub></th><th>T<sub>1</sub></th><th>T<sub>2</sub></th><th>T<sub>3</sub></th><th>Mean differences<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>2</sub></th><th>t (<italic>p</italic>) value<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>2</sub></th><th>Mean differences<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>3</sub></th><th>t (<italic>p</italic>) value<break/>T<sub>1</sub> - T<sub>3</sub></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="15">POMS</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Tension/Anxiety</td><td>9.85 (0&#x02013;17)</td><td>6.05 (&#x02212;4&#x02013;17)</td><td>5.40 (&#x02212;4&#x02013;17)</td><td>3.80</td><td>3.98 <italic>(0.001)</italic></td><td>4.45</td><td>4.45 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>7.00 (&#x02212;2&#x02013;24)</td><td>6.5 (&#x02212;3&#x02013;20)</td><td>6.5 (&#x02212;&#x02009;2&#x02013;19)</td><td>0.50</td><td>0.45 <italic>(0.65)</italic></td><td>0.5</td><td>0.63 <italic>(0.53)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Depression/Dejection</td><td>12.90 (0&#x02013;40)</td><td>8 (0&#x02013;31)</td><td>6.35 (0&#x02013;24)</td><td>4.90</td><td>3.54 <italic>(0.002)</italic></td><td>6.55</td><td>3.90 <italic>(0.001)</italic></td><td>9.10 (0&#x02013;36)</td><td>10.05 (0&#x02013;33)</td><td>9.3 (0&#x02013;33)</td><td>&#x02212;0.95</td><td>&#x02212;0.62 <italic>(0.54)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;0.2</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;0.13 <italic>(0.89)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Anger/Hostility</td><td>9.50 (0&#x02013;26)</td><td>5.40 (0&#x02013;15)</td><td>4.25 (1&#x02013;12)</td><td>4.10</td><td>3.2 <italic>(0.005)</italic></td><td>5.25</td><td>3.63 <italic>(0.002)</italic></td><td>8.65 (0&#x02013;25)</td><td>5.75 (0&#x02013;28)</td><td>6.6 (0&#x02013;28)</td><td>2.90</td><td>2.05 <italic>(0.05)</italic></td><td>2.05</td><td>1.54 <italic>(0.13)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Vigor/Activity</td><td>24.40 (10&#x02013;42)</td><td>24.80 (9&#x02013;43)</td><td>28.10 (10&#x02013;43)</td><td>&#x02212;0.4</td><td>&#x02212;0.28 <italic>(0.78)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;3.70</td><td>&#x02212;2.98 <italic>(0.008)</italic></td><td>28.75 (17&#x02013;43)</td><td>26.70 (11&#x02013;40)</td><td>25.9 (11&#x02013;40)</td><td>2.05</td><td>1.91 <italic>(0.07)</italic></td><td>2.85</td><td>2.18 <italic>(0.04)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue/Inertia</td><td>11.75 (2&#x02013;21)</td><td>8.85 (0&#x02013;21)</td><td>6.40 (0&#x02013;15)</td><td>2.90</td><td>2.86 <italic>(0.01)</italic></td><td>5.35</td><td>
<italic>4.42 (0.00)</italic>
</td><td>9.20 (2&#x02013;16)</td><td>8.75 (2&#x02013;16)</td><td>8.00 (0&#x02013;18)</td><td>0.45</td><td>0.56 <italic>(0.57)</italic></td><td>1.20</td><td>1.45 <italic>(0.16)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Confusion/Bewilderment</td><td>8.6 (0&#x02013;23)</td><td>5.95 (&#x02212;2&#x02013;19)</td><td>3.75 (&#x02212;3&#x02013;17)</td><td>2.65</td><td>2.80 <italic>(0.01)</italic></td><td>4.85</td><td>4.50 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>6.55 (&#x02212;3&#x02013;24)</td><td>7.10 (&#x02212;2&#x02013;24)</td><td>5.00 (&#x02212;&#x02009;2&#x02013;24)</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;0.55</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;0.72 <italic>(0.47)</italic></td><td>1.55</td><td>1.38 <italic>(0.18)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;TMD</td><td>128.20 (84&#x02013;189)</td><td>109.90 (80&#x02013;166)</td><td>98.05 (68&#x02013;153)</td><td>18.30</td><td>3.45 <italic>(0.003)</italic></td><td>30.15</td><td>
<italic>5.97 (0.00)</italic>
</td><td>111.75 (67&#x02013;193)</td><td>111.30 (68&#x02013;194)</td><td>109.4 (63&#x02013;194)</td><td>0.45</td><td>0.11 <italic>(0.90)</italic></td><td>2.35</td><td>0.53 <italic>(0.59)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="15">EORTC QLQ-C30</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Global health status/QoL</td><td>53.76 (0&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>67.49 (4&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>76.66 (50&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;13.75</td><td>&#x02212;3.62 <italic>(0.002)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;22.91</td><td>&#x02212;4.18 (0.00)</td><td>57.08 (0&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>63.74 (33.33&#x02013;91.66)</td><td>62.91 (33.33&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>&#x02212;6.66</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;1.39 <italic>(0.18)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;5.83</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;1.16 <italic>(0.25)</italic></td></tr><tr><td colspan="15">Functional scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Physical functioning</td><td>67.61 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>78.68 (27&#x02013;100)</td><td>80.18 (20&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;11.06</td><td>&#x02212;2.41 <italic>(0.26)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;12.56</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;2.75 (0.01)</td><td>76.91 (33.33&#x02013;100)</td><td>74.03 (27&#x02013;100)</td><td>75.03 (27&#x02013;100)</td><td>2.88</td><td>0.96 <italic>(0.34)</italic></td><td>1.88</td><td>0.82 <italic>(0.41)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Role functioning</td><td>75.83 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>85.83 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>91.66 (33.33&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;10</td><td>&#x02212;2.34 <italic>(0.03)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;15.83</td><td>&#x02212;3.22 (0.004)</td><td>79.16 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>70.83 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>79.16 (33&#x02013;100)</td><td>8.33</td><td>1.20 <italic>(0.24)</italic></td><td>0.001</td><td>0.00 (<italic>1.00)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Emotional functioning</td><td>72.56 (16.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>83.78 (50&#x02013;100)</td><td>85.90 (50&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;11.21</td><td>&#x02212;2.95 <italic>(0.008)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;13.33</td><td>&#x02212;2.53 (0.02)</td><td>79.68 (25&#x02013;100)</td><td>77.96 (25&#x02013;100)</td><td>81.36 (33.33&#x02013;100)</td><td>1.71</td><td>
<italic>0.39 (0.69)</italic>
</td><td>&#x02212;1.68</td><td>&#x02212;0.38 <italic>(0.70)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Cognitive functioning</td><td>81.66 (16.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>91.66 (16.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>92.49 (33.33&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;10</td><td>&#x02212;1.98 <italic>(0.62)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;10.83</td><td>&#x02212;2.66 (0.01)</td><td>79.99 (16.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>84.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>84.16 (16.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;5.00</td><td>&#x02212;1.37 <italic>(0.18)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;4.16</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;0.72 (<italic>0.48)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Social functioning</td><td>79.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>87.49 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>91.66 (33.33&#x02013;100)</td><td>&#x02212;7.50</td><td>&#x02212;1.69 <italic>(0.10)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;11.66</td><td>&#x02212;2.40 (0.02)</td><td>90.83 (50&#x02013;100)</td><td>86.66 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>94.99 (66.66&#x02013;100)</td><td>4.16</td><td>0.62 <italic>(0.54)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;4.16</td><td>
<italic>&#x02212;0.81 (0.42)</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td colspan="15">Symptoms scales</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fatigue</td><td>51.07 (11&#x02013;88.66)</td><td>26.62 (11&#x02013;77.66)</td><td>21.62 (0&#x02013;77.66)</td><td>24.45</td><td>5.66 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>29.44</td><td>7.25 (0.00)</td><td>40.53 (0&#x02013;77.77)</td><td>37.76 (0&#x02013;77.77)</td><td>39.42 (0&#x02013;77.77)</td><td>2.76</td><td>
<italic>0.75 (0.46)</italic>
</td><td>1.10</td><td>0.26 <italic>(0.79)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Nausea and vomiting</td><td>0.87 (0&#x02013;16.66)</td><td>0.00</td><td>1.75 (0&#x02013;16.66)</td><td>0.87</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;0.87</td><td>&#x02212;0.56 (0.57)</td><td>1.66 (0&#x02013;16.66)</td><td>0.83 (0&#x02013;16.66)</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.83</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td><td>1.66</td><td>1.45 <italic>(0.16)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Pain</td><td>50.83 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>29.16 (0&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>19.99 (066.66)</td><td>21.66</td><td>4.61 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>30.83</td><td>5.80 (0.00)</td><td>38.33 (0&#x02013;83.33)</td><td>31.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>34.16 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>6.66</td><td>1.32 <italic>(0.20)</italic></td><td>4.16</td><td>
<italic>1.04 (0.30)</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Dyspnoea</td><td>6.66 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>5.00 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>3.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>1.66</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td><td>3.33</td><td>1.45 (0.16)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>4.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td><td>3.33</td><td>
<italic>1.00 (0.33)</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Insomnia</td><td>53.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>29.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>23.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>23.33</td><td>2.89 <italic>(0.009)</italic></td><td>29.99</td><td>4.41 (0.00)</td><td>44.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>29.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>23.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>15</td><td>2.43 <italic>(0.02)</italic></td><td>21.66</td><td>3.32 <italic>(0.004)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Appetite loss</td><td>14.99 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>11.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>11.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>3.33</td><td>
<italic>0.69 (0.49)</italic>
</td><td>3.33</td><td>0.81 (0.42)</td><td>14.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>18.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>14.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>&#x02212;3.33</td><td>&#x02212;0.49 <italic>(0.62)</italic></td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Constipation</td><td>4.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>1.66 (0&#x02013;33.33)</td><td>1.66 (0&#x02013;33.33)</td><td>3.33</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td><td>3.33</td><td>0.80 (0.42)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>9.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>6.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>&#x02212;1.66</td><td>
<italic>&#x02212;0.32 (0.74)</italic>
</td><td>1.66</td><td>0.27 <italic>(0.78)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Diarrhoea</td><td>11.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>3.33 (0&#x02013;33.33)</td><td>3.33</td><td>0.62 <italic>(0.54)</italic></td><td>8.33</td><td>1.75 (0.09)</td><td>6.66 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>4.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>1.66</td><td>0.43 <italic>(0.66)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;1.66</td><td>&#x02212;0.37 <italic>(0.71)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Financial difficulties</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;100)</td><td>3.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>3.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>5.00</td><td>1.00 <italic>(0.33)</italic></td><td>5.00</td><td>1.00 (0.33)</td><td>14.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>8.33 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>4.99 (0&#x02013;66.66)</td><td>6.66</td><td>1.45 <italic>(0.16)</italic></td><td>9.99</td><td>1.83 <italic>(0.08)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;VAS</td><td>7.4 (5&#x02013;10)</td><td>6.1 (4&#x02013;9)</td><td>4.90 (1&#x02013;8)</td><td>1.30</td><td>
<italic>7.93 (0.00)</italic>
</td><td>
<italic>2.50</italic>
</td><td>8.01 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>6.65 (4&#x02013;9)</td><td>6.15 (2&#x02013;9)</td><td>6.45 (3&#x02013;9)</td><td>0.50</td><td>2.12 <italic>(0.47)</italic></td><td>0.20</td><td>1.16 <italic>(0.25)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;SFI</td><td>57.40 (8&#x02013;84)</td><td>67.20 (20&#x02013;84)</td><td>66.80 (0&#x02013;92)</td><td>&#x02212;9.8</td><td>&#x02212;5.24 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;9.40</td><td>&#x02212;1.74 <italic>(0.09)</italic></td><td>56.90 (6&#x02013;96)</td><td>59.80 (44&#x02013;88)</td><td>59.20 (40&#x02013;84)</td><td>&#x02212;2.90</td><td>
<italic>&#x02212;0.93 (0.36)</italic>
</td><td>&#x02212;2.30</td><td>&#x02212;0.65 <italic>(0.51)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;ULFI</td><td>61.80 (16&#x02013;84)</td><td>72.60 (28&#x02013;92)</td><td>72.40 (0&#x02013;92)</td><td>&#x02212;10.80</td><td>&#x02212;6.89 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;10.60</td><td>&#x02212;&#x02009;2.05 <italic>(0.05)</italic></td><td>69.60 (40&#x02013;100)</td><td>72.20 (48&#x02013;100)</td><td>70.60 (48&#x02013;96)</td><td>&#x02212;2.60</td><td>&#x02212;0.95 <italic>(0.35)</italic></td><td>&#x02212;1.00</td><td>&#x02212;0.26 <italic>(0.79)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BAI</td><td>0.59 (0.07&#x02013;1.00)</td><td>0.42 (0.13&#x02013;0.93)</td><td>0.33 (0.07&#x02013;0.93)</td><td>0.17</td><td>4.01 <italic>(0.001)</italic></td><td>0.25</td><td>4.52 (<italic>0.00)</italic></td><td>0.42 (0&#x02013;0.86)</td><td>0.44 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.40 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>&#x02212;0.02</td><td>
<italic>&#x02212;0.90 (0.37)</italic>
</td><td>0.01</td><td>0.44 <italic>(0.66)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;MBS</td><td>0.40 (0.00&#x02013;1.00)</td><td>0.19 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.17 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.21</td><td>3.46 <italic>(0.003)</italic></td><td>0.23</td><td>3.61 <italic>(0.002)</italic></td><td>0.33 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.33 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.33 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00 <italic>(1.00)</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;BADIX</td><td>0.53 (0.02&#x02013;1.00)</td><td>0.35 (0.01&#x02013;0.90)</td><td>0.28 (0.02&#x02013;0.90)</td><td>0.18</td><td>4.80 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>0.25</td><td>5.59 <italic>(0.00)</italic></td><td>0.40 (0&#x02013;0.80)</td><td>0.42 (0&#x02013;0.75)</td><td>0.39 (0&#x02013;0.75)</td><td>&#x02212;0.02</td><td>&#x02212;0.93 <italic>(0.36)</italic></td><td>0.01</td><td>0.49 <italic>(0.62)</italic></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations: POMS</italic> Profile of Mood States, <italic>TMD</italic> Total Emotional Distortion, <italic>EORTC QLQ-C30</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORT) Quality of Life Questionnaire QLQ-C30, <italic>QoL</italic> Quality of Life, <italic>VAS</italic> Visual Analogue Scale, <italic>SFI</italic> Spine Functional Index, <italic>ULFI</italic> Upper Limb Functional Index, <italic>BAI</italic> Backache Index, <italic>MBS</italic> Morning Stiffness Score, <italic>BADIX</italic> Backache Disability Index</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Time 1-time 3</title><p id="Par68">When analyzing intra-group variations from the baseline (T1) to the second intervention (T3), in the experimental group, we found significant differences in all aspects of the POMS, except for the variable vigor/activity. These statistically significant changes also occur in most of the variables evaluated in the EORTC QLQ-C30 quality of life questionnaire. Statistically significant changes were observed in the overall health status (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01); Physical functioning (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01), role (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004), emotional (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02), cognitive (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.01) and social (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02); We also observed differences in symptoms such as fatigue (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), pain, (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) insomnia (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) and changes in the EVA scale (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0). Changes were observed in almost all functional indexes, such as ULFI (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05), BAI (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0), MBS (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002) and BADIX (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Changes within control group</title><sec id="FPar5"><title>Time 1-time 2</title><p id="Par69">When analyzing intra-group variations from the baseline (T1) to the first intervention (T2), in the control group we observed that only significant differences were observed in the anger/hostility variable of the POMS scale (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05), and In the insomnia variable of the EORTC quality of life questionnaire (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.02) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Time 1-time 3</title><p id="Par70">When analyzing the intra-group variations from the baseline (T1) to the second intervention (T3), in the control group we observed that the benefit in the anger / hostility variable was not maintained until the end of the study (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.13), However, there were significant differences at the end of the intervention in the varibale vigor-activity (POMS scale) (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04), as well as in the insomnia variable of the EORTC quality of life questionnaire (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.004) (Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Changes in the dynamometry and pressure pain threshold</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Changes between control and intervention groups</title><p id="Par71">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> analyze the objective variables inter-group changes over 6 times in which we recorded these variables. The values of the hand grip strength have improved in the experimental group, both affects and healthy hand. Despite this strength gain that can be seen in the improvement of the means, the change is not statistically significant (healthy hand <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.54; affected hand <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77). In the control group hardly seen changes in the grip strength of the participants. Therefore, we can affirm that there were no statistically significant inter-group differences with respect to dynamometry, nor were differences observed with respect to the pain threshold.<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Change in grip strength (kg) and pressure pain threshold from baseline to 5&#x000a0;week neuromuscular taping therapy</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3">Measure</th><th colspan="4">Groups</th></tr><tr><th colspan="2">Experimental</th><th colspan="2">Control</th></tr><tr><th>Mean (CI 95%)</th><th>F(<italic>p</italic>)</th><th>Mean (CI 95%)</th><th>F(<italic>p</italic>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>HG Healthy Hand</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.80 (<italic>0.54</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.11 (<italic>0.98</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>16.45 (13.68&#x02013;19.21)</td><td/><td>18.70 (16.61&#x02013;20.78)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>16.70 (14.13&#x02013;19.26)</td><td/><td>18.32 (16.35&#x02013;20.29)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>17.31 (14.57&#x02013;20.05)</td><td/><td>17.90 (15.82&#x02013;19.98)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>17.65 (15.12&#x02013;20.17)</td><td/><td>18.20 (16.09&#x02013;20.30)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>19.07 (16.26&#x02013;21.88)</td><td/><td>18.80 (16.79&#x02013;20.80)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>19.12 (16.44&#x02013;21.80)</td><td/><td>18.45 (16.34&#x02013;20.55)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>HG Affected Hand</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.49 (<italic>0.77</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.18 (<italic>0.96</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>14.16 (10.99&#x02013;17.33)</td><td/><td>16.85 (14.58&#x02013;19.11)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>13.88 (11.24&#x02013;16.53)</td><td/><td>16.30 (14.09&#x02013;18.50)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>15.18 (12.43&#x02013;17.93)</td><td/><td>16.65 (14.35&#x02013;18.94)</td><td rowspan="2"/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>15.12 (12.55&#x02013;17.69)</td><td/><td>16.27 (14.03&#x02013;18.51)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>15.87 (13.23&#x02013;18.51)</td><td/><td>17.50 (15.24&#x02013;19.75)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>16.27 (13.50&#x02013;19.04)</td><td/><td>16.57 (14.50&#x02013;18.64)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Cervical PPT</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.35 (<italic>0.88</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.44 (<italic>0.81</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>11.96 (10.12&#x02013;13.80)</td><td/><td>12.31 (10.63&#x02013;13.99)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>12.37 (10.50&#x02013;14.23)</td><td/><td>11.80 (10.13&#x02013;13.46)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>10.93 (9.24&#x02013;12.62)</td><td/><td>12.08 (10.52&#x02013;13.63)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>11.35 (9.69&#x02013;13.01)</td><td/><td>11.07 (9.47&#x02013;12.66)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>11.73 (9.74&#x02013;13.71)</td><td/><td>11.47 (10.05&#x02013;12.88)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>11.34 (9.56&#x02013;13.12)</td><td/><td>11.13 (9.55&#x02013;12.71)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Lumbar PPT</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.08 (<italic>0.99</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.23 (<italic>0.94</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>13.76 (11.52&#x02013;16.00)</td><td/><td>15.43 (13.35&#x02013;17.50)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>14.38 (12.20&#x02013;16.56)</td><td/><td>14.50 (12.63&#x02013;16.37)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>14.05 (12.06&#x02013;16.04)</td><td/><td>15.06 (12.61&#x02013;17.51)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>14.49 (12.46&#x02013;16.52)</td><td/><td>14.25 (12.04&#x02013;16.45)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>14.05 (12.07&#x02013;16.02)</td><td/><td>15.35 (13.54&#x02013;17.16)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>14.45 (12.56&#x02013;16.34)</td><td/><td>15.12 (13.25&#x02013;16.99)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Median Nerve PPT</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.46 (<italic>0.80</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.42 (<italic>0.83</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>18.74 (16.27&#x02013;21.21)</td><td/><td>17.99 (15.97&#x02013;20.01)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>18.45 (16.02&#x02013;20.87)</td><td/><td>17.19 (15.34&#x02013;19.04)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>17.53 (15.76&#x02013;19.29)</td><td/><td>17.51 (15.73&#x02013;19.28)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>17.43 (15.53&#x02013;19.32)</td><td/><td>16.88 (14.98&#x02013;18.77)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>17.16 (15.19&#x02013;19.13)</td><td/><td>16.76 (14.84&#x02013;18.68)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>17.14 (15.17&#x02013;19.10)</td><td/><td>16.32 (14.43&#x02013;18.21)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Tibialis Anterior PPT</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.22 (<italic>0.95</italic>)</td><td/><td char="(" align="char">0.80 (<italic>0.55</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Basal (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>15.39 (13.41&#x02013;17.37)</td><td/><td>17.29 (15.49&#x02013;19.08)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 1st NMT (T<sub>1</sub>)</td><td>15.51 (13.53&#x02013;17.48)</td><td/><td>17.10 (15.35&#x02013;18.84)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 1st week (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>15.02 (13.14&#x02013;16.89)</td><td/><td>16.65 (14.87&#x02013;18.43)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 2nd NMT (T<sub>2</sub>)</td><td>14.86 (12.89&#x02013;16.82)</td><td/><td>16.16 (14.17&#x02013;18.14)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Arrival 5nd week (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>14.56 (12.74&#x02013;16.38)</td><td/><td>15.71 (14.04&#x02013;17.38)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;After 3rd NMT (T<sub>3</sub>)</td><td>14.46 (12.70&#x02013;16.21)</td><td/><td>15.39 (13.69&#x02013;17.08)</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations: HG</italic> Hand Grip, <italic>PPT</italic> Pressure Pain Threshold, <italic>NMT</italic> Neuromuscular Taping. T<sub>1</sub> (Baseline). T<sub>2</sub> (1&#x000a0;week after) and T<sub>3</sub> (5&#x000a0;week after)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par72">The Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> represent graphically, changes in objective variables, based on the data contained in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>. We observe how the hand strength improvement in the experimental group in the healthy hand and on the side of surgery (albeit with lower values). Instead, records in the group which received the sham intervention, remain within the same range (means of &#x000b1;18 in healthy side and&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;16 in the affected). In the representation of the cervical and lumbar PPT it tells us how after each application of NMT, (both real and sham) had a slight increase in the threshold values. That is, all participants were less painful sensitivity to pressure after each intervention at these levels. The opposite effect appears to occur when we apply the bandage at the level of the median nerve. After each application the participant, in both groups, support less pressure before the painful sensation appears. In the case of the algometer application on the tibialis anterior of all participants, the results hardly alter pre and post intervention. If we make an overall assessment at this point, the threshold decreases discretely in both groups between baseline and the end, especially in the control group, although as in the previous cases, without statistical significance.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Means of objective measures from both groups at different times of the study</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12906_2018_2236_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Changes in the plasmatic proteins</title><sec id="Sec18"><title>Changes between control and intervention groups</title><p id="Par73">When analyzing the variations between the two groups from the baseline (T1) to the second intervention (T3), there were no statistically significant differences in C-reactive protein (CRP) or Creatin-kinase (CK) values (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.53 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.99 respectively); So we can say that the intervention has failed to modify these biochemical parameters (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Change scores between-group and within-group in biological outcomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th/><th>Mean (SD)</th><th>Mean difference</th><th>CI 95%</th><th>t (<italic>p</italic>)</th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">CRP 5th week</td><td>Experimental</td><td>4.09 (6.51)</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;2.48</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;10.54 to 5.57</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.63 (<italic>0.53</italic>)</td><td rowspan="4">Between group</td></tr><tr><td>Control</td><td>6.57 (11.52)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">CK 5th week</td><td>Experimental</td><td>105.36 (44.17)</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.20</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;37.92 to 37.50</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.01 (<italic>0.99</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>Control</td><td>105.57 (46.05)</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td>Mean (SD)</td><td>Mean difference</td><td>CI 95%</td><td>t (<italic>p</italic>)</td><td rowspan="9">Within group</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Experimental</td><td>Basal CRP</td><td>4.27 (5.81)</td><td rowspan="2">0.182</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.47 to 0.84</td><td rowspan="2">0.61 (<italic>0.55</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>5th week CRP</td><td>4.09 (6.51)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Control</td><td>Basal CRP</td><td>5.36 (5.13)</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;1.21</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;7.28 to 4.85</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.43 (<italic>0.67</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>5th week CRP</td><td>6.57 (11.52)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Experimental</td><td>Basal CK</td><td>102.36 (39.08)</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;3.00</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;16.17 to 10.17</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;0.50 (<italic>0.62</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>5th week CK</td><td>105.36 (44.17)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Control</td><td>Basal CK</td><td>112.50 (43.57)</td><td rowspan="2">6.92</td><td rowspan="2">&#x02212;12.19 to 26.05</td><td rowspan="2">0.78 (<italic>0.44</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td>5th week CK</td><td>105.57 (46.05)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations: CRP</italic> C-reactive Protein, <italic>CK</italic> Creatine Kinase, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Changes within-groups</title><p id="Par74">Intra-group levels of PCR and CK have not been statistically different before and after the intervention; Both in the experimental group and in the placebo group (Table <xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par75">Mialgias and arthralgias are increasingly recognised to be a toxicity induced by AI therapy, but the mechanism underlying it development and it management remains unclear. As a result, there is no scientifically supported treatment indicated to treat these symptoms. In this pilot study we try to improve the participants subjective feeling of pain through an intervention using NMT.</p><p id="Par76">After performing this pragmatic clinical trial, we can conclude that in BC patients treated with adjuvant AI, the application of a VNM improves the subjective sensation of pain according to the EVA scale (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.009), confirming our initial hypothesis that VNM Could improve the sensation of pain in BC patients with musculoskeletal alterations secondary to the use of IAs. Additionally in our study the application of this therapy improves the subjective perception of their overall health, fatigue and subjective pain sensation according to the EORTC quality of life scale.</p><p id="Par77">Results of this pilot study are consistent with those of Imperatory et al., who investigated the safety and efficacy of NMT in reducing postoperative chest pain after lobectomy for lung cancer. After tape application, VNM patients reported overall less thoracic pain than the control group, assessed by VAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. In contrast another study with BCS taking AIs performed an intervention assessing the effect of acupuncture on reducing musculoskeletal symptoms and they did not observe a statistically significant difference in VAS reduction (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.31) between cases and controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. This improvement in VAS besides decreasing the adverse effects of the drugs can influence the treatment adherence. Worsening in VAS is associated with increased risk for early AIs discontinuation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. NMV has also been used to improve pain in other groups of patients. In patients with knee osteoarthritis, VNM application demonstrated large decrease in VAS, although unlike our study, from the initial taping application [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Instead, in nonspecific low back patients, the same effects was achieved on pain scale cases and controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>].</p><p id="Par78">There is a significant association between pain and lower health-related quality of life scores in the physical and mental component summary scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>], so it is not surprising that patients in addition to changing VAS improved their overall health status and symptoms contained in their quality of life questionnaire, such as pain or fatigue. A home-based exercise program provided similar benefits to BCS undergoing AI treatment by reducing joint pain and improving QoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. This study is in line with another that intervened through aerobic exercise and stretching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Galantino et al. analyzed the utility of yoga in these BCS using qualitative methods and concluded that this technique improved QoL and pain, although the sample was very small [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. However, another pilot study did not achieve changes in pain severity or QoL by an intervention using electroacupuncture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Reducing fatigue could enhance therapeutic outcomes by increasing adherence and is also important following completion of cancer treatment, to get the resumption of pre-cancer lifestyles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Regarding the improvement of fatigue, large number of research studies support the ability of exercise training to alleviate cancer-related fatigue, various meta-analysis revealed that it has a favorable effect when compared to conventional care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Other interventions that reduced fatigue in BCS used Mindfulness-Based Music Therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>] and yoga [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. In contrast to our pilot study, NMV did not reduce fatigue in muscular affections with healthy subjects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].</p><p id="Par79">It would be very useful to be able to identify early changes in Patient-Reported Outcomes that ultimately stopped treatment as a result of toxicity. Identification of these changes could be used to target interventions in patients at high risk for early discontinuation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].</p><p id="Par80">Regarding the objective variables, there is a clear trend of improvement in grip force of the healthy and affects hand after the intervention, although not statistically significant. In order to evaluate these results, it is necessary to take into account that this variable does not remain stable during the administration of the AIs, grip strength in the left and right hands decrease after 6&#x000a0;months of antihormonal therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This gain is hardly seen between controls. Consistent with our findings, women in a resistance and impact training program significantly improved their grip strength (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01) compared to a stretching placebo program [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. In contrast to this trial, (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.47) a group of participants who performed an aerobic exercise and supervised strength training during 12&#x000a0;months, showed no improvement in their grip strength [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p><p id="Par81">BC may increase the pain experience at distant sites presumably via alterations in neuroendocrine profiles or direct sensitizing effects on the Central Nervous System [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Besides this painful sensitization it is greater if the patient is practiced mastectomy instead of a lumpectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. In fact, in previous studies, the presence of central nervous system hypersensitivity has already been reported in BCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The results of this pilot study indicate that the subject&#x02019;s pressure sensitivity does not change significantly at any level or group after taping applications. Only a slight increase of its values in the cervical and lumbar zone was obtained. Similarly, previous findings suggest that an intervention through myofascial release technique also fails to change the PPT values in BCS over the cervical spine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. This may be because three interventions may not be sufficient to activate pain inhibitory mechanisms. Our results are in line with Henry y cols trial, where no statistically significant change in PPT was identified following estrogen deprivation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Taking into account these new findings, it is possible that our intervention did not achieve changes because estrogen depletion have not effects on pain sensibility.</p><p id="Par82">The coexistence of arthralgia, fatigue, and insomnia is associated with elevated C-reactive protein and other inflammatory biomarkers. This suggest a possible inflammatory mechanism underlying these common symptoms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Instead, there are a negative correlation between serum CK levels and BC stage. Its level, which may reflect the status of host immunity, may be an important factor in determining BC development and progression. The results of our trial indicating that plasma proteins such as CRP and CK exhibiting no significant changes after the intervention, at the time of the last assessment, between cases and controls. Besides, there were no differences between the beginning and the end of the trial or in cases or controls for these variables. These results are in line with another study with BCS which present lymphedema, each experimental session involved standard resistance exercises and there were no significant changes in CRP or the CK at the end of the intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. A similar, non-significant trend was observed for the CRP with a 12-week yoga intervention in fatigued BCS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. No changes is observed when intervention, in this case a 12-month moderate-intensity physical activity intervention, is performed in elderly men and women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. In contrast to our work, other authors such as Rock et al. decreased blood content of CRP changing the diet composition in overweight/obese women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>].</p><p id="Par83">One limitation of this study is the small sample size which we have recruited, since it is a pilot study, and a possible selection bias produced by those who agree to participate in this type of studies given the time requirements. Furthermore, because our study relies on self-report, there is some degree of misclassification bias because of the existence of the patient&#x02019;s perception; In spite of this, for subjective symptoms like AIA, patient-reported outcome is considered the gold standard. Another limitation of this study is the focus on systemic (observing changes in plasma proteins) instead of local. Others authors have demostrated using magnetic resonance imaging that local inflammatory processes occurs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Therefore, future studies could be designed to investigate changes at the local level.</p><p id="Par84">In spite of these limitations, this study is, to the best of our knowledge, the first study to date evaluating in BCS con AIA, the association of patient-reported symptoms with an intervention by neuromuscular taping. Strengths of our study include the randomized design, and a focus on women experiencing arthralgia resulting from AI use. It was also an advantage to have the high persistence of the subjects to the intervention and the fact that all measures were taken by the same examiner, which improves the reliability. Finally, it is important to note that no significant side effects were associated with NMT treatment.</p><p id="Par85">A future replication study is needed, with a larger subjects sample, to verify the results identified in our trial. It would also be interesting to relate these results to the hormone therapy regimen administered, that is, if they started with tamoxifen before switching to AIs. In addition to analyzing the impact of the taping, we could verify whether this arthralgia is actually more likely in women switching from tamoxifen to an AI compared with women starting with AI [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. It would also be interesting to include genetic variables in our study and to analyze their possible relationship with AIA and the impact of the intervention on the outcome variables. Although some benefit of taping was observed after 5&#x000a0;weeks of intervention, we will probably get better results if we extend the application over time. It would also be interesting to know how many interventions are optimal to obtain the desired improvement, as well as a posteriori control to verify that the results have been maintained over time.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par86">In conclusion, we have shown that after 5&#x000a0;week of NMT therapy, patients treated with an AI experience an improvement of preexisting musculoskeletal symptoms, mainly of their subjective sensation of pain. Furthermore, this passive intervention achieved significant changes in variables related to quality of life such as global health, fatigue or pain, with a strong impact on the subject well-being. Considering the effectiveness of AIs preventing BC recurrences and the proportion of women who discontinue this therapy because of AIAA, interventions designed to minimize the adverse effects of these therapies are useful and necessary. An intervention by NMT to MSCM under treatment with AIs improves their subjective sensation of pain. In addition, this taping had an impact on variables related to the quality of life. This pilot study may be the basis for others to support the use of NMT for the treatment of AIAs, thereby improving their well-being and reducing the dropout rate.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AIA</term><def><p id="Par6">AI- induced arthralgia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AIs</term><def><p id="Par7">Aromatase Inhibitors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ATAC</term><def><p id="Par8">Arimidex and tamoxifen alone or in combination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BADIX</term><def><p id="Par9">Backache Disability Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BAI</term><def><p id="Par10">Back Pain Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BC </term><def><p id="Par11">Breast cancer</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BCS</term><def><p id="Par12">Breast cancer survivors</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CK</term><def><p id="Par13">Creatine Kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRP</term><def><p id="Par14">C-reactive Protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CTS </term><def><p id="Par15">Carpal Tunnel Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EORTC QLQ - C30</term><def><p id="Par16">European Organization for Research and Treatment Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p id="Par17">Hormone receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IES</term><def><p id="Par18">Intergroup Exemestane Study</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MBS</term><def><p id="Par19">Morning Stiffness in the Back</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MS</term><def><p id="Par20">Mass Spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NMT</term><def><p id="Par21">Neuromuscular Taping</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NSAIDs</term><def><p id="Par22">Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>POMS</term><def><p id="Par23">Profile of Mood States</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPT</term><def><p id="Par24">Pressure Pain Threshold</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QoL</term><def><p id="Par25">Quality of Life</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SFI</term><def><p id="Par26">Spine Functional Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ULFI</term><def><p id="Par27">Upper Limb Functional Index</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAS</term><def><p id="Par28">Visual Analogue Scale</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank all participants and the Oncology Department at the General University Hospital of M&#x000e1;laga for their contribution to the development of this project.</p><sec id="FPar7"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par87">The datasets generated during the current study are available in the Repositorio Institucional de la Universidad de M&#x000e1;laga (RIUMA) repository, (available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://riuma.uma.es/xmlui">http://riuma.uma.es/xmlui</ext-link>). All data analysed during this study are included in this published article and in supplementary information files.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>IC and AICV participated in the conception and design of the study, and in the data collection, analysis and interpretation of the data, and drafted the manuscript. BP and EA participated in the data collection and critical revision of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar8"><title>Authors&#x02019; information</title><p id="Par88">Inmaculada Conejo is Physiotherapist and a PhD student at the University of M&#x000e1;laga, M&#x000e1;laga, Spain.</p><p id="Par89">Bella Pajares MD, PhD and Professor Emilio Alba are a oncologist of Oncology Department at the General University Hospital of M&#x000e1;laga, IBIMA, University of M&#x000e1;laga, Spain.</p><p id="Par90">Antonio I. Cuesta-Vargas is a Professor of Physiotherapy at the University of M&#x000e1;laga, Spain and Adjunct Professor at Queensland University of Technology, Australia.</p></sec><sec id="FPar9"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par91">The Provincial Ethics Committee of M&#x000e1;laga was approved this study. All patients gave their informed written consent for the study.</p></sec><sec id="FPar10"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par92">Consent to publish was obtained from the patients featured in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="FPar11"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par93">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar12"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par94">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GLOBOCAN 2012 [Internet]. GLOBOCAN 2012. 2016 [citado 28 de junio de 2016]. Disponible en: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://globocan.iarc.fr/Pages/fact_sheets_population.aspx">http://globocan.iarc.fr/Pages/fact_sheets_population.aspx</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Sociedad Espa&#x000f1;ola de Oncolog&#x000ed;a M&#x000e9;dica (SEOM)</collab></person-group><source>Las Cifras del C&#x000e1;ncer en Espa&#x000f1;a 2016</source><year>2016</year><publisher-loc>Madrid</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sociedad Espa&#x000f1;ola de Oncolog&#x000ed;a M&#x000e9;dica (SEOM)</publisher-name><fpage>24</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez San Felipe</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Manuel-y-Keenoy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of body weight on the prognosis of breast cancer survivors; nutritional approach after diagnosis</article-title><source>Nutr Hosp diciembre de</source><year>2013</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1829</fpage><lpage>1841</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Early Breast Cancer Trialists&#x02019; Collaborative Group (EBCTCG)</collab><name><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aihara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aromatase inhibitors versus tamoxifen in early breast cancer: patient-level meta-analysis of the randomised trials</article-title><source>Lancet Lond Engl</source><year>2015</year><volume>386</volume><issue>10001</issue><fpage>1341</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)61074-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crew</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenlee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Capodice</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Raptis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Brafman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of joint symptoms in postmenopausal women taking aromatase inhibitors for early-stage breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2007</year><volume>25</volume><issue>25</issue><fpage>3877</fpage><lpage>3883</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2007.10.7573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niravath</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aromatase inhibitor-induced arthralgia: a review</article-title><source>Ann Oncol Off J Eur Soc Med Oncol ESMO</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1443</fpage><lpage>1449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdt037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadji</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical considerations for the use of antiresorptive agents in the treatment of metastatic bone disease</article-title><source>Crit Rev Oncol Hematol</source><year>2011</year><volume>80</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.critrevonc.2011.03.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21511491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21511491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Duration of adjuvant endocrine therapy of breast cancer: how much is enough?</article-title><source>Curr Opin Obstet Gynecol</source><year>2010</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/GCO.0b013e328334ff40</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19952743?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19952743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ziller</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>U-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holzhauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adherence to adjuvant endocrine therapy in postmenopausal women with breast cancer</article-title><source>Ann Oncol Off J Eur Soc Med Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdn646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Portela</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vasconcellos</surname><given-names>MTL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adherence to hormone therapy among women with breast cancer</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>397</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2407-14-397</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24893670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24893670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mieog</surname><given-names>JSD</given-names></name><name><surname>Morden</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coombes</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>van de CJH</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><collab>IES Steering Committee</collab></person-group><article-title>Carpal tunnel syndrome and musculoskeletal symptoms in postmenopausal women with early breast cancer treated with exemestane or tamoxifen after 2&#x02013;3 years of tamoxifen: a retrospective analysis of the Intergroup Exemestane Study</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>432</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(11)70328-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22265698?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22265698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sestak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapunar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aromatase inhibitor-induced carpal tunnel syndrome: results from the ATAC trial</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><issue>30</issue><fpage>4961</fpage><lpage>4965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.22.0236</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lintermans</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Hoydonck</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verhaeghe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhovens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Aromatase inhibitor-induced loss of grip strength is body mass index dependent: hypothesis-generating findings for its pathogenesis</article-title><source>Ann Oncol Off J Eur Soc Med Oncol ESMO</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1763</fpage><lpage>1769</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annonc/mdq699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000f8;nning</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eikesdal</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aromatase inhibition 2013: clinical state of the art and questions that remain to be solved</article-title><source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source><year>2013</year><volume>20</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>R183</fpage><lpage>R201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/ERC-13-0099</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23625614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23625614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crew</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Capodice</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenlee</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brafman</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Randomized, blinded, sham-controlled trial of acupuncture for the management of aromatase inhibitor-associated joint symptoms in women with early-stage breast cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1154</fpage><lpage>1160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.23.4708</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bocca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bassignana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miglietta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiproliferative effects of COX-2 inhibitor celecoxib on human breast cancer cell lines</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biochem</source><year>2011</year><volume>350</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11010-010-0682-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21140284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21140284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sestak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuzick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapunar</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eastell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for joint symptoms in patients enrolled in the ATAC trial: a retrospective, exploratory analysis</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>866</fpage><lpage>872</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(08)70182-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18703382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18703382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peppone</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Janelsins</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohile</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprod</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gewandter</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of YOCAS&#x000a9;&#x000ae; yoga for musculoskeletal symptoms among breast cancer survivors on hormonal therapy</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2015</year><volume>150</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>597</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-015-3351-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25814054?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25814054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Onishi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Okido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokohata</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Short-term and low-dose prednisolone administration reduces aromatase inhibitor-induced arthralgia in patients with breast cancer</article-title><source>Anticancer Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2331</fpage><lpage>2336</lpage><?supplied-pmid 22641670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22641670</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xepapadakis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntasiou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Koronarchis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Koufoudakis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Panousis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosomanidis</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New views on treatment of aromatase inhibitors induced arthralgia</article-title><source>Breast Edinb Scotl</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.breast.2010.03.031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yang GS, Kim HJ, Griffith KA, Zhu S, Dorsey SG, Renn CL. Interventions for the treatment of aromatase inhibitor-associated arthralgia in breast Cancer survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Cancer Nurs. 2017;40(4):E26-E41.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ristow</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohlweg-Majert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kehl</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Koerdt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahnefeld</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pautke</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does elastic therapeutic tape reduce postoperative swelling, pain, and trismus after open reduction and internal fixation of mandibular fractures?</article-title><source>J Oral Maxillofac Surg Off J Am Assoc Oral Maxillofac Surg</source><year>2013</year><volume>71</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1387</fpage><lpage>1396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.joms.2013.03.020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J-H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of proprioceptive neuromuscular facilitation stretching and kinesiology taping on pelvic compensation during double-knee extension</article-title><source>J Hum Kinet</source><year>2015</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/hukin-2015-0108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26839606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26839606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez Soriano</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasc&#x000f3; L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lacalle</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Merino Josa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandra Meijide</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moll Puigcerver</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ant&#x000fa;nez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influencia del vendaje neuromuscular sobre la presi&#x000f3;n plantar durante la marcha</article-title><source>Fisioterapia</source><year>2010</year><volume>32</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ft.2009.12.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Campolo M, Babu J, Dmochowska K, Scariah S, Varughese J. A comparison of two taping techniques (kinesio and mcconnell ) and their effect on previous knee pain during functional activities. Int J Sports Phys Ther. 2013;8(2):105&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of kinesio taping on architecture, strength and pain of muscles in delayed onset muscle soreness of biceps brachii</article-title><source>J Phys Ther Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1589/jpts.27.457</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25729190?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25729190</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yazici</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Guclu-Gunduz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayraktar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazliel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilinc</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Does correcting position and increasing sensorial input of the foot and ankle with Kinesio taping improve balance in stroke patients?</article-title><source>NeuroRehabilitation</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>353</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/NRE-151223</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26409338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26409338</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>da Costa</surname><given-names>CSN</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>NACF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pilot study: investigating the effects of Kinesio taping&#x000ae; on functional activities in children with cerebral palsy. Dev</article-title><source>NeuroRehabilitation</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/17518423.2012.727106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bravi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Quarta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minciacchi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of direction and tension of Kinesio taping application on sensorimotor coordination</article-title><source>Int J Sports Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>37</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-0042-109777</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27454132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27454132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donec</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kri&#x00161;&#x0010d;i&#x0016b;nas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effectiveness of Kinesio taping&#x000ae; after total knee replacement in early postoperative rehabilitation period</article-title><source>A randomized controlled trial Eur J Phys Rehabil Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>50</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>363</fpage><lpage>371</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24819349?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24819349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pekyava&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>N&#x000d6;</given-names></name><name><surname>Tunay</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbayrak</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karata&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complex decongestive therapy and taping for patients with postmastectomy lymphedema: a randomized controlled study</article-title><source>Eur J Oncol Nurs Off J Eur Oncol Nurs Soc</source><year>2014</year><volume>18</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejon.2014.06.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smykla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Walewicz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Trybulski</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Halski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucharzewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of kinesiology taping on breast cancer-related lymphedema: a randomized single-blind controlled pilot study</article-title><source>Biomed Res Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>2013</volume><fpage>767106</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/767106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24377096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24377096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijmonsma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>Taping Neuro Muscular. Manual. 1<sup>a</sup> Ed</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Cascais</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Aneid Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sijmonsma J. Taping Neuro Muscular. Manual. 2<sup>a</sup>. Cascais: Aneid Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Added</surname><given-names>MAN</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>LOP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>de Freitas</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Salom&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of adding the Kinesio taping method to guideline-endorsed conventional physiotherapy in patients with chronic nonspecific low back pain: a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>301</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-14-301</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24156687?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24156687</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Iglesias</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleland</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Huijbregts</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Rosario Guti&#x000e9;rrez-Vega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Short-term effects of cervical kinesio taping on pain and cervical range of motion in patients with acute whiplash injury: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2519/jospt.2009.3072</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19574662?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19574662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thelen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dauber</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stoneman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical efficacy of kinesio tape for shoulder pain: a randomized, double-blinded, clinical trial</article-title><source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source><year>2008</year><volume>38</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2519/jospt.2008.2791</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18591761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18591761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bauml</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalos</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Arthralgia among women taking aromatase inhibitors: is there a shared inflammatory mechanism with co-morbid fatigue and insomnia?</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res BCR</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>89</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-015-0599-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26126656?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26126656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minton</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The identification of plasma proteins associated with cancer-related fatigue syndrome (CRFS) in disease-free breast cancer patients using proteomic analysis</article-title><source>J Pain Symptom Manage</source><year>2013</year><volume>45</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>868</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpainsymman.2012.04.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23017604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23017604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanderwee&#x000eb;n</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Oostendorp</surname><given-names>RAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vaes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Duquet</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pressure algometry in manual therapy</article-title><source>Man Ther</source><year>1996</year><volume>1</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/math.1996.0276</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11440515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11440515</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Karatepe</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;naydn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeti&#x0015f;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uslu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disability and health-related quality of life after breast cancer surgery: relation to impairments</article-title><source>South Med J</source><year>2010</year><volume>103</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SMJ.0b013e3181c38c41</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19996840?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19996840</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantarero-Villanueva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Lao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-De-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-Cantalejo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associations among musculoskeletal impairments, depression, body image and fatigue in breast cancer survivors within the first year after treatment</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Care (Engl)</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>639</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2354.2011.01245.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21410803</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuesta-Vargas</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabel</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-cultural adaptation, reliability and validity of the Spanish version of the upper limb functional index</article-title><source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><year>2013</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-11-126</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23889883?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23889883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krohe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamoureux</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Galipeau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Globe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Foley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported outcomes in metastatic breast Cancer: a review of industry-sponsored clinical trials</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Basic Clin Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4137/BCBCR.S39385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sriwatanakul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelvie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasagna</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Calimlim</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><collab>Weis OF</collab><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies with different types of visual analog scales for measurement of pain</article-title><source>Clin Pharmacol Ther</source><year>1983</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/clpt.1983.159</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6872418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6872418</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuesta-Vargas</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabel</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Validation of a Spanish version of the spine functional index</article-title><source>Health Qual Life Outcomes</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>96</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7525-12-96</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24972525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24972525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Llobera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil Del Real</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraira</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gestoso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Validation of the spanish version of the Roland-Morris questionnaire</article-title><source>Spine</source><year>2002</year><volume>27</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>538</fpage><lpage>542</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007632-200203010-00016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11880841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11880841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farasyn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Meeusen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijs</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuesta-Vargas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploration of the validity and reliability of the &#x000ab;backache disability index&#x000bb; (BADIX) in patients with non-specific low back pain</article-title><source>J Back Musculoskelet Rehabil</source><year>2013</year><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/BMR-130405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23948835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23948835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lara-Palomo</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Matar&#x000e1;n-Pe&#x000f1;arrocha</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Labraca</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinesio taping reduces disability and pain slightly in chronic non-specific low back pain: a randomised trial</article-title><source>J Physiother</source><year>2012</year><volume>58</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1836-9553(12)70088-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22613238?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22613238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imperatori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castiglioni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasperini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Faini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Spampatti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chest pain control with kinesiology taping after lobectomy for lung cancer: initial results of a randomized placebo-controlled study</article-title><source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source><year>2016</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icvts/ivw110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27130717?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27130717</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarpinian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A dual-center randomized controlled double blind trial assessing the effect of acupuncture in reducing musculoskeletal symptoms in breast cancer patients taking aromatase inhibitors</article-title><source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2013</year><volume>138</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-013-2427-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23393007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23393007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kadakia</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seewald</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Flockhart</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaar</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient-reported outcomes and early discontinuation in aromatase inhibitor-treated postmenopausal women with early stage breast Cancer</article-title><source>The Oncologist</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>546</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2015-0349</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27009936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27009936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kaya Mutlu E, Mustafaoglu R, Birinci T, Razak Ozdincler A. Does Kinesio taping of the knee improve pain and functionality in patients with knee osteoarthritis?: a randomized controlled clinical trial. Am J Phys med Rehabil. 2016;</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kachanathu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alenazi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Seif</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafez</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Alroumim</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison between Kinesio taping and a traditional physical therapy program in treatment of nonspecific low back pain</article-title><source>J Phys Ther Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1589/jpts.26.1185</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25202177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202177</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olufade</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallicchio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Helzlsouer</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Musculoskeletal pain and health-related quality of life among breast cancer patients treated with aromatase inhibitors</article-title><source>Support Care Cancer Off J Multinatl Assoc Support Care Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>455</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DeNysschen</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ademuyiwa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetewsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise intervention in breast cancer patients with aromatase inhibitor-associated arthralgia: a pilot study</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer Care (Engl)</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>493</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ecc.12155</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289215</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irwin</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartmel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ercolano</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Randomized exercise trial of aromatase inhibitor-induced arthralgia in breast cancer survivors</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>1111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2014.57.1547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galantino</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Archetto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassall</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A qualitative exploration of the impact of yoga on breast cancer survivors with aromatase inhibitor-associated arthralgias</article-title><source>Explore N Y N</source><year>2012</year><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.explore.2011.10.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>DSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acupuncture for treatment of arthralgia secondary to aromatase inhibitor therapy in women with early breast cancer: pilot study</article-title><source>Acupunct Med J Br Med Acupunct Soc</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/acupmed-2012-010309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaVoy</surname><given-names>ECP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagundes</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Dantzer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exercise inflammation and fatigue in cancer survivors</article-title><source>Exerc Immunol Rev</source><year>2016</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26853557?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26853557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meneses-Ech&#x000e1;vez</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez-V&#x000e9;lez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of supervised exercise on cancer-related fatigue in breast cancer survivors: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>BMC Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>77</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12885-015-1069-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25885168?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25885168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lesiuk T. The Development of a Mindfulness-Based Music Therapy (MBMT) Program for Women Receiving Adjuvant Chemotherapy for Breast Cancer. Healthc Basel Switz. 2016;4(3)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greendale</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Crosswell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Garet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sternlieb</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganz</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Yoga reduces inflammatory signaling in fatigued breast cancer survivors: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology mayo de</source><year>2014</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2014.01.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanca</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattiello</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Karduna</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinesio taping of the deltoid does not reduce fatigue induced deficits in shoulder joint position sense</article-title><source>Clin Biomech Bristol Avon</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>903</fpage><lpage>907</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinbiomech.2015.07.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Winters-Stone</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nail</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leo</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of resistance training on muscle strength and physical function in older, postmenopausal breast cancer survivors: a randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>J Cancer Surviv Res Pract</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11764-011-0210-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Lao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantarero-Villanueva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del-Moral-&#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Menj&#x000f3;n-Beltr&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread mechanical pain hypersensitivity as a sign of central sensitization after breast cancer surgery: comparison between mastectomy and lumpectomy</article-title><source>Pain Med Malden Mass</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1526-4637.2010.01027.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Lao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantarero-Villanueva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-Las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Del-Moral-&#x000c1;vila</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arendt-Nielsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myofascial trigger points in neck and shoulder muscles and widespread pressure pain hypersensitivtiy in patients with postmastectomy pain: evidence of peripheral and central sensitization</article-title><source>Clin J Pain</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/AJP.0b013e3181f18c36</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20842013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20842013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Lao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantarero-Villanueva</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-de-las-Pe&#x000f1;as</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Salado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo-Morales</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of patient attitude toward massage on pressure pain sensitivity and immune system after application of myofascial release in breast cancer survivors: a randomized, controlled crossover study</article-title><source>J Manipulative Physiol Ther</source><year>2012</year><volume>35</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmpt.2011.09.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22018755?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22018755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Conlon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidwell</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smerage</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of estrogen depletion on pain sensitivity in aromatase inhibitor-treated women with early-stage breast cancer</article-title><source>J Pain Off J Am Pain Soc</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2014.01.487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cormie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peake</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Galv&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Taaffe</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Acute inflammatory response to low-, moderate-, and high-load resistance exercise in women with breast Cancer-related lymphedema</article-title><source>Integr Cancer Ther</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1534735415617283</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26582633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicklas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>F-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brinkley</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodpaster</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kritchevsky</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exercise training and plasma C-reactive protein and interleukin-6 in elderly people</article-title><source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source><year>2008</year><volume>56</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2045</fpage><lpage>2052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1532-5415.2008.01994.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19016938?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19016938</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rock</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pakiz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effects of diet composition on weight loss, metabolic factors and biomarkers in a 1-year weight loss intervention in obese women examined by baseline insulin resistance status</article-title><source>Metabolism</source><year>2016</year><volume>65</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1605</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.metabol.2016.07.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27733248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27733248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morales</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Verschueren</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Paridaens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Westhovens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prospective study to assess short-term intra-articular and tenosynovial changes in the aromatase inhibitor-associated arthralgia syndrome</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol Off J Am Soc Clin Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>3147</fpage><lpage>3152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2007.15.4005</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>