<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">brainj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">brain</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brain</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0006-8950</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2156</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4620514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26463677</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awv276</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">awv276</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1010</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pain and temperature processing in dementia: a clinical and neuroanatomical analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>Phillip D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>Laura E.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>Hannah L.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Camilla N.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>Catherine F.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>Ross W.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>Jonathan D.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>Jonathan M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>Martin N.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>Jason D.</given-names></name></contrib><aff>Dementia Research Centre, UCL Institute of Neurology, University College London, London, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence to: Prof J. D. Warren Dementia Research Centre, UCL Institute of Neurology, University College London, 8&#x02013;11 Queen Square London, WC1N 3BG, UK E-mail: <email>jason.warren@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the							<pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>138</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>3360</fpage><lpage>3372</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author (2015). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Guarantors of Brain.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p>Symptoms suggesting altered pain and temperature processing have been described in dementia diseases. Using a semi-structured caregiver questionnaire and MRI voxel-based morphometry in patients with frontotemporal degeneration or Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic> show that these symptoms are underpinned by atrophy in a distributed thalamo-temporo-insular network implicated in somatosensory processing.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical"><p>
<fig id="fig1g" fig-type="featured" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><p>Symptoms suggesting altered pain and temperature processing have been described in dementia diseases. Using a semi-structured caregiver questionnaire and MRI voxel-based morphometry in patients with frontotemporal degeneration or Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic> show that these symptoms are underpinned by atrophy in a distributed thalamo-temporo-insular network implicated in somatosensory processing.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="awv276fig1g"/></fig>
</p></abstract><abstract><p>Symptoms suggesting altered processing of pain and temperature have been described in dementia diseases and may contribute importantly to clinical phenotypes, particularly in the frontotemporal lobar degeneration spectrum, but the basis for these symptoms has not been characterized in detail. Here we analysed pain and temperature symptoms using a semi-structured caregiver questionnaire recording altered behavioural responsiveness to pain or temperature for a cohort of patients with frontotemporal lobar degeneration (<italic>n = </italic>58, 25 female, aged 52&#x02013;84 years, representing the major clinical syndromes and representative pathogenic mutations in the <italic>C9orf72</italic> and <italic>MAPT</italic> genes) and a comparison cohort of patients with amnestic Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (<italic>n = </italic>20, eight female, aged 53&#x02013;74 years). Neuroanatomical associations were assessed using blinded visual rating and voxel-based morphometry of patients&#x02019; brain magnetic resonance images. Certain syndromic signatures were identified: pain and temperature symptoms were particularly prevalent in behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia (71% of cases) and semantic dementia (65% of cases) and in association with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (6/6 cases), but also developed in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (45% of cases) and progressive non-fluent aphasia (25% of cases). While altered temperature responsiveness was more common than altered pain responsiveness across syndromes, blunted responsiveness to pain and temperature was particularly associated with behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia (40% of symptomatic cases) and heightened responsiveness with semantic dementia (73% of symptomatic cases) and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (78% of symptomatic cases). In the voxel-based morphometry analysis of the frontotemporal lobar degeneration cohort, pain and temperature symptoms were associated with grey matter loss in a right-lateralized network including insula (<italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05 corrected for multiple voxel-wise comparisons within the prespecified anatomical region of interest) and anterior temporal cortex (<italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.001 uncorrected over whole brain) previously implicated in processing homeostatic signals. Pain and temperature symptoms accompanying <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations were specifically associated with posterior thalamic atrophy (<italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05 corrected for multiple voxel-wise comparisons within the prespecified anatomical region of interest). Together the findings suggest candidate cognitive and neuroanatomical bases for these salient but under-appreciated phenotypic features of the dementias, with wider implications for the homeostatic pathophysiology and clinical management of neurodegenerative diseases.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="keywords"><kwd>pain</kwd><kwd>temperature</kwd><kwd>sensory</kwd><kwd>frontotemporal dementia</kwd><kwd>Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The frontotemporal lobar degenerations (FTLDs) are a diverse group of proteinopathies characterized by selective degeneration of distributed brain networks involving the frontal and temporal lobes. Altered processing of sensory signals is an important feature of these diseases (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B78" ref-type="bibr">Pijnenburg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B50" ref-type="bibr">Jesso <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B72" ref-type="bibr">Omar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B73" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B85" ref-type="bibr">Rohrer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B33" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B56" ref-type="bibr">Landqvist Waldo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B76" ref-type="bibr">Perry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B104" ref-type="bibr">Woolley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). Patients commonly fail to interpret emotional and social cues correctly (<xref rid="awv276-B50" ref-type="bibr">Jesso <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B72" ref-type="bibr">Omar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B54" ref-type="bibr">Kumfor and Piguet, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>) and may show obsessional attachment to particular stimuli such as sweet foods (<xref rid="awv276-B104" ref-type="bibr">Woolley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) or music (<xref rid="awv276-B33" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) suggesting a generic disturbance in processing reward and attributing hedonic valence (<xref rid="awv276-B76" ref-type="bibr">Perry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). However, several series have documented symptoms that might signify a more fundamental abnormality in coding somatosensory signals, in particular pain and temperature, by patients with FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Unpleasant somatic symptoms, often with a nociceptive component (including non-specific unexplained headaches, musculoskeletal, abdominal or urogenital discomfort, vague migrating pains, chest pain and pruritus), have been described in a substantial proportion of patients with FTLD and may be early and prominent (<xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>); such symptoms may be particularly salient in the syndromes of semantic dementia and behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia (FTD), especially with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<xref rid="awv276-B55" ref-type="bibr">Landqvist Waldo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Patients may exhibit strikingly abnormal &#x02018;sensory behaviours&#x02019;, especially reduced responsiveness to painful stimuli in behavioural variant FTD and exaggerated responses to pain in semantic dementia (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>). Symptoms suggesting disturbed thermoregulation have also been reported with high prevalence in behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia (<xref rid="awv276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Limited psychophysical evidence has suggested overall increases in pain threshold and tolerance in FTD, albeit with considerable individual variation (<xref rid="awv276-B14" ref-type="bibr">Carlino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Such reports suggest that pain and temperature responsiveness are commonly though variably altered in FTLD and are of considerable interest on both neurobiological and clinical grounds. The neuroanatomical correlates of pain processing in the healthy brain comprise a distributed network with critical hubs in thalamus and insula and somatosensory, prefrontal, anterior temporal, limbic and subcortical connections (<xref rid="awv276-B77" ref-type="bibr">Peyron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Herde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B68" ref-type="bibr">Moulton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Temperature sensibility is mediated by a closely overlapping network (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B68" ref-type="bibr">Moulton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Together these networks have a core role in regulation of bodily homeostasis: current neurobiological formulations emphasize convergent processing of somatic and visceral pain and thermoregulatory signals as functionally interdependent aspects of interoception (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Separable network components underpin sensory gating and representation (thalamus, posterior insula, somatosensory cortex), arousal and attention (thalamus, anterior cingulate), evaluative and contextual processing (anterior insula, anterior cingulate, anterior temporal cortex, amygdala, hippocampus), and programming behavioural responses (anterior cingulate, orbitofrontal and prefrontal cortices) (<xref rid="awv276-B39" ref-type="bibr">Greenspan and Winfield, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B77" ref-type="bibr">Peyron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B92" ref-type="bibr">Singer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B13" ref-type="bibr">Brooks <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B44" ref-type="bibr">H&#x000f6;istad and Barbas, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B62" ref-type="bibr">Mazzola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B47" ref-type="bibr">Isnard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B68" ref-type="bibr">Moulton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B64" ref-type="bibr">Meerwijk <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). These networks overlap extensively with networks targeted by the pathological process in FTLD. Impaired body schema integrity has recently been demonstrated in patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<xref rid="awv276-B30" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and may be a generic pathophysiological mechanism of somatic delusions, somatization and other neuropsychiatric symptoms in these patients, due to disruption of a core thalamo-cortico-cerebellar network (<xref rid="awv276-B60" ref-type="bibr">Mahoney <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>); involvement of thalamus, in particular, has emerged as a consistent and early signature of this mutation subgroup (<xref rid="awv276-B86" ref-type="bibr">Rohrer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Impaired appraisal of salient sensory objects and events is integral to the clinical syndromes of semantic dementia and behavioural variant FTD, notably in association with right anterior temporal lobe atrophy (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Chan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Considered together, this evidence suggests that pain and temperature pathophysiology may link brain network disintegration with clinical symptoms in these diseases. However, in contrast with the well-characterized central pain syndromes attending focal lesions of thalamocortical circuitry (<xref rid="awv276-B87" ref-type="bibr">Schmahmann and Leifer, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B9" ref-type="bibr">Blomqvist <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>), the phenomenology of pain and temperature processing and their neuroanatomical bases have not been studied in detail in FTLD. Moreover, altered experience of pain and temperature might be predicted in other neurodegenerative diseases that disrupt the integrity of distributed networks that process pain and temperature (<xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>). A notable test case is Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. Limited available information suggests that sensory encoding and perception of pain are retained in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, at least in early to moderate stage disease, with engagement of a similar central nociceptive network to healthy older individuals (<xref rid="awv276-B18" ref-type="bibr">Cole <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>); however, patients&#x02019; pain tolerance has been variously reported as unaltered, increased or diminished (<xref rid="awv276-B18" ref-type="bibr">Cole <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B19" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B49" ref-type="bibr">Jensen-Dahm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and semantic processing of pain concepts may also be diminished (<xref rid="awv276-B75" ref-type="bibr">Oosterman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p><p>Here we addressed these issues in cohorts of patients representing the major syndromes of FTLD and typical Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. Symptoms suggesting altered pain and temperature processing were characterized using a semi-structured pro forma administered to patients&#x02019; caregivers. Structural neuroanatomical correlates of these symptoms were assessed using voxel-based morphometry (VBM) of patients&#x02019; brain magnetic resonance images. We hypothesized that pain and temperature symptoms would be over-represented in behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia versus progressive non-fluent aphasia (PNFA) and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease, and more specifically, in patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations versus other disease groups; and that behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia have overlapping but differentiable symptom profiles characterized by blunted versus heightened pain and temperature responsiveness, respectively. We further hypothesized that pain and temperature symptoms in the FTLD cohort and in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease would be associated with grey matter atrophy in the distributed network previously implicated in pain and temperature processing in the healthy brain. More specifically, we hypothesized an association of insular atrophy with symptoms across syndromes (<xref rid="awv276-B77" ref-type="bibr">Peyron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>); and partly separable neuroanatomical associations, targeting thalamus in <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations, more anterior cortical regions in other FTLD subgroups and more posterior somatosensory cortical association areas in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (<xref rid="awv276-B18" ref-type="bibr">Cole <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Chan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec sec-type="subjects"><title>Patient characteristics</title><p>Fifty-eight patients with FTLD (25 female, aged 52&#x02013;84 years) and 20 patients with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (eight female, aged 53&#x02013;74 years) were assessed consecutively over a 3-year interval via a tertiary Cognitive Disorders Clinic. All fulfilled consensus diagnostic criteria for a syndrome of FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B37" ref-type="bibr">Gorno-Tempini <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B82" ref-type="bibr">Rascovsky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) (behavioural variant FTD, <italic>n = </italic>21; semantic dementia, <italic>n = </italic>17; PNFA, <italic>n = </italic>20) or for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease led by decline in episodic memory (<xref rid="awv276-B31" ref-type="bibr">Dubois <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>). The syndromic diagnosis was supported in each case by detailed clinical and neuropsychological evaluation following a standard protocol referenced to a historical, age-matched healthy control group (<xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Table 1</xref>) and further corroborated by CSF and brain amyloid PET imaging findings (ratio of total tau: amyloid-&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub> levels &#x0003e;1 in 14/14 Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cases and &#x0003c;0.8 in 13/13 FTLD cases; florbetapir PET-negative for amyloid deposition in 7/7 FTLD cases for which data were available). All patients had MRI profiles of regional brain atrophy concordant with their clinical diagnosis; no patient had radiological evidence of significant or strategic vascular damage. Genetic screening revealed 11 patients with a pathogenic mutation (six <italic>C9orf72</italic>; five <italic>MAPT</italic>). All patients with a genetic mutation presented with behavioural variant FTD apart from one patient with a <italic>C9orf72</italic> expansion who presented with PNFA.
<table-wrap id="awv276-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>General demographic and neuropsychological data for patient subgroups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">FTLD: pain / temperature<hr/></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">AD: pain / temperature<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Healthy controls<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF2"><sup>a</sup></xref></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No symptoms</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptoms</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">No symptoms</th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>General demographics</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic>: total (F:M)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31(10:21)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF3"><sup>b</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (15:12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2:7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF4"><sup>c</sup></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (6:5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (23:27)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic>: syndromes bvFTD / SD / PNFA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/ 11 / 5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 / 6 / 15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic>: no mutation / <italic>C9orf72 / MAPT</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 / 6 / 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 / 0 / 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.4 (52&#x02013;84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.8 (47&#x02013;80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.8 (53&#x02013;71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (57&#x02013;74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.5 (54&#x02013;80)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Education (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9 (11&#x02013;20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (11&#x02013;21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (11&#x02013;17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (12&#x02013;17)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.2 (10&#x02013;18)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symptom duration (years)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5 (3&#x02013;21)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.8 (2&#x02013;18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (2&#x02013;8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5 (4&#x02013;9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MMSE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>21.1 (4&#x02013;30)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>21.9 (1&#x02013;30)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>20 (13&#x02013;25)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>22.5 (14&#x02013;29)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.6 (28&#x02013;30)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>MRI profiles</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF5"><bold><sup>d</sup></bold></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temporal lobe atrophy (L:R:symm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22(8:5:9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16(12:1:3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6(0:0:6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9(0:0:9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frontal lobe atrophy (L:R:symm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10(3:2:5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(6:1:4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parietal lobe atrophy (L:R:symm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3(1:0:2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2(0:0:2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(0:0:1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>General intellect</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Verbal IQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>76 (40&#x02013;126)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>78 (55&#x02013;119)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>86 (55&#x02013;115)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>93 (55&#x02013;120)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (101&#x02013;137)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Performance IQ</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>91 (65&#x02013;136)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>101 (69&#x02013;134)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>81 (59&#x02013;125)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>92 (63&#x02013;119)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115 (84&#x02013;141)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Episodic memory</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMT words (/50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>34 (20&#x02013;49)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>37 (18&#x02013;47)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>29 (17&#x02013;42)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>32 (24&#x02013;50)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (39&#x02013;50)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMT faces (/50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>31 (24&#x02013;50)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF6"><bold>*</bold></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>36 (25&#x02013;47)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>32 (18&#x02013;45)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>39 (24&#x02013;46)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (30&#x02013;50)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Executive function</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop word (90 s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>35 (16&#x02013;90)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>39 (18&#x02013;90)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>43 (17&#x02013;79)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>36.6 (17&#x02013;58)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.7 (15&#x02013;53)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stroop inhibition (180 s)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>100 (48&#x02013;180)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>105 (48&#x02013;180)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>143 (42&#x02013;180)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>101.4 (30&#x02013;180)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6 (35&#x02013;103)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Digit span reverse (/12)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.7 (0&#x02013;7)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4 (0&#x02013;7)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3 (1&#x02013;6)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3.6 (1&#x02013;7)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (3&#x02013;7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Semantic processing</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">BPVS (/150)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>98 (2&#x02013;149)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>118 (8&#x02013;149)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (76&#x02013;146)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">132 (52&#x02013;147)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">147 (137&#x02013;150)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Synonyms (/50)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>34 (12&#x02013;50)</bold><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF3"><bold><sup>b</sup></bold></xref></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>38 (20&#x02013;49)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>41 (30&#x02013;49)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>47.5 (46&#x02013;49)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (36&#x02013;50)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6" rowspan="1"><bold>Visuospatial</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">VOSP object decision (/20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (8&#x02013;20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (10&#x02013;20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>16 (10&#x02013;18)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>15 (7&#x02013;19)</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (12&#x02013;20)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="awv276-TF1"><p>Mean (range) data are shown unless otherwise indicated and maximum scores on neuropsychology tests are also indicated in parentheses. Significant differences (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) between patients and controls are in bold.</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF2"><p><sup>a</sup>Historical age-matched group.</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF3"><p><sup>b</sup>Five patients with altered pain responses only, 13 with altered temperature responses only, 13 with both (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T2">Table 2</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF4"><p><sup>c</sup>Six patients with altered temperature responses only, three with alteration of both pain and temperature responses.</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF5"><p><sup>d</sup>Blinded visual rating of brain MRI scans (L:R:symm, number of cases with relatively focal lobar atrophy predominantly left-sided, right-sided or relatively symmetric; note lobar involvement not mutually exclusive).</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF6"><p>*Significantly (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) different from non-symptomatic patients with FTLD.</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF7"><p>AD = syndrome of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease led by decline in episodic memory; BPVS = British Picture Vocabulary Scale; bvFTD = behavioural variant FTD; F = female; M = male; MMSE = Mini-Mental State Examination score; NA = not applicable; RMT = Recognition Memory Test; SD = semantic dementia; temp = temperature; VOSP = Visual Object and Space Perception battery.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Patients&#x02019; caregivers completed a semi-structured questionnaire designed to identify symptoms suggesting altered pain or temperature processing (altered experience of pain or temperature) developing since the onset of their illness (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 1</ext-link>). This questionnaire recorded caregiver descriptions of patients&#x02019; symptoms and initially sought to capture any unexplained unpleasant physical symptoms more generally, before focusing explicitly on altered behavioural responses to pain or temperature variations. Questionnaire data were analysed off-line to determine the nature of any alteration in pain or temperature responsiveness and its directionality (increased versus decreased), based on caregiver descriptions of patients&#x02019; overt verbal and non-verbal behaviours. Chi-square tests were used to compare categorical differences in symptom prevalence and linear regression was used to compare differences in background demographic and neuropsychological measures between groups. In addition, we assessed for any correlation between pain and temperature symptoms and any alteration in hedonic processing in the domains of music and environmental sounds, as previously recorded for this patient cohort (<xref rid="awv276-B34" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p>All participants gave informed consent to be involved in the study, which was approved by the local institutional ethics committee in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec><sec><title>Brain MRI acquisition and analyses</title><p>At the time of questionnaire data collection each patient underwent volumetric brain MRI on a 3.0 T Siemens scanner using a 32-channel phased-array head coil. A sagittal 3D magnetization prepared rapid gradient echo T<sub>1</sub>-weighted volumetric MRI (echo time/repetition time/inversion time 2.9/2200/900 ms, dimensions 256 &#x000d7; 256 &#x000d7; 208, voxel size 1.1 &#x000d7; 1.1 &#x000d7; 1.1 mm) was acquired. In all cases, volumetric scans were assessed visually in all planes to ensure adequate coverage and to exclude artefacts or significant motion.</p><p>To assess any relation between individual brain atrophy profile and development of pain and temperature symptoms, each patient&#x02019;s brain magnetic resonance scan was reviewed by two experienced cognitive neurologists (P.D.F., J.D.W.) while blinded to symptomatic and clinical syndromic status. In each case, the presence of relatively focal brain atrophy (disproportionate to more diffuse background atrophy) and the direction of any cerebral hemispheric asymmetry on visual inspection were recorded for the frontal, temporal and parietal lobes. Any apparent right:left directionality of atrophy was assessed for each lobar region using chi-square tests.</p><p>Preprocessing of patients&#x02019; brain magnetic resonance images for VBM was performed using New Segment (<xref rid="awv276-B200" ref-type="bibr">Ashburner and Friston, 2005</xref>) and the DARTEL (<xref rid="awv276-B3" ref-type="bibr">Ashburner, 2007</xref>) toolbox of SPM8 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm">www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm</ext-link>) running under Matlab7.0&#x000ae;. Segmentation, normalization and modulation of grey and white matter images were performed using default parameter settings. Images were smoothed using a Gaussian full-width at half-maximum of 6 mm. To adjust for individual differences in global grey matter volume during subsequent analysis, total intracranial volume was calculated for each participant by summing grey matter, white matter and CSF volumes following segmentation of all three tissue classes. A study-specific group mean template brain image was created by warping all native space whole-brain images to the final DARTEL template and calculating the average of the warped brain images.</p><p>Voxel intensity (grey matter volume) was modelled for the combined FTLD cohort and for the Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohort: firstly, as a function of presence versus absence of any symptoms suggesting altered pain or temperature processing; and as a function of presence versus absence of symptoms for pain and for temperature separately. Participant age, total intracranial volume, Mini-Mental State Examination score (as a global measure of disease severity) and syndromic group membership (where relevant) were included as covariates of no interest in the models. In addition, in light of recent evidence suggesting a distinct pathophysiological signature of <italic>C9orf72</italic>-associated FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), we performed a subanalysis of the symptomatic FTLD cohort contrasting patients with and without <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations. To help protect against voxel drop-out due to potentially marked local regional atrophy, a customized explicit brain mask was applied based on a specified &#x02018;consensus&#x02019; voxel threshold intensity criterion (<xref rid="awv276-B83" ref-type="bibr">Ridgway <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) whereby a voxel was included in the analysis if grey matter intensity at that voxel was &#x0003e;0.1 in &#x0003e;70% of participants (rather than in all participants, as with the default SPM8 mask).</p><p>Statistical parametric maps of regional grey matter volume correlating with pain and temperature symptoms were assessed using two prescribed criteria, each thresholded at <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05 after family-wise error (FWE) correction for multiple voxel-wise comparisons. Maps were first assessed after correction over the whole brain volume, to determine any associations that emerged without taking the evidence of previous studies into account. Maps were next assessed after correction within a regional small volume of interest, taking account of previous evidence and our specific anatomical hypotheses: this single anatomical small volume combined structures in both cerebral hemispheres consistently identified as critical for interoceptive and homeostatic processing of pain and temperature in the healthy brain, namely, insular cortex and thalamus (<xref rid="awv276-B58" ref-type="bibr">Lenz <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B27" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B23" ref-type="bibr">Craig <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B13" ref-type="bibr">Brooks <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B51" ref-type="bibr">Kim <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B47" ref-type="bibr">Isnard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B63" ref-type="bibr">Mazzola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). Relevant anatomical subregions were customized from the Oxford/Harvard brain maps in FSLview v3.1 (<xref rid="awv276-B28" ref-type="bibr">Desikan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B48" ref-type="bibr">Jenkinson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) to fit the group mean template brain image. The overall distribution of grey matter atrophy in key disease subgroups with and without pain and temperature symptoms was assessed relative to healthy controls in a separate VBM analysis (further details in the online <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary material</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Analysis of pain and temperature symptoms</title><p>Characteristics of the patient cohort are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Table 1</xref> and a detailed analysis of symptoms is presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T2">Table 2</xref>; extracts from caregiver questionnaire reports for individual patients are presented in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>.
<table-wrap id="awv276-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Detailed description of the symptomatic patient cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="3" colspan="1">Syndromic diagnosis</th><th rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">MRI profile: focal atrophy<sup>a</sup><hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Symptom category</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Response shift</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">TL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">FL</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PL</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/R/symm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/R/symm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">L/R/symm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">P/T/both</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">inc/dec/both<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="awv276-TF9"><sup>b</sup></xref></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavioural variant FTD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2/5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/2/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/0/0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4/7/4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/6/3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Semantic dementia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6/2/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/3/7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8/1/2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PNFA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/1/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/0/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0/1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/3/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3/0/2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0/6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/0/2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/6/3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7/0/2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="awv276-TF8"><p>*Blinded visual rating of brain MRI scans (L:R:symm, number of cases with relatively focal lobar atrophy predominantly left-sided, right-sided or relatively symmetric; note lobar involvement not mutually exclusive).</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF9"><p><sup>b</sup>Variably increased or decreased responsiveness within or between modalities.</p></fn><fn id="awv276-TF10"><p>dec = decreased; FL = frontal lobe atrophy; inc = increased; L = left; N = normal; P = symptoms of altered pain experience; PL = parietal lobe atrophy; R = right; symm = relatively symmetric; T = symptoms of altered temperature experience; TL = temporal lobe atrophy.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Symptoms suggesting abnormalities of pain and/or temperature processing were reported in 31/58 patients with FTLD (53% of the whole FTLD cohort) and in 9/20 patients with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (45% of the Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohort). In both FTLD and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohorts, altered responses to temperature variations were more frequently reported than altered responses to pain. While patients with FTLD (13/31 cases, 41%) and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (3/9, 33%) commonly had altered responses both to pain and temperature, only patients with FTLD (5/31 cases, 16%) had altered pain responses alone. Within the FTLD cohort, symptoms suggesting altered pain or temperature processing were statistically significantly more common in the behavioural variant FTD group (15/21 cases, 71%) and semantic dementia group (11/17 cases, 65%) than in the PNFA group (5/20 cases, 25%: <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05 all comparisons): accordingly, behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia phenotypes were relatively over-represented in the symptomatic FTLD subgroup (<xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Table 1</xref>). Of the genetic FTLD subgroups, patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations were over-represented in the symptomatic subgroup, reporting symptoms suggesting altered pain or temperature processing in all (6/6) cases; whereas these symptoms were recorded less frequently (2/5 cases) for patients with <italic>MAPT</italic> mutations.</p><p>Caregiver reports (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>) revealed a diverse phenomenology of altered pain and temperature experience among patients in the symptomatic cohort. Pain symptoms were variably reported as arising from the external environment or from within the patient&#x02019;s own body; while temperature symptoms were mainly described as subjective discomfort relative to the ambient environment and only occasionally referred to thermal touch <italic>per se</italic>. Symptoms varied widely in intensity and frequency. Both increased responsiveness and decreased responsiveness to pain and temperature variations were described, as well as responses that were variably increased or decreased within or between modalities. Within the temperature modality, patients more often developed a dislike of cold (rather than warm) environments. The directional preponderance of altered pain and temperature responsiveness varied between syndromic groups: within the behavioural variant FTD group, decreased responsiveness and increased responsiveness to pain and temperature variations were equally frequent (each reported in six cases, 40%); whereas increased responsiveness was more commonly described within the semantic dementia group (8/11 cases, 73%), the PNFA group (3/5 cases, 60%) and the Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease group (7/9 cases, 78%; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T2">Table 2</xref>). More complex bidirectional shifts in pain and temperature responses were also described in all syndromic groups. The small <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutation subgroup described symptoms similar to those reported for the cohort as a whole (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 2</ext-link>).</p><p>When neuropsychological profiles in the patient subgroups within the FTLD and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohorts were compared according to the presence or absence of pain and temperature symptoms, the symptomatic FTLD group showed significantly (<italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.01) greater impairment of face memory than the non-symptomatic FTLD subgroup; the subgroups within each disease cohort were otherwise similar overall (<xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Table 1</xref>). Thyroid function (available for 66/78 patients including 34/40 patients with pain and temperature symptoms) was normal in all cases assessed. Three patients in the FTLD cohort with pain and temperature symptoms underwent nerve conduction studies, which were normal in all cases. The presence of pain and/or temperature symptoms was positively correlated with altered liking for music (<italic>P = </italic>0.03) but not environmental sounds (<italic>P = </italic>0.8).</p></sec><sec><title>Neuroanatomical correlates of altered pain and temperature processing</title><p>Visual review of individual patient MRI scans (summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Tables 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T2">2</xref>) revealed an over-representation of cases with relatively focal temporal lobe atrophy in the subgroup of patients with FTLD and pain and temperature symptoms in comparison to the group without such symptoms. In particular, right-sided temporal lobe atrophy was more common in the subgroup of patients with pain and temperature symptoms than the subgroup without symptoms (case ratio 5:1; see <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T1">Table 1</xref>). However, this apparent disproportion was not statistically significant (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). Focal temporal lobe atrophy was frequent in all three FTLD syndromes within the symptomatic cohort but concentrated (as anticipated) in the semantic dementia subgroup. These findings were further corroborated in the VBM analysis mapping overall grey matter atrophy profiles in FTLD subgroups with and without pain and temperature symptoms versus healthy controls (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 1 and</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Table 3</ext-link>). Disproportionate temporal lobe atrophy was also frequent in patients with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and pain and temperature symptoms; however, in contrast to the FTLD cases, none of these Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease patients exhibited asymmetric temporal lobe involvement nor was there any temporal lobe predilection for symptomatic versus non-symptomatic Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cases.</p><p>Regional grey matter correlates of pain and temperature symptoms from the VBM analysis are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T3">Table 3</xref> and statistical parametric maps are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="awv276-F1">Fig. 1</xref>. No grey matter correlates of pain and temperature symptoms were identified at the prescribed corrected significance threshold (<italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05<sub>FWE</sub>) at the level of the whole brain. However, within the combined FTLD cohort, the presence of any alteration in pain or temperature responsiveness was significantly associated with atrophy of right mid insula (and borderline significant also for right posterior insula) when thresholded at <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05<sub>FWE</sub> after correction within the prespecified anatomical region of interest; no significant grey matter associations were identified for pain symptoms or for temperature symptoms separately, at the prescribed threshold. In the separate VBM subanalysis of patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> expansions contrasted with other FTLD patients showing altered pain or temperature responses (<xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T3">Table 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="awv276-F1">Fig. 1</xref>), symptoms due to <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations were significantly associated with atrophy of right posterior thalamus (and borderline significant also for left posterior thalamus; <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.05<sub>FWE</sub> within the prespecified anatomical region of interest). No other grey matter associations were identified at the prescribed significance threshold.
<fig id="awv276-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Statistical parametric maps (SPMs) showing regional grey matter atrophy significantly associated with altered pain and/or temperature responsiveness in the FTLD cohort.</bold> See also <xref ref-type="table" rid="awv276-T3">Table 3</xref>. SPMs are based on the contrast between patient subgroups with and without symptoms in the combined cohort (<italic>All FTLD, top</italic>) and in patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<italic>C9orf72</italic>; all symptomatic) versus symptomatic patients without <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<italic>bottom</italic>). SPMs are thresholded for display purposes at <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.001 uncorrected for multiple comparisons over the whole brain and rendered on sections of a group mean T<sub>1</sub>-weighted magnetic resonance brain template image in MNI standard space; coordinates (mm) of the plane of each section are indicated and the right hemisphere is shown on the right of the coronal sections and the axial section (<italic>bottom right</italic>, magnified to show thalamic anatomy). <italic>Z</italic>-scores for the SPMs are scaled according to the colour bar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="awv276f1p"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="awv276-T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Voxel-based morphometric correlates of altered pain and temperature processing in FTLD</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Grey matter association</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Brain region</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Side</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Cluster (voxels)</th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Peak (mm)<hr/></th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>Z</italic>-score</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>x</italic></bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>y</italic></bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>z</italic></bold></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">All FTLD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mid insula</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">227</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Posterior insula</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1"><italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Posterior thalamus</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">R</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="awv276-TF11"><p>Significant regional correlates of altered pain and temperature processing (grey matter atrophy associated with any symptoms suggesting altered responsiveness to pain and/or temperature) are based on contrasts over the whole frontotemporal lobar degeneration (FTLD) cohort (all symptomatic versus all asymptomatic patients) and in patients with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (all symptomatic versus symptomatic patients without <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations). Associations are reported after correction for multiple voxel-wise comparisons within the prespecified anatomical small volume of interest; all significant clusters &#x0003e;40 voxels are shown and peak (local maximum) coordinates are in MNI standard stereotactic space (see also <xref ref-type="fig" rid="awv276-F1">Fig. 1</xref> and further details in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>To identify any less robust but potentially relevant neuroanatomical associations of pain and temperature symptoms in the patient cohort, we performed a separate <italic>post hoc</italic> exploratory analysis of the VBM data thresholded more leniently at <italic>P &#x0003c; </italic>0.001 uncorrected for multiple voxel-wise comparisons over the whole brain. At this more lenient threshold, additional regional grey matter correlates were observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">3</ext-link>). Pain and temperature symptoms in the combined FTLD cohort and in the subgroup not associated with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations were additionally associated with atrophy of right anterior temporal cortex; while temperature symptoms (but not pain symptoms) in the FTLD cohort were associated with atrophy of right mid-insula (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 2</ext-link>). Pain and temperature symptoms within the smaller Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohort were associated with grey matter atrophy in left angular gyrus (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. 3</ext-link>) using this relaxed criterion.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Here we have shown that altered experience of pain and temperature is common in the major dementia syndromes. Altered behavioural responses to both pain and temperature were frequently reported but more often reported for temperature than pain. In line with our prior hypotheses and previous work (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B94" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B78" ref-type="bibr">Pijnenburg <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B60" ref-type="bibr">Mahoney <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B56" ref-type="bibr">Landqvist Waldo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), certain syndromic signatures were identified. Pain and temperature symptoms were commonly described across FTLD syndromes, exhibited by the majority of patients with behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia and most frequently in the molecular subtype represented by <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations. Patients with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease exhibited similar symptoms in a somewhat lower proportion (45%) of cases. The directionality of symptoms (heightened versus diminished responses to pain and temperature) varied across the cohort but was also modulated by syndrome: increased responsiveness to pain or temperature variations was most often reported in the semantic dementia, PNFA and Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease groups whereas decreased responsiveness was most often associated with behavioural variant FTD, again consistent with previous evidence (<xref rid="awv276-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bathgate <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B14" ref-type="bibr">Carlino <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). Occurrence of symptoms was not simply attributable to disease severity or other demographic or general neuropsychological factors. Though not quantified here, the reported intensity and frequency of symptoms varied widely among individuals in each syndromic group.</p><p>Pain and temperature symptoms were frequently accompanied by focal (and particularly, right-sided) temporal lobe atrophy in individual patients with FTLD, as anticipated from previous work and consistent with the more severe face processing deficit in this FTLD subgroup (<xref rid="awv276-B93" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Chan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B74" ref-type="bibr">Omar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011<italic>b</italic></xref>). However, asymmetric temporal lobe atrophy was not a <italic>sine qua non</italic> for development of such symptoms, as illustrated by the Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cases. In line with these findings and with previous studies in the healthy brain (<xref rid="awv276-B77" ref-type="bibr">Peyron <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B92" ref-type="bibr">Singer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Henderson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B43" ref-type="bibr">Herde <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B47" ref-type="bibr">Isnard <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B68" ref-type="bibr">Moulton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>), a VBM group analysis of patients&#x02019; brain MRIs delineated a distributed network of brain regions where atrophy was associated with altered responsiveness to pain or temperature. The most robust network correlates of pain and temperature symptoms comprised right-lateralized grey matter areas in mid and posterior insula in the combined FTLD group and bilateral posterior thalamus in the <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutation group.</p><p>These findings substantiate current formulations of the neural organization of central somatosensory and homeostatic signal processing (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B79" ref-type="bibr">Preusser <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Peripheral somatic and visceral sensory afferents conveying pain and thermal information relay via postero-lateral thalamic nuclei to somatosensory cortex (Brodmann area 3a) and dorsal posterior insula (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>). While primary somatosensory cortex may process tactile events (<xref rid="awv276-B79" ref-type="bibr">Preusser <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>), classical models emphasizing somatosensory labelled lines have been incorporated by current models that emphasize the intimate association of pain and thermal information and their integration as joint aspects of interoception, salient sensory phenomena that are potentially critical for signalling body homeostasis (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). The posterior insula is a central network hub for integration of these homeostatic signals to map an interoceptive &#x02018;image&#x02019; of body state (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>). Focal lesions of posterior thalamus and posterior insula are well known to produce central pain syndromes and microstimulation of these regions may produce pain and thermal sensations (<xref rid="awv276-B9" ref-type="bibr">Blomqvist <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B62" ref-type="bibr">Mazzola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B96" ref-type="bibr">Sprenger <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The thalamo-insular network plays a broader role in integrating external and interoceptive sensory signals to generate a coherent body schema that defines bodily integrity and agency in relation to the environment (<xref rid="awv276-B58" ref-type="bibr">Lenz <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B27" ref-type="bibr">Davis <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B4" ref-type="bibr">Banzett <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B23" ref-type="bibr">Craig <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B25" ref-type="bibr">Critchley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B26" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B13" ref-type="bibr">Brooks <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B24" ref-type="bibr">Critchley, 2005</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B41" ref-type="bibr">Henderson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B88" ref-type="bibr">Seeley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007<italic>a</italic></xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B90" ref-type="bibr"><italic>b</italic></xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B89" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B20" ref-type="bibr">Corbetta <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B97" ref-type="bibr">Sridharan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B8" ref-type="bibr">Bjornsdotter <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B62" ref-type="bibr">Mazzola <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B63" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B65" ref-type="bibr">Menon and Uddin, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B6" ref-type="bibr">Beissner <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p>Both insula and thalamus are involved by the pathological process in FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B16" ref-type="bibr">Chow <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B106" ref-type="bibr">Zhou <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B35" ref-type="bibr">Garibotto <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). In this regard, it is particularly pertinent that posterior thalamic atrophy emerged here as a signature of pain and temperature symptoms with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations. While the clinical and neuroanatomical phenotypic spectrum of <italic>C9orf72</italic>-associated disease is protean, neuropsychiatric disturbances are often early and prominent and may be underpinned by disintegration of a large-scale cortico-thalamo-cerebellar brain network (<xref rid="awv276-B30" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B60" ref-type="bibr">Mahoney <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B95" ref-type="bibr">Snowden <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B94" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B99" ref-type="bibr">Takada and Sha, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B102" ref-type="bibr">Whitwell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B57" ref-type="bibr">Lee <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B86" ref-type="bibr">Rohrer <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Deranged body schema processing is a candidate pathophysiological mechanism linking network pathology with clinical features in <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), and disturbed pain processing due to thalamic dysfunction might be a critical signal of this more general impairment in representing bodily integrity. It would be intriguing if this clinical phenotype had a specific micro-anatomical marker (<xref rid="awv276-B9" ref-type="bibr">Blomqvist <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>). Pathological data have demonstrated heavy thalamic involvement in a series of <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutation cases reporting a high frequency of unexplained somatic and visceral pains during life (<xref rid="awv276-B55" ref-type="bibr">Landqvist Waldo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Although precise localization was not possible in this study, the posterior thalamic correlate identified in the <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutation group here closely approximates several potentially relevant thalamic subregions. These include pulvinar, which may regulate cortical &#x02018;set&#x02019; for interpreting painful stimuli (<xref rid="awv276-B91" ref-type="bibr">Shipp, 2003</xref>); and the posterior portion of the ventral medial thalamic nucleus, which is likely to serve as a dedicated spinothalamocortical relay for pain and temperature sensations and may play a fundamental role in signalling physiological body states (<xref rid="awv276-B9" ref-type="bibr">Blomqvist <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000</xref>).</p><p>Caution is needed in interpreting the additional neuroanatomical correlates identified in this study, as these were exploratory and substantially less statistically robust. However, involvement of right anterior temporal cortex in the FTLD group (and more particularly, the subgroup of patients without <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations) here was corroborated both by inspection of individual magnetic resonance brain images and the relaxed VBM analysis, and chimes with previous evidence implicating this region in non-verbal sensory semantic (including pain and somatic) processing (<xref rid="awv276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Chan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B36" ref-type="bibr">Goll <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B71" ref-type="bibr">Omar <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B73" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B45" ref-type="bibr">Hsieh <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Unpleasant somatic and visceral sensory experiences occur with focal damage involving this region (<xref rid="awv276-B69" ref-type="bibr">Naga <italic>et al.</italic>, 2004</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B32" ref-type="bibr">Erickson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), while anterior temporal lobe dysfunction associated with migraine enhances thalamo-cortical connectivity (<xref rid="awv276-B67" ref-type="bibr">Moulton <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The temporal lobe may play a key role in contextualizing unpleasant sensory experience by linking these to other data on current bodily state, previous autobiographical experiences and stored conceptual (including social normative) knowledge (<xref rid="awv276-B81" ref-type="bibr">Rankin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B105" ref-type="bibr">Zahn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B2" ref-type="bibr">Aminoff <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B46" ref-type="bibr">Irish <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>) and by engaging a distributed anterior fronto-temporal appraisal network (<xref rid="awv276-B40" ref-type="bibr">Guo <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). Degradation of this contextualizing function might preclude programming of a coherent, organized behavioural response to pain and temperature variations. The critical linkage of anterior temporal mechanisms with interoceptive processing networks is likely to be mediated via an integrative hub in mid-insular cortex (<xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>), which emerged as a separate neuroanatomical correlate of altered pain and temperature responsiveness here. This region may be involved in generating subjective psychological states via projections to anterior insula, anterior cingulate, orbitofrontal and prefrontal cortices and in programming coherent autonomic effector responses (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B38" ref-type="bibr">Grecucci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). This in turn suggests a brain substrate for autonomic dysregulation in FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B1" ref-type="bibr">Ahmed <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>).</p><p>With a similar caveat regarding interpretation of uncorrected data, VBM analysis of the present Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohort revealed a distinct cortical correlate of pain and temperature symptoms in inferior parietal cortex. This cortical region has been implicated in processing pain and in particular, in reorienting brain activity between resting &#x02018;default mode&#x02019; and active attention to salient stimuli (<xref rid="awv276-B52" ref-type="bibr">Kucyi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B12" ref-type="bibr">Bray <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>). Moreover, the region is a core target of pathology in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease (<xref rid="awv276-B100" ref-type="bibr">Warren <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>) and may be involved in a range of behavioural features in this disease that remain incompletely characterized. These Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease-associated behavioural changes include anxiety and hyper-emotionality, features that also typically develop in chronic pain syndromes (<xref rid="awv276-B98" ref-type="bibr">Sturm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B53" ref-type="bibr">Kucyi <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B80" ref-type="bibr">Pujol <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Aberrant activity of temporo-parietal cortex in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease might disrupt processing of interoceptive signals, both by amplifying ruminative awareness of body states via the default mode network and by gating activity in insula and anterior networks that reciprocally interact in evaluating salient stimuli (<xref rid="awv276-B38" ref-type="bibr">Grecucci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B59" ref-type="bibr">Letzen <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). The relative prominence of temperature (relative to pain) symptoms in the Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease cohort here supports this interpretation, as under most circumstances thermal comfort or distress reflects the degree of perceived mismatch between one&#x02019;s own body temperature and the environment; temperature sensibility might therefore be regarded as a probe of interoceptive signal processing <italic>par excellence</italic> (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>).</p><p>Our focus on behaviourally relevant symptoms underlines several challenges in studying patients&#x02019; experience of pain and temperature. As conceptualized in contemporary neurobiological models (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, 2009) and illustrated by the present behavioural data, these are complex psychological constructs: alteration in a patient&#x02019;s responsiveness to pain or temperature variations might reflect altered awareness, tolerance, motivation, behavioural organization or some interaction of these, all potentially dissociable processes. Informant-derived data are subject to bias: caregivers may be more likely to report patients&#x02019; behaviour or verbal output where these are heightened rather than attenuated, while certain modalities (such as non-painful thermal touch) are intrinsically less accessible to such reporting. In a number of cases, complex or bidirectional shifts in patient behaviour were described; the attempt to assign a direction to behavioural change is particularly problematic in the case of temperature processing, which might, in principle, reflect altered sensitivity to external heat, cold or both relative to own body temperature. Moreover, structural neuroanatomical correlation using VBM is a rather blunt instrument for investigating such complex network-based processes. In addition to any direct association with atrophy profile, relevant disease effects are likely to reside in connectivity alterations among network elements that are not captured on VBM, perhaps accounting for the absence here of disease effects in anterior cingulate or orbitofrontal regions that might have been anticipated <italic>a priori</italic> (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). On the other hand, VBM can identify brain substrates that are critical in the generation of symptoms.</p><p>Taking the above caveats into account, the present behavioural, MRI and VBM data together allow certain conclusions to be drawn about the breakdown of brain organization for pain and temperature processing in these neurodegenerative diseases. The processing of pain and temperature entails the transformation of sensory data into a complex experiential construct via hierarchical and integrative processing over a series of cortical relays: these stimuli are of fundamental biological significance (demanding high fidelity decoding) and at the same time, richly invested with subjective emotional, mnestic and semantic associations (demanding contextual editing and interpretation). As such, pain and temperature provide a paradigmatic illustration of a key principle of cortical neurobiology (<xref rid="awv276-B66" ref-type="bibr">Mesulam, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, 2009) and an ideal probe of large-scale brain network operations in neurodegenerative disease (<xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). The present evidence suggests a model for synthesizing neurodegenerative disease effects on these cortical operations that is consistent both with data from normal neurophysiological and functional neuroimaging work and the effects of focal brain lesions (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr">Borsook, 2012</xref>). According to this synthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="awv276-F2">Fig. 2</xref>), <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations target early encoding of pain and temperature signals at the level of thalamo-cortical circuitry, accounting for the high proportion of cases reporting relevant symptoms here; while behavioural variant FTD more generally disrupts the relay of body state information from posterior insula and its integration with hedonic and environmental context in mid insula and more anterior regions. This interpretation allows for either abnormally reduced or abnormally increased subjective awareness of homeostatic signals, based on the extent to which network activity is interrupted or continues to transfer noisy signals (a mechanism potentially analogous to pain asymbolia following focal insular lesions: <xref rid="awv276-B7" ref-type="bibr">Berthier <italic>et al.</italic>, 1988</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B61" ref-type="bibr">Masson <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991</xref>). Such noisy processing might involve degraded temporal scheduling of salient sensory and emotional signals, a key function attributed to anterior insula that is vulnerable in FTLD (<xref rid="awv276-B103" ref-type="bibr">Wiener and Coslett, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B42" ref-type="bibr">Henley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). More anterior insular regions are also targeted in PNFA, providing a candidate locus for altered homeostatic awareness in this syndrome (<xref rid="awv276-B89" ref-type="bibr">Seeley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>). Degeneration of anterior temporal lobe mechanisms in semantic dementia impairs contextual processing of minor discomforts via the linkage to mid insula, resulting in aberrant &#x02018;over-valuation&#x02019; (decreased tolerance) of such stimuli; while temporo-parietal cortical damage in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease leads to aberrant salience coding of homeostatic signals, perhaps via abnormally enhanced gating of interoceptive information between the default mode network and anterior salience network (<xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>).
<fig id="awv276-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>A schematic synthesis of the effects of dementia syndromes on pain and temperature processing. Based on present data and current formulations of central homeostasis (</bold><xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Craig, 2002, 2009</bold></xref><bold>; </bold><xref rid="awv276-B44" ref-type="bibr"><bold>H&#x000f6;istad and Barbas, 2008</bold></xref><bold>; </bold><xref rid="awv276-B10" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Borsook, 2012</bold></xref><bold>; </bold><xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr"><bold>Zhou and Seeley, 2014)</bold></xref><bold>.</bold> Ellipses indicate core components of the homeostatic processing network, rectangles indicate linked brain regions that modulate processing of homeostatic signals and arrows signify predominant direction of information flow; anatomical regions are labelled alongside their putative roles in the processing hierarchy (grey filled ellipses) and dementia syndromes are labelled (italics) with grey crosses indicating the major locus of dysfunction in that syndrome. According to the proposed synthesis, <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations target early encoding of pain and temperature signals in thalamo-cortical circuitry; behavioural variant FTD disrupts the relay of body state information from posterior insula and both behavioural variant FTD and PNFA degrade its contextual integration in mid insula and more anterior regions; semantic dementia degrades anterior temporal lobe mechanisms that evaluate stimulus context; and temporo-parietal cortical damage in Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease leads to abnormally enhanced gating and aberrant salience coding of homeostatic signals. Besides interruption of signalling pathways, degraded (e.g. temporally dysregulated) information flow may also contribute to network dysfunction (<xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>). ACC = anterior cingulate cortex; AD = Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease; ant = anterior; bvFTD = behavioural variant FTD; OFC = orbitofrontal cortex; post = posterior; SD = semantic dementia; TL = temporal lobe; TPJ = temporo-parietal junction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="awv276f2p"/></fig></p><p>This model does not exclude the possibility of additional loci (for example, spinal and brainstem pathways) at which neurodegenerative pathologies might degrade pain and temperature signals, with potential consequences for cortical elaboration of these signals (<xref rid="awv276-B11" ref-type="bibr">Braak <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B70" ref-type="bibr">Olausson <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). However, the cerebral regions implicated in altered pain and temperature processing here overlap closely with regions previously implicated in social cognition, underlining the close coupling of homeostatic and social signal processing and their joint vulnerability in disease states (<xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B38" ref-type="bibr">Grecucci <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). Related phenomena such as social touch (the human analogue of grooming behaviour) are likely to share this brain circuitry and may contribute to deficits of interpersonal awareness in FTLD and other dementias (<xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2009</xref>). It is increasingly recognized that neurodegenerative diseases disrupt the hedonic valuation of a range of sensory signals. Besides pain and temperature, this spectrum includes signals related to eating and satiety (<xref rid="awv276-B101" ref-type="bibr">Whitwell <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B104" ref-type="bibr">Woolley <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>), music and other complex sounds (<xref rid="awv276-B33" ref-type="bibr">Fletcher <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B34" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and somatosensory boundaries (<xref rid="awv276-B30" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). It is therefore of interest that homeostatic symptoms in the present patient cohort were correlated with altered hedonic valuation of music. This work has demonstrated neural networks that are engaged jointly by these diverse phenomena and reaffirms the primacy of the thalamo-insular linkage in regulating the interface between homeostatic and environmental contingencies, reward and punishment (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B76" ref-type="bibr">Perry <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>). Furthermore, pain like other signals in this spectrum is a crucial basis for empathy and understanding of others&#x02019; mental states, suggesting a mechanism for co-opting this same brain circuitry to represent selves other than one&#x02019;s own. Such &#x02018;mentalizing&#x02019; activity been proposed as the evolutionary driver for music (<xref rid="awv276-B17" ref-type="bibr">Clark <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>) and its disruption is an essential harbinger of many dementias (<xref rid="awv276-B81" ref-type="bibr">Rankin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B98" ref-type="bibr">Sturm <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013</xref>).</p><p>From a clinical perspective, the present work provides a framework for understanding an important category of symptoms that has been under-emphasized in neurodegenerative disease. Our findings underline the prevalence of pain and temperature symptoms across the FTLD spectrum and suggest a syndromic preponderance characterized by blunted versus heightened responsiveness to pain and temperature signals in behavioural variant FTD and semantic dementia, respectively. This syndromic association in turn may suggest a candidate mechanism for the somatization, hypochondriasis and abnormal illness behaviour that these patients frequently exhibit, particularly in the setting of focal right temporal lobe atrophy (<xref rid="awv276-B15" ref-type="bibr">Chan <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>): bodily sensations divested of contextual meaning might plausibly drive such behaviours, particularly if compounded by deficits of social comportment (<xref rid="awv276-B81" ref-type="bibr">Rankin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B105" ref-type="bibr">Zahn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B46" ref-type="bibr">Irish <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>). Prominent pain and temperature alterations may constitute a clinical signature of <italic>Corf72</italic> mutations. Perhaps more surprisingly, our findings suggest that similar symptoms (particularly affecting thermoregulatory signals) are not uncommon in patients with Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease and have probably been under-recognized. Aside from any potential value in diagnosing dementia syndromes, improved understanding of patients&#x02019; experience of pain and temperature holds clear practical implications for management. The present findings go beyond the simple assumption that cognitive impairment hampers communication of distress&#x02014;the data suggest that underlying brain mechanisms of pain and temperature processing may be altered in dementia. Patients with dementia may be at increased risk of undetected illness or injury and potentially vulnerable to hypothermia, or other homeostatic derangements. The recognition that homeostatic processing may be significantly degraded in these diseases paves the way for developing strategies to ensure that patients are neither subjected to futile diagnostic procedures nor denied medical attention simply because they are uncomplaining.</p><p>This study suggests a number of directions for further work. Future studies should engage larger patient cohorts and assess those cohorts longitudinally, to allow more detailed clinical stratification and validate the diagnostic biomarker potential of pain and temperature alterations; ultimately, histopathological correlation will be required. The Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease group here was relatively young; further work should extend this population to the wider population of older-onset Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease. Processing of pain and thermal signals should be directly assessed and clinical rating scales should be verified using quantitative sensory testing and other neurophysiological and autonomic techniques and brain mechanisms should be elucidated using parallel functional neuroimaging paradigms. Rather than relying on a simplified binary classification (symptoms present or absent), future work should code symptom frequency and intensity for parametric correlation with other disease measures. It will also be important to explore patients&#x02019; conceptualization of interoceptive signals, as this might yield further signatures of disease [for example, delusional elaboration in association with <italic>C9orf72</italic> mutations (<xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>); degraded semantic representations of pain, potentially relevant to a number of diseases (<xref rid="awv276-B75" ref-type="bibr">Oosterman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>)]. Pain and temperature may constitute a useful model system for investigating abnormalities of sensory salience, homeostatic and self schema processing that are core to the pathophysiology of canonical neurodegenerative diseases (<xref rid="awv276-B21" ref-type="bibr">Craig, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="awv276-B22" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B29" ref-type="bibr">Downey <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014</xref>; <xref rid="awv276-B107" ref-type="bibr">Zhou and Seeley, 2014</xref>).</p></sec>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplementary Table 1</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="brain_awv276_index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application"
mime-subtype="x-zip-compressed"
xlink:href="suppl_data.zip"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to all patients and healthy volunteers for their participation. We thank our two anonymous reviewers for helpful insights.</p></ack><sec><title>Funding</title><p>The Dementia Research Centre is supported by <funding-source>Alzheimer's Research UK</funding-source>, the <funding-source>Brain Research</funding-source> Trust and the <funding-source>Wolfson Foundation</funding-source>. This work was supported by the <funding-source>Wellcome Trust, the UK Medical Research Council and the NIHR Queen Square Dementia Biomedical Research Unit</funding-source>. The amyloid PET study mentioned was supported by funding from <funding-source>AVID Radiopharamaceuticals (a wholly owned subsidiary of Eli Lilly) and the National Brain Appeal - Frontotemporal Dementia Research Fund</funding-source>. P.D.F. is supported by an MRC Research Training Fellowship. H.L.G. holds an Alzheimer Research UK PhD Fellowship. N.C.F. and M.N.R. are NIHR senior investigators. J.D.W. holds a Wellcome Trust Senior Clinical Fellowship (Grant No <award-id>091673/Z/10/Z</award-id>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials"><title>Supplementary material</title><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/brain/awv276/-/DC1">Supplementary material</ext-link> is available at <italic>Brain</italic> online.</p></sec><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations</title><def-item><term id="G1">FTD</term><def><p>frontotemporal dementia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G2">FTLD</term><def><p>frontotemporal lobar degeneration</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G3">PNFA</term><def><p>progressive non-fluent aphasia</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="G4">VBM</term><def><p>voxel-based morphometry</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="awv276-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Iodice</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Daveson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiernan</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Piguet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Autonomic dysregulation in frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1048</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25550415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aminoff</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kveraga</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The role of the parahippocampal cortex in cognition</article-title>. <source>Trends Cogn Sci</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23850264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A fast diffeomorphic image registration algorithm</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>113</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17761438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B200"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friston</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Unified segmentation</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>260</volume>: <fpage>839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15955494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banzett</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mulnier</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Breathlessness in humans activates insular cortex</article-title>. <source>Neuroreport</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>2117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10923655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bathgate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Snowden</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neary</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Behaviour in frontotemporal dementia, Alzheimer's disease and vascular dementia</article-title>. <source>Acta Neurol Scand</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11421849</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beissner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Napadow</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The autonomic brain: an activation likelihood estimation meta-analysis for central processing of autonomic function</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>10503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23785162</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berthier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Starkstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiguarda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Asymbolia for pain: a sensory-limbic disconnection syndrome</article-title><italic>.</italic>
<source>Ann Neurol</source>
<year>1988</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3415199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjornsdotter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Loken</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Olausson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallbo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatotopic organization of gentle touch processing in the posterior insular cortex</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>9314</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625521</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blomqvist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cytoarchitectonic and immunohistochemical characterization of a specific pain and temperature relay, the posterior portion of the ventral medial nucleus, in the human thalamus</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10686182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neurological diseases and pain</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>320</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22067541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braak</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sastre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohl</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vos</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Tredici</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parkinson's disease: lesions in dorsal horn layer I, involvement of parasympathetic and sympathetic pre- and postganglionic neurons</article-title>. <source>Acta Neuropathol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>421</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17294202</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Iaria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Spatial and temporal functional connectivity changes between resting and attentive states</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp</source>
<year>2015</year>: <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25271132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>JCW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zambreanu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Godinez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatotopic organisation of the human insula to painful heat studied with high resolution functional imaging</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15921935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carlino</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Benedetti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rainero</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Asteggiano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarenzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pain perception and tolerance in patients with frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20934811</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pijnenburg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitwell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Scahill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The clinical profile of right temporal lobe atrophy</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>1287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19297506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Izenberg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Binns</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuss</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Magnetic resonance imaging in frontotemporal dementia shows subcortical atrophy</article-title>. <source>Dem Ger Cogn Disord</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Brain disorders and the biological role of music</article-title>. <source>Soc Cogn Affect Neurosci</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24847111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pain sensitivity and fMRI pain-related brain activity in Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>2957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951408</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gavrilescu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The impact of Alzheimer's disease on the functional connectivity between brain regions underlying pain perception</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>568 e1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21257326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbetta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The reorienting system of the human brain: from environment to theory of mind</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18466742</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>How do you feel? Interoception: the sense of the physiological condition of the body</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12154366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>How do you feel&#x02013;now? The anterior insula and human awareness</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19096369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Thermosensory activation of insular cortex</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>184</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10649575</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neural mechanisms of autonomic, affective, and cognitive integration</article-title>. <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>493</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16254997</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Corfield</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandler</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cerebral correlates of autonomic cardiovascular arousal: a functional neuroimaging investigation in humans</article-title>. <source>J Physiol</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>523 (Pt 1)</volume>, <fpage>259</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673560</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathias</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dissecting axes of autonomic control in humans: insights from neuroimaging</article-title>. <source>Auton Neurosci</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>161</volume>: <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozano</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Manduch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasker</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dostrovsky</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Thalamic relay site for cold perception in humans</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>1970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10200232</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Desikan</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Segonne</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischl</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dickerson</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Blacker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>An automated labeling system for subdividing the human cerebral cortex on MRI scans into gyral based regions of interest</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>968</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16530430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Agustus</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schott</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Altered body schema processing in frontotemporal dementia with C9ORF72 mutations</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24521566</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Impaired self-other differentiation in frontotemporal dementia due to the C9ORF72 expansion</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Res Ther</source>
<year>2012</year><italic>;</italic>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23016833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubois</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacova</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dekosky</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Barberger-Gateau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Research criteria for the diagnosis of Alzheimer's disease: revising the NINCDS-ADRDA criteria</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>734</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erickson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Clapp</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jabbari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatosensory auras in refractory temporal lobe epilepsy</article-title>. <source>Epilepsia</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16417550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Witoonpanich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The brain basis of musicophilia: evidence from frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>347</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23801975</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Slattery</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Auditory hedonic phenotypes in dementia: A behavioural and neuroanatomical analysis</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25929717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garibotto</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Borroni</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Agosti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Premi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberici</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eickhoff</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Subcortical and deep cortical atrophy in Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol Aging</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19501427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goll</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Loo</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Frost</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bamiou</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Non-verbal sound processing in the primary progressive aphasias</article-title><italic>.</italic>
<source>Brain</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19797352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappa</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Classification of primary progressive aphasia and its variants</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1006</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21325651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grecucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Giorgetta</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonini</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanfey</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reappraising social emotions: the role of inferior frontal gyrus, temporo-parietal junction and insula in interpersonal emotion regulation</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24027512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reversible pain and tactile deficits associated with a cerebral tumor compressing the posterior insula and parietal operculum</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>1992</year>; <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1513603</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gesierich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trujillo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shany-Ur</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Anterior temporal lobe degeneration produces widespread network-driven dysfunction</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>2979</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24072486</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandevia</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Macefield</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatotopic organization of the processing of muscle and cutaneous pain in the left and right insula cortex: a single-trial fMRI study</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17011704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinnunen</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Degradation of cognitive timing mechanisms in behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25447066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herde</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Strupf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Handwerker</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Itch induced by a novel method leads to limbic deactivations a functional MRI study</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>2347</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17715198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000f6;istad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Sequence of information processing for emotions through pathways linking temporal and insular cortices with the amygdala</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornberger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Piguet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neural basis of music knowledge: evidence from the dementias</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>2523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21857031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Piguet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Right anterior temporal lobe dysfunction underlies theory of mind impairments in semantic dementia</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>1241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24523434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isnard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauguiere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Larrea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Does the insula tell our brain that we are in pain?</article-title>
<source>Pain</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>152</volume>: <fpage>946</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21277680</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckmann</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Behrens</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolrich</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>FSL</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>782</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21979382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen-Dahm</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Werner</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballegaard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hejl</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Quantitative sensory testing and pain tolerance in patients with mild to moderate Alzheimer disease compared to healthy control subjects</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>1439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24412285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jesso</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Morlog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The effects of oxytocin on social cognition and behaviour in frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>2493</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>501</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21859765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenspan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Coghill</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>(2007) Lesions limited to the human thalamic principal somatosensory nucleus (ventral caudal) are associated with loss of cold sensations and central pain</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>4995</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5004</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17475808</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kucyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodaie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Lateralization in intrinsic functional connectivity of the temporoparietal junction with salience- and attention-related brain networks</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>3382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23019004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kucyi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moayedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Weissman-Fogel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenenbaum</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Enhanced medial prefrontal-default mode network functional connectivity in chronic pain and its association with pain rumination</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>3969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24623774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumfor</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Piguet</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Disturbance of emotion processing in frontotemporal dementia: a synthesis of cognitive and neuroimaging findings</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychol Rev</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22577002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landqvist Waldo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Traynor</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Renton</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Frontotemporal dementia with a C9ORF72 expansion in a Swedish family: clinical and neuropathological characteristics</article-title>. <source>Am J Neurodegen Dis</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landqvist Waldo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Santillo</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Passant</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>(2014) Somatic complaints in frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Am J Neurodegen Dis</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Khazenzon</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trujillo</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Altered network connectivity in frontotemporal dementia with C9orf72 hexanucleotide repeat expansion</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>3047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25273996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenz</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Seike</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoja</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Thermal and pain sensations evoked by in the area of human ventrocaudal nucleus</article-title>. <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8360716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letzen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Craggs</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlstein</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional connectivity of the default mode network and its association with pain networks in irritable bowel patients assessed via lidocaine treatment</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>1077</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>87</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23743257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lashley</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mok</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakespeare</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Frontotemporal dementia with the C9ORF72 hexanucleotide repeat expansion: clinical, neuroanatomical and neuropathological features</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>736</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Koskas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cambier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Masson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>[Left pseudothalamic cortical syndrome and pain asymbolia]</article-title>. <source>Rev Neurol</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>147</volume>: <fpage>668</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1763257</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Isnard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guenot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauguiere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatotopic organization of pain responses to direct electrical stimulation of the human insular cortex</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>146</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19665303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzola</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Isnard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauguiere</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stimulation of the human cortex and the experience of pain: Wilder Penfield's observations revisited</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22036962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meerwijk</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>(2013) Brain regions associated with psychological pain: implications for a neural network and its relationship to physical pain</article-title>. <source>Brain Image Behav</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Uddin</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>(2010) Saliency, switching, attention and control: a network model of insula function</article-title>. <source>Brain Struct Funct</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>214</volume>: <fpage>655</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20512370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mesulam</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>From sensation to cognition</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>121</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9648540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Becerra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Pendse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Painful heat reveals hyperexcitability of the temporal pole in interictal and ictal migraine States</article-title>. <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562317</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moulton</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pendse</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Becerra, L.R. &#x00026; Borsook, D. BOLD responses in somatosensory cortices better reflect heat sensation than pain</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>6024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22539862</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naga</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Devinsky</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatoform disorders after temporal lobectomy</article-title>. <source>Cogn Behav Neurol</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15453513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olausson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wessberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>McGlone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vallbo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The neurophysiology of unmyelinated tactile afferents</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18952123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailstone</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Crutch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The cognitive organization of music knowledge: a clinical analysis</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Henley</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailstone</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The structural neuroanatomy of music emotion recognition: evidence from frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2011a</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21385617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahoney</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Flavour identification in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23138765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hailstone</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural neuroanatomy of face processing in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
<year>2011b</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21172863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oosterman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lord</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>When pain memories are lost: a pilot study of semantic knowledge of pain in dementia</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24401151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Anatomical correlates of reward-seeking behaviours in behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>1621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24740987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Larrea</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional imaging of brain responses to pain</article-title>. <source>A review and meta-analysis Neurophysiol Clin</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11126640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pijnenburg</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillissen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheltens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Initial complaints in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>Dem Ger Cogn Dis</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preusser</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiel</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rook</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Roggenhofer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosatschek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Draganski</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The perception of touch and the ventral somatosensory pathway</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25541190</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Macia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Fontanals</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco-Hinojo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Sola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Blanco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The contribution of sensory system functional connectivity reduction to clinical pain in fibromyalgia</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>1492</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>503</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24792477</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorno-Tempini</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Glenn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Structural anatomy of empathy in neurodegenerative disease</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>2945</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17008334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rascovsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Knopman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sensitivity of revised diagnostic criteria for the behavioural variant of frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>2456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21810890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ridgway</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ourselin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Issues with threshold masking in voxel-based morphometry of atrophied brains</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>99</fpage>-<lpage>&#x02013;111</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18848632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Receptive prosody in nonfluent primary progressive aphasias</article-title>. <source>Cortex</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>308</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21047627</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohrer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cash</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Swieten</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dopper</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiskoot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Presymptomatic cognitive and neuroanatomical changes in genetic frontotemporal dementia in the Genetic Frontotemporal dementia Initiative (GENFI) study: a cross-sectional analysis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Neurol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25662776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmahmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Leifer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Parietal pseudothalamic pain syndrome. Clinical features and anatomic correlates</article-title>. <source>Arch Neurol</source>
<year>1992</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>1032</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1417510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Allman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlin</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Macedo</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Divergent social functioning in behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia and Alzheimer disease: reciprocal networks and neuronal evolution</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Dis Assoc Disord</source>
<year>2007a</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>S50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neurodegenerative diseases target large-scale human brain networks</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19376066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Schatzberg</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Dissociable intrinsic connectivity networks for salience processing and executive control</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<year>2007b</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shipp</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The functional logic of cortico-pulvinar connections</article-title>. <source>Phil Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>1605</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Doherty</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaube</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Empathy for pain involves the affective but not sensory components of pain</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>303</volume>: <fpage>1157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14976305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowden</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bathgate</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Blackshaw</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibbons</surname><given-names>ZC</given-names></name><name><surname>Neary</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Distinct behavioural profiles in frontotemporal dementia and semantic dementia</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowden</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Neary</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Frontotemporal dementia with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: a clinical comparison of patients with and without repeat expansions in C9orf72</article-title>. <source>Amyotroph Lateral Scler Frontotemporal Degener</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>172</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>76</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23421625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowden</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stopford</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>AMT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Distinct clinical and pathological characteristics of frontotemporal dementia associated with C9ORF72 mutations</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>708</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22300873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprenger</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Valet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Andreou</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Foerschler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Assessing the risk of central post-stroke pain of thalamic origin by lesion mapping</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>2536</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22719000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sridharan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levitin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A critical role for the right fronto-insular cortex in switching between central-executive and default-mode networks</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>12569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18723676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sturm</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Heightened emotional contagion in mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer's disease is associated with temporal lobe degeneration</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>9944</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23716653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takada</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sha</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Neuropsychiatric features of C9orf72-associated behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia and frontotemporal dementia with motor neuron disease</article-title>. <source>Alzheimers Res Ther</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23034079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The paradox of syndromic diversity in Alzheimer disease</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22801974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitwell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Loy</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossor</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>VBM signatures of abnormal eating behaviours in frontotemporal lobar degeneration</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17240166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitwell</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigand</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boeve</surname><given-names>BF</given-names></name><name><surname>Senjem</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gunter</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>DeJesus-Hernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Neuroimaging signatures of frontotemporal dementia genetics: C9ORF72, tau, progranulin and sporadics</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>135</volume>: <fpage>794</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>806</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22366795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiener</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coslett</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Disruption of temporal processing in a subject with probable frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychologia</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>1927</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18329055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Natesan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Karydas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dallman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Havel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Satiety-related hormonal dysregulation in behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24415571</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moll</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyengar</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Social conceptual impairments in frontotemporal lobar degeneration with right anterior temporal hypometabolism</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>132</volume>: <fpage>604</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19153155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gennatas</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Growdon</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabinovici</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Divergent network connectivity changes in behavioural variant frontotemporal dementia and Alzheimer's disease</article-title>. <source>Brain</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>1352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20410145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="awv276-B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Network dysfunction in Alzheimer's disease and frontotemporal dementia: implications for psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24629669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>