<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">SAGE Open Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">SAGE Open Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCO</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spsco</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>SAGE Open Medical Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2050-313X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5464513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2050313X17713150</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2050313X17713150</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Tinnitus after administration of sublingual immunotherapy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juel</surname><given-names>Jacob</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2050313X17713150"/></contrib><aff id="aff1-2050313X17713150">Department of Plastic Surgery, Aalborg University Hospital, Aalborg, Denmark</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2050313X17713150">Jacob Juel, Department of Plastic Surgery, Aalborg University Hospital, Sdr. Skovvej 3, DK-9000 Aalborg, Denmark. Email: <email>Jacob.juel@rn.dk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><elocation-id>2050313X17713150</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="section1-2050313X17713150"><title>Background/objectives:</title><p>Sublingual immunotherapy was first described in 1986. Since then, its use has been increased as an alternative to subcutaneously administered immunotherapy in the treatment of allergic rhinitis. The most common side effects are of oropharyngeal and gastrointestinal in nature, for example, itching, swelling, irritation, ulceration of the oropharynx and nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhoea, and vomiting. More severe side effects are dominated by systemic and respiratory tract manifestations.</p></sec><sec id="section2-2050313X17713150"><title>Results:</title><p>In this clinical case, the author reports a right-sided transient tinnitus lasting for 48&#x02009;h after administration of sublingual immunotherapy for house dust mite in allergic rhinitis.</p></sec><sec id="section3-2050313X17713150"><title>Conclusions:</title><p>This case provide important insights for clinical practice, as tinnitus has not been previously reported as a side effect of sublingual immunotherapy with house dust mite allergens.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Sublingual immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>allergic rhinitis</kwd><kwd>side effects</kwd><kwd>tinnitus</kwd><kwd>ACARIZAX</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="section4-2050313X17713150"><title>Introduction</title><p>Allergen immunotherapy has traditionally been administered by subcutaneous injections, but regular injections for a period of 3&#x02013;5&#x02009;years are often required for efficacy. Conversely, sublingual immunotherapy (SLIT), first described in 1986,<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> is given as a tablet or a liquid extract. Since then, its use has been growing globally, representing an alternative to subcutaneously administered immunotherapy in the treatment of allergic rhinitis. The safety profile of SLIT is superior to that of subcutaneously administered immunotherapy, as side effects are less severe and frequent.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Furthermore, SLIT can be self-administered. The clinical efficacy in allergic rhinitis due to house dust mite (HDM) allergens is well established.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Mild side effects are frequent primarily in the initial period of SLIT treatment and include both local and systemic manifestations. Anaphylaxis has been reported, but it is considered as extremely rare.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> The most common local side effects are of oropharyngeal and gastrointestinal in nature, for example, itching, swelling, irritation, ulceration of the oropharynx and nausea, abdominal pain, diarrhoea, and vomiting. Pruritus and itching of the ear canal have also been reported. Systemic side effects are dominated by respiratory tract manifestations, particularly rhinitis and asthma, but angioedema and urticaria may occur, although less frequently compared to local side effects.</p></sec><sec id="section5-2050313X17713150"><title>Case study</title><p>The SLIT dosage regimen of the current case was initiated as one tablet a day (ACARIZAX 12 SQ-HDM, Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus and Dermatophagoides farinae 50%/50%; ALK-Abell&#x000f3;, H&#x000f8;rsholm, Denmark) for a planned 3&#x02009;years. A 35-year-old male with known allergic rhinitis due to HDM (Dermatophagoides pteronyssinus specific IgE 11&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>3</sup> IU/L), diagnosed using a radioallergosorbent test, received the first tablet (ACARIZAX 12 SQ-HDM) at an outpatient facility. The dose was held sublingually for 1&#x02009;min before any swallowing was permitted. The treatment was performed in the morning. During the first few minutes, only discrete oropharyngeal itching was present. After 30&#x02009;min, the itching had subsided. However, 1&#x02009;h post treatment, a debilitating right-sided, high-frequent, subjective buzzing noise with constant intensity started. The sound was independent of position of the head. There was no concomitant hearing loss. No exposure to loud, high noises was reported, and there was no history of use of portable music devices. The patient had not suffered from any recent respiratory tract infections, taken any concomitant medication, or experienced any head and neck traumas. A case-note review showed no preceding episodes of tinnitus, problems with the ears, or hearing loss. There were no psychiatric disorders or stress-related complaints. Furthermore, no temporomandibular joint problems were present. The patient had an examination at the Department of Ear, Nose, and Throat after symptom duration of 24&#x02009;h, but no pathology was revealed. Hence, no obvious reason for the symptoms was found. The dosage regimen was upheld at one tablet a day during the period of tinnitus, and after 48&#x02009;h, the buzzing sound spontaneously disappeared. At 6&#x02009;months, no further episodes of tinnitus have been reported, and the SLIT therapy continues with good effect at recommended dosage regimen at one tablet a day. A review of his prescriptions showed great compliance to SLIT.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section6-2050313X17713150"><title>Discussion</title><p>Tinnitus is the debilitating subjective sensation of sound in the absence of actual acoustical stimulation.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> It can affect one or both ears and may be permanent, intermittent, or transient. Since otological conditions, particularly hearing loss, represent one of the most frequent causes of tinnitus, the auditory phantom sensations are often thought to be neuroplastic responses to sensory deprivation. The pathophysiology of tinnitus is intricate and not simply a correlate of the disproportion of firing patterns across the tonotopic pattern of the damaged cochlea, because the sound perception can persist even when input is eradicated by denervation of the auditory nerve. Although cochlear abnormalities could be the initial source of tinnitus, the subsequent neural changes centrally in auditory system is more likely to sustain the condition.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>Common causes of intermittent tinnitus include infection, for example, otitis media and mastoiditis, whereas sensorineural causes, for example, hearing loss, presbycusis, and noise exposure, are believed to be permanent in their nature. Furthermore, M&#x000e9;ni&#x000e8;re&#x02019;s disease and vestibular vertigo may also cause intermittent tinnitus. Mechanical causes like impacted cerumen, temporomandibular joint disorder, or otosclerosis are common; however, the latter is a permanent condition. Neurological diseases, such as migraine, multiple sclerosis, and epilepsy, may also play a prominent role in the cause of tinnitus, although only migraine is of intermittent character. Cardiovascular diseases, such as hypertension, could cause tinnitus, yet again, this would be permanent or at least long-standing until appropriate treatment is administered. Moreover, psychiatric disorders, for example, anxiety, depression, or emotional trauma, are often a cause of intermittent tinnitus. Analgesics, antibiotics, antineoplastic drugs, corticosteroids, diuretics, immunosuppressive drugs, and non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs may cause pharmacologically induced tinnitus.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-2050313X17713150" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> A short escalation in dose could potentially circumvent the initial side effects; ACARIZAX is, however, only available in 12 SQ-HDM, but other SLIT products are also available. Taken together, the pathophysiological mechanisms of monosymptomatic transient tinnitus induced by SLIT with HDM allergen remain unknown, as none of the enumerated causes fit the current case. Mechanical distortion of the inner ear due to mild swelling of the mucosal membrane may provide a theoretical explanation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section7-2050313X17713150"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The details of this case provide important insights for clinical practice, as tinnitus has not been previously reported as a side effect of SLIT with HDM allergens. Although side effects may occur, SLIT remains efficacious and safe. Informing patients receiving SLIT remains an important component of prescribing SLIT and should include information regarding risks of both local and systemic side effects including transient tinnitus.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of conflicting interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethical approval:</bold> Our institution does not require ethical approval for reporting individual cases or case series.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Informed consent:</bold> Written informed consent was obtained from the patient(s) for their anonymized information to be published in this article.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2050313X17713150"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scadding</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brostoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Low dose sublingual therapy in patients with allergic rhinitis due to house dust mite</article-title>. <source>Clin Allergy</source>
<year>1986</year>; <volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>483</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3536171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2050313X17713150"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Larenas Linnemann</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sublingual immunotherapy: a comprehensive review</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>117</volume>(<issue>5</issue>): <fpage>1021</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1035</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16675328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2050313X17713150"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Compalati</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Passalacqua</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The efficacy of sublingual immunotherapy for house dust mites respiratory allergy: results of a GA2LEN meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Allergy</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>64</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>1570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19796205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2050313X17713150"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Klimek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Sublingual Immunotherapy Dosing Regimens: what is ideal?</article-title>
<source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28065336</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2050313X17713150"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Dyken</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical case of anaphylaxis with sublingual immunotherapy: house dust mite allergen</article-title>. <source>J Allergy Clin Immunol Pract</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>2</volume>(<issue>4</issue>): <fpage>485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>486</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25017545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2050313X17713150"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baguley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McFerran</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tinnitus</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>382</volume>(<issue>9904</issue>): <fpage>1600</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1607</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23827090</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2050313X17713150"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis and management of somatosensory tinnitus: review article</article-title>. <source>Clinics</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>66</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>1089</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1094</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21808880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2050313X17713150"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cianfrone</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pentangelo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianfrone</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pharmacological drugs inducing ototoxicity, vestibular symptoms and tinnitus: a reasoned and updated guide</article-title>. <source>Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>15</volume>(<issue>6</issue>): <fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>636</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21796866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>