<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Clin Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Elmer Press</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Clinical Medicine Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1918-3003</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1918-3011</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elmer Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3194009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22121397</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4021/jocmr581w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dubowitz Syndrome: A Review and Implications for Cognitive, Behavioral, and Psychological Features</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Dubowitz Syndrome</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>Rebekah S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aa">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Houlihan</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ab">b</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="CORc">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Filter</surname><given-names>Kevin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Ab">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="Aa"><label>a</label>University of Utah, SLC, USA</aff><aff id="Ab"><label>b</label>Minnesota State University, Mankato, USA
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CORc"><label>c</label>Corresponding author: Daniel Houlihan. Email: <email>daniel.houlihan@mnsu.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2011, Huber et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Dubowitz syndrome is a rare autosomal recessive disorder characterized by micorcephaly, short stature, abnormal faces, and mild to severe mental retardation. Growth retardation occurs both intrauterine and postnatal. Behavioral characteristics include hyperactivity, short attention span, and aggressiveness. Behavior problems include difficulty feeding, sleep disturbance, and bedwetting. Individuals with the disorder have displayed shyness, fear of crowds, and dislike of loud noises. A high-pitched or hoarse voice is common. Deficits have been found in speech and language skills, reasoning and memory skills, self-help skills, and psychomotor functioning. Ocular, dental, cutaneous, skeletal, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal, neurological, immunological, and hematological medical difficulties have been noted. Approximately 148 cases have been described in the literature. The cause of the disorder remains unknown, however, research suggests genetic origin. Past research emphasizes physical characteristics and medical complications. There is a lack of cognitive, behavioral, and psychological information available regarding the disorder. This article presents a review of the literature and provides assessment and treatment implications for the cognitive, behavioral, and psychological aspects of Dubowitz syndrome.</p><sec id="a1"><title>Keywords</title><p>Dubowitz; Syndrome; Autosomal; Recessive</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Dubowitz syndrome is a rare autosomal recessive disorder that was first identified in children over 40 years ago. Less than 200 cases have been documented in the literature. It is marked by growth retardation, microcephaly, short stature, characteristic facial features, skin eruptions, and mild to severe mental retardation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Children with the disorder also display similar behavioral characteristics. Hyperactivity and short attention span [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>], impulsivity and aggressiveness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>], shyness and a dislike of crowds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], refusal of food and bedwetting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>] have all been reported. Certain medical problems are associated with the condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6-10</xref>]. Dubowitz syndrome commonly leads to decreased motor and language functioning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], developmental delay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>], and an increased risk for a shorter life span [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>].</p><p>The disorder was first discovered in a female child in 1965 by Victor Dubowitz. He described the disorder and proposed it was a phenotype of Boone&#x02019;s syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. The syndrome was later identified and named by Grosse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>] and Opitz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. The cause of Dubowitz syndrome remains unknown, however, literature points to genetics and chromosomal instability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. Sporadic cases suggest growth hormone deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>] or defects in the cholesterol biosynthetic pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>] as the source of the disorder. Due to its rarity, most reports discussed in the literature are case studies that emphasize specific physical anomalies and new medical findings.</p><p>Emphasis has been given to physical and medical phenomenology of the disorder, but there is a lack of thorough examination of cognitive, behavioral, and psychological aspects. To date, only one publication has focused specifically on the psychological status of individuals with Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. The study reported on intellectual functioning, language and fine motor developmental delays in ten cases. Parent report addressed adaptive functioning and behavioral deficits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. However, this research was conducted more than two decades ago and failed to objectively evaluate individuals&#x02019; behavioral characteristics and adaptability. There is a need in the literature to measure these features to provide a complete illustration of the disorder and how it affects children. The literature also fails to discuss management of these attributes. This paper thoroughly reviews 148 cases of Dubowitz syndrome and provides assessment and treatment implications for cognitive, behavioral, and psychological functioning.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Description of Disorder</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Phenomenology</title><sec id="s2a1"><title>Facial characteristics</title><p>Individuals with Dubowitz syndrome have distinct facial characteristics which distinguish it from other disorders with similar symptomology. Distinctive abnormalities with the shape of the face, eyes, ears, nose, and mouth are common. The face is narrow or triangular shaped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] with a sloping forehead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. The supraorbital ridge is shallow and even with the face [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Micrognathia, a receding chin that results in an underbite, was present in 85 of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16-19</xref>]. The hair and the eyebrows are thin and sparse [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Facial asymmetry or abnormal neck has been reported, but occurs in less than ten percent of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. The ears vary in size, but are usually more prominently positioned. Ears are low set [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] and can be posteriorly angulated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. In 41 cases, dysplastic (poorly-formed) ears exist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Otis media (inflammation of the middle ear) is often severe and can require the insertion of tubes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. A broad or flat nasal bridge is common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], and some cases document a prominent round tip of the nose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>].</p><p>Several malformations are associated with the eyes. Drooping of the upper eyelid was observed in the majority of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Epicanthal folds are excessive and cover the inner corner of the eye [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Twenty five percent of the cases report abnormal palperbral fissures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>] (narrow longitudinal opening above the eyelids). Fifteen percent noted telecanthus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>] (increased distance between the inside corner of the eye to the nose) or hypertelorism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. Investigation of the size and functioning of the eyes has also revealed irregularities. Unnatural smallness of the eyes has been mentioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Microphthalmia (large eyes in comparison to the face) were noted in one case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Megalocornea (enlarged rear segment of the eye) is rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Strabismis and estropia exist but have been less mentioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Visual problems such as farsightedness (hyperopia), cataracts, and primary pigmentary degeneration of the retina (tapetoretinal degeneration) have also been found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Iris coloboma, (some structure of the eye is absent) iris hypoplasia, (underdevelopment of the iris), nystagmus, anisocoria, paresis, and astigmatism were noted in less than 5 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Strabismus is an anomaly in which the eyes are not aligned with each other under normal conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. Children who experience strabismus can also experience diplopia (double vision) and problems with depth perception due to the misalignment of the eyes. Often, one of the images is suppressed by the brain in order to compensate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>].</p><p>A large mouth is rare, but was observed in some cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Studies have shown multiple abnormalities with the palate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. The palate has been found to be unusually narrow and high arched [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Other oral abnormalities include cleft palate, submucous cleft palate, and cleft uvula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Velopharngeal insufficiency results in failure of the soft palate to reach the rear pharyngeal wall which can cause high pitched or hoarse speech [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Dental manifestations include crowded, missing, irregular, or rotated teeth. In children with Dubowitz syndrome, delayed eruption of teeth has been more commonly documented [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title>Growth retardation</title><p>Growth retardation occurs both pre and post birth. In 14 cases, it was found only after birth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. One of the most distinct features is the small size of the body and the head. Microcephaly, short stature, and low weight is common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16-19</xref>]. In 141 cases, the average circumference of the head at birth was 31.0 cm and the weight ranged from 900 to 3,600 g [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Short stature is not as common as low weight. In 56 percent of cases, intrauterine growth retardation (birth weight less than 2,500 g at full term) was noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Physical development is often months to years behind the actual age of the child [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Growth charts of 5 cases presented by Orrison and colleagues illustrate growth retardation in all cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. At birth, only one child was 3 standard deviations below normal birth weight. When measured months later, 4 children were below the 3rd standard deviation and one was below the second standard deviation of weight for their age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>].</p><p>Retarded bone maturation can result in decreased tone of the skeletal muscle, characterized by weakness and floppiness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] (hypotonia). Retarded bone maturation was found in over 25% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. In a few individuals, the joints were hyper extensible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Other anomalies include scoliosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>], missing or underdeveloped ribs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], and fused vertebra [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. One patient presented skeletal abnormalities similar to his brother who was diagnosed with Klippel Feil syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>]. The hands and feet are not apart from physical deformities. Problems with the feet include flat footedness, club foot, dorsiflexion, plantar flexion, abducted and inverted foot, or various combinations in which the foot is twisted out of shape or position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. More common anomalies include fifth finger clinodactyly, which is permanent bending of the &#x0201c;baby&#x0201d; finger, and syndactyly, which the 2nd or 3rd fingers or toes have fusion or webbing together with skin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Two cases found children with abducted thumbs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>].</p><p>Dubowitz syndrome has been associated with genital and rectal abnormalities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Cryptorchidism, the condition when one or both testes fails to descend, was found in 27 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Hypospadias, abnormal development of the urethra, was found in 10 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. In males, the urethra opens on the bottom surface of the penis or in the perineum. In females, the urethra opens into the vagina. Genital anomalies in females were found in 23 cases, which included hypospadias or hypoplastic genitalia. This includes an underdeveloped clitoris, labia, or vagina [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Chronic diarrhea and constipation have been found in 16% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Illynia and Lurie first noted rectal malformations in patients with Dubowitz syndrome in 1990. Anal stenosis and constipation were discovered in children from 3 different families [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Less common anal and rectal difficulties consist of rectal prolapse, anal stenosis, congenital constipation, inguinal and hatial hernia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2a3"><title>Cognition</title><p>Dubowitz syndrome has shown a deficiency in cognition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Mild to moderate mental retardation is common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Severe mental retardation is rare, but has been found in 7% of the cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Some cases reported that children with cognitive deficits attended special education classes or special schools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Normal intelligence also exists in children with the syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Children with Dubowitz syndrome have also shown a short attention span [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] and preference for concrete thinking [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. In the evaluation of ten cases, Parrish and Wilroy indentified deficits in reasoning and memory, and severe delays with expressive and receptive vocabulary [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Difficulties specific to individual cases included problems with spatial perception, numerical abilities, spelling, abstract reasoning, visual motor coordination, and fine motor development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. In the study, many parents also reported that their children were months to years behind other children with regard to self-help skills [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. A few children required assistance with dressing, eating, and toileting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2a4"><title>Behavioral characteristics</title><p>There are many behavioral characteristics associated with Dubowitz syndrome that have been reported throughout the literature. These are known to affect speech, temperament, and overall behavior. In the majority of patients, there are problems related to language development and speech [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. A high pitched voice, which is common to the disorder was found in 39 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5-7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. High pitched or hoarse voice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>] can be characterized as a voice disorder. Voice disorders are often accompanied by problems with articulation or speech delay which form a complex communication disorder. Development of speech was delayed in 20% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. It is important to correctly identify any communication difficulties and get treatment started as soon as possible to prevent other learning or developmental problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>].</p><p>In 53 cases, children exhibited behavior problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>]. Hyperactivity was found in the 34% of the total cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Tsukahara and colleagues mentioned that hyperactivity was &#x0201c;very difficult to manage and in some cases interferes with sleep&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Hyperactivity can exacerbate impulsiveness, problem behaviors, and learning deficits. Frequent outbursts are not uncommon in these children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Less reported behavior problems include irritability, agitation, moodiness, carelessness, poor compliance, and frequent tempertantrums [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].</p><p>Another behavioral factor that appears to be affected by Dubowitz syndrome is temperament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Although it is somewhat uncommon, children have shown a tendency to withdrawal from others or experience shyness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Other individuals dislike large crowds or have a fear of public places [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Individuals with a range of mental abilities prefer to avoid crowds and public places [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. It has not been distinguished if individuals simply have an aversion to these places or if they are uncomfortable with their physical appearance and consequently avoid public. Children with hyperactivity and impulsivity may also experience anxious [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>] or aggressive temperament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. Irritable, whiny, and attention seeking has been found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>]. Understanding the temperament of the individual can also help direct treatment and set up an educational program that is appropriate for the child [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>].</p><p>Difficulty feeding has been found in 31 cases of children with Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. These difficulties are sometimes discovered immediately after birth and include food refusal, vomiting, and regurgitation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. Some cases with difficulty feeding have found to be associated with medical concerns of the gastrointestinal system or the esophagus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>]. On the other hand, lack of eating has been associated with failure to thrive or anorexic-like tendencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>].</p><p>Failure to thrive is associated with a child&#x02019;s inability to gain weight, grow or feed normally [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Several causes have been hypothesized for the disorder of failure to thrive. One relates low birth weight with the mother&#x02019;s nourishment during intrauterine development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Another theory proposes that children do not receive effective reinforcement from parents when the feeding behavior occurs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Study of the feeding behaviors of a child diagnosed exclusively with failure to thrive were assessed by Casey and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Via descriptive analysis, researchers identified schedules of reinforcement by the child&#x02019;s parents. When the child refused food and the parents removed the food, it resulted in negative reinforcement. The study implemented a behavioral intervention to address feeding behaviors with the child and schedules of reinforcement with the parents. When refusal of food became extinct in the study, normal feeding behaviors that resulted in weight gain and growth persisted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>].</p><p>Less common behavior characteristics include a preference for vibrations and musical beat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Children sit close to speakers to enjoy vibrations from playing music [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Other fascinations include watching ceiling fans or rolling credits on television, and engaging in repetitious phrases and behaviors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Bouncing, dancing, twirling of the hair, and giggling have all been found to be repetitious, excessive, and often inappropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. When parents reported on their children&#x02019;s behavior, a few children displayed sensitivity to criticism, were &#x0201c;picky eaters&#x0201d;, or wet the bed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2a5"><title>Medical difficulties</title><p>Case studies of patients with Dubowitz syndrome have shown various medical phenomena. Medical problems with the skin, esophagus, gastrointestinal system, cardiovascular system, immune system, and neurological problems have all been established [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4-9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. Although they don&#x02019;t appear regularly, they still have shown to exist in cases and are associated with the disorder.</p><p>Complications with the integumentary system are common in individuals with this disorder. Fifty-nine patients reported a cutaneous abnormality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. Since the disorder was first discovered, eczema has been considered to be a characteristic feature, however, it has been vaguely described in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Eczema is a type of dermatitis that causes acute or chronic noncontiguous inflammation of the skin. It is characterized chiefly by redness, itching, and the outbreak of lesions that may discharge serous matter and become encrusted and scaly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. A small amount of cases examined various skin problems in depth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. One case study found scaly skin dermatitis in a young boy and made a diagnosis of ichthyosiform eruption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. He responded well to a treatment with daily topical application of 10% urea-containing ointment. Fifty percent of individuals reported to have eczematous lesions did not respond to the typical treatment of topical corticosteroids with success [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Kato and colleges suggested an incorrect diagnosis of eczema in many of these cases. They implied that some lesions may a result of ichthyosiform eruption [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26">26</xref>]. Although rare, keliodal lesions have also been reported in a few cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>].</p><p>Problems with the esophagus and gastrointestinal system are often related to feeding problems. Irregularities found in the literature include gastroesophageal reflux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>] (return of the stomach contents back up into the esophagus), and achalasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R09">9</xref>] (narrowing of the esophagus). Vomiting and regurgitation result with both. Vomiting occurred with 24 of the cases in which 5 of the cases involved gastroesophageal reflux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. There is still much information needed to understand the cause of feeding problems and the association to the esophagus and gastrointestinal system.</p><p>Medical concerns with the hematology, immunology, and malignancies include aplastic anemia, actute lymphatic leukemia, malignant lymphoma, germinal blastic sarcoma, neuroblastoma, pancytopenia, embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma, hypogammaglobulinmia, hypoplastic anemia, and bone marrow hypoplasia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4-6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>]. These have occurred very rarely in cases with Dubowitz syndrome. However, with the majority of the anomalies, there is great risk for a fatal outcome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Aplastic anemia results when bone marrow causes sufficient red and white blood cell production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">6</xref>]. Acute lymphatic leukemia is a rapidly progressing cancer of the blood that affects white blood cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Lymphoma is malignant tumor of the lymph glands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Neuroblastoma is a malignant tumor derived from primitive ganglion cells that most commonly appear on the adrenal glands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Hypogammaglobulinmia is a condition where the immunoglobulin level is depressed below the normal range. In many of these cases, chromosomal instability and breakage was described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. Frequent infections, allergies, and asthma are associated with Dubowitz syndrome. Infections appear in the ears, sinuses, gastrointestinal system, respiratory system, and urinary tract [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>].</p><p>Other reported medical complications consist of cardiovascular abnormalities, neurological problems, and migraine headaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Congenital heart defects have been found in 13 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. The defects included ventricular septal defect, heat murmurs, atrial septal defect, mitral valve prolapse, and coarctation of the aorta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. Many of these abnormalities required surgical attention. Neurological difficulties were found in 17% of the cases. Seizures with abnormal and normal EEG findings, migraine headaches, and paralysis of the limbs, anus and bladder have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Abnormalities in the brain have also been discovered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>]. These included decreased density in the frontal region of the brain and abnormal ventricles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Diagnosis</title><p>Diagnosis for Dubowitz syndrome is based primarily on inspection of facial appearance, growth records, and previous medical history [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. It is difficult to diagnosis, as some of the characteristic facial features are not always prominent or similar in each case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. A medical doctor can make a diagnosis of the disorder, however, there are a few doctors that are considered to be experts at diagnosing Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>]. Diagnosis by these experts is not required, however, these doctors have familiarity with the features and have often made more than one diagnosis. Consulting a physician that has had previous experience with the disorder is recommended if symptoms are variable and do not fit the common features of the disorder. At this time, the karotype is normal, so diagnosis is done primarily through observation methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Patients with Dubowitz syndrome are often evaluated by several different specialists for associated medical problems and abnormalities with eyes, ears, teeth, skin, and skeletal system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].</p><sec id="s2b1"><title>Age</title><p>Diagnosis can occur at any age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Diagnosis is more common during early childhood due to the associated features and medical problems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. It has also been diagnosed in adolescence and adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Some infants have been diagnosed with the disorder due to low birth size and weight, microcephaly, and recurrent need of medical assistance following birth due to medical difficulties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. It is common that undiagnosed patients present with other medical problems and upon examination, Dubowitz syndrome is diagnosed.</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>Differential diagnosis</title><p>Dubowitz syndrome can easily be confused with other disorders. It has frequently been mistaken for Bloom syndrome, Fanconi anemia, and fetal alcohol syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Dubowitz syndrome shares similar symptoms of mental retardation, skin lesions, and growth retardation. Fanconi anemia and Dubowitz syndrome share problems with chromosomal instability and the hematological and immune systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. However, Bloom syndrome and Fanconi anemia do not share the facial characteristics of Dubowitz syndrome and therefore can be easily distinguished [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. On the other hand, fetal alcohol syndrome has similar facial abnormalities, hyperactivity, growth retardation, varying degrees of mental retardation, and microcephaly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Fetal alcohol syndrome requires intrauterine exposure to alcohol which separates it from Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>]. Dubowitz syndrome and fetal alcohol can also be differentiated by evaluating clinical manifestations, as they are different in each disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Prevalence</title><sec id="s2c1"><title>Gender</title><p>Dubowitz syndrome is present equally in males and females. Of the 148 cases reported, 66 were female and 73 were male [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16-19</xref>]. The literature failed to report the gender of nine cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s2c2"><title>Race and location of origin</title><p>The disorder has been found in diverse groups worldwide. Sixty-nine percent of the cases have been reported in the United States, Russia, and Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Cases have also been found in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16">16</xref>], Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>], Turkey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17">17</xref>], Hong Kong [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>], France, Italy, Mexico, Canada, England, Poland, Venezuela, Israel, Hungary, Croatia, Netherlands, Brazil, and Poland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. The disorder does not appear to be specific to any particular race or region.</p></sec><sec id="s2c3"><title>Family</title><p>Dubowitz syndrome has shown to exist within other members of the family. Nine cases of family occurrence are reported in the literature. The disorder has occurred in siblings and twins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25">25</xref>] Dubowitzs original findings describe the disorder in three sisters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>]. Tsukahara and Opitz discovered Dubowitz syndrome in only one of two twins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. One case reported of the diagnosis within an aunt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10">10</xref>] and another case described a mother with similar features of the disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Etiology</title><p>The cause of Dubowitz syndrome remains unknown. Due to familial occurrence, it is believed to have genetic origins. Direct consanguinity was found in three cases involving parents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>] and one case involving first cousins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. Hormone deficiency has been found sporadically throughout the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. Three cases showed success with growth hormone treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>]. Other cases have reported hyperthirodism, iron deficiency, and cholesterol deficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15">15</xref>]. Chromosomal instability and breakage has been examined in detail in a few cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13">13</xref>]. However, Tsukahara and Opitz assert that metabolic and DNA repair defects must be ruled out as the cause [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Instead, they suggest that mosaic pleiotropy, which is intrcellular action of the muntant genotype during various periods of pre and post natal development. Their reasoning is based on the broad variability of phenotype that there must be action of many modifying genetic or epigenetic factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. This however, fails to account for the fact that the phenotype is similar among siblings with Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. Recent research declares that Dubowitz syndrome is a microdeletion and a microduplication syndrome rather than an autosomal disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23">23</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Behavioral Assessment/Conceptualization</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Cognitive functioning</title><p>Due to the severe physical and medical effects the disorder has on an individual, it is necessary to assess all physical aspects and medical concerns during examination. Past research has shown the benefits of examining different characteristics such as the skin, immune system, brain structure, lymphatic functioning and hormones, skeletal, ocular, dental, and ears. It is equally important to assess the cognitive functioning of individuals. Assessment and diagnosis of cognitive deficits can guide treatment and individualized education plans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27">27</xref>]. Much of the literatures discusse the cognitive and behavioral aspects of each case, however, there is not a great deal of information regarding assessment in the majority of individuals described with cognitive problems.</p><p>Few studies have used cognitive and developmental assessments to tap into the functioning of children with Dubowitz syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. The Thermann-Merrill was used to asses IQ in one case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22">22</xref>]. Five cases assessed personal, social, fine motor, adaptive, language, and gross motor development with the Denver Developmental Screening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21">21</xref>]. In Parrish and Wilroy&#x02019;s psychological analysis of ten children, the measures used included the Cattell Infant Intelligence Test, Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scale, Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children-Revised, Vineland Social Maturity Scale, Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test-Form A, Bender Gestalt Test, Goodenough Draw-A-Man Test, and Wide Range Achievement Test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>]. Sunku and colleagues reported results of one of childs performance on the Wechsler Intelligence Scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>].</p><p>Information is missing from the literature about how cognitive functioning was assessed in many individuals diagnosed with mental retardation. Lack of proper cognitive assessment may be inferred in some of the cases that present mental retardation in Dubowitz syndrome. In the majority of the existing cases with a diagnosis of severely mentally retarded, the literature described developmental and speech delays. However, no assessment was mentioned. This suggests that the child was not tested, but rather assumed to have severe mental retardation based on the inability to talk, walk, or perform specific tasks.</p><p>When assessing cognitive abilities, it is essential to use a valid measure that generates an IQ score and level of performance. Suggested assessments that can achieve this task include the Wechsler Intelligence Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30-32</xref>], Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scale: 4th Edition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>], Bayley Scales of Infant Development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>], and the Test of Nonverbal Intelligence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>]. Individual functioning and academic achievement can be measured on the Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children 4th Edition (WISC-IV) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>] and the Wechsler Individual Achievement Test 2nd Edition (WIAT-II) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>]. For youth ages 6 to16, the WISC-IV is used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30">30</xref>]. The Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence (WPPSI-III) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32">32</xref>] is used for children ages 2 7 years, 3 moths. The Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scale: 4th Edition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>] has also been used to properly assess intelligence and provide an IQ score for individuals ages 2 up. For some children, it may not be practical to administer the Wechsler or Stanford-Binet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33">33</xref>]. There is no single assessment that is appropriate for all individuals. The Bayley Scales of Infant Development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R34">34</xref>] and the Test of Nonverbal Intelligence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35">35</xref>] can be utilized instead.</p><p>A measure of development and performance in various areas would also be essential. This could be accomplished with the Denver Developmental Screening: Revised [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36">36</xref>]. Additionally, many individuals diagnosed with mental retardation were in their early years of childhood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>]. It would be important to have an initial measurement of cognitive ability and continue to reassess the IQ, development, and performance of each child. This longitudinal measurement could show change over time and help identify needs for treatment and special educational programs.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Maladaptive behavior</title><p>Behavior of children with Dubowitz syndrome also needs to be assessed. Children have displayed hyperactivity, aggressiveness, difficulty concentrating, behavior problems, sleep disturbance, and feeding problems. The literature fails to discuss an assessment strategy for these individuals. Suggestions for assessment include behavioral observation, functional assessment, behavioral checklists, the Differential Ability Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>], and the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38">38</xref>].</p><p>Many of the associated behavioral characteristics such as behavior problems, hyperactivity, aggressiveness, sleeping and feeding difficulties can all be examined through the use of behavioral observation or functional assessment. Functional assessment would provide more information about the antecedents and consequences of the behavior and can guide treatment. Behavioral observation can assess psychomotor retardation. Behavioral checklists such as the Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales could be given to a parent to complete. It is not suggested that behavioral checklists are administered alone. They need to be supplemented with an objective measure. Functional assessment and observation is one way that this can be accomplished and can be applied to a variety of settings and behaviors. A multifaceted approach to behavioral assessment is recommended, and can be accomplished by incorporating different methods of measurement.</p><p>Dubowitz syndrome and attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) have common symptoms of hyperactivity, aggressiveness, irritability, and the inability to concentrate. Due to the overlap of the symptomology, it is important to consider ADHD as a possible diagnosis and to use the proper tools for assessment. The Differential Ability Scales [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R37">37</xref>] have shown validity in assessment for ADHD. Accurate diagnosis of ADHD would be essential to developing a treatment and educational plan for the individual.</p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Speech and language</title><p>It is necessary to assess speech functioning to check for social skills deficits in children with Dubowitz syndrome. One case showed that a patient was very outgoing, friendly, attentive, and talkative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18">18</xref>]. Other cases have shown patients to be withdrawn and shy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. The range of cognitive abilities, temperament and social skills illustrate the need for further assessment. Speech and language assessment can be measured by the Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test-3rd edition (PPVT-III) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R39">39</xref>], Assessment of Child Language Comprehension (ACLC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40">40</xref>], and Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals-Revised (CELF-R) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41">41</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Treatment</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Medical</title><p>Various treatments have been used with different medication conditions associated with Dubowitz syndrome. The majority of treatments consist of surgery or medication. Surgery has been done on the face, hands, and feet to correct abnormal features. The skeletal, gastrointestinal, ocular, dental, and cardiovascular systems have also been treated with surgery.</p><p>Aphakic extended-wear contact lenses were used to treat a boy with nuclear cataracts and strabismus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20">20</xref>]. In other cases, surgical removal of cataracts and cosmetic strabismus surgery can help restore comfortable, normal, clear vision that also provides an aesthetically pleasing result. Despite the benefits of cosmetic strabismus surgery, common side effects include persistent diplopia.</p><p>Other interventions consist of medications, blood transfusions, growth hormones treatments, and transplants. Treatment for aplastic anemia has shown to be most effective with a bone marrow transplant. However, a donor is not always available, so although it has been found to be extremely effective, it is not the most common form of treatment. A blood transfusion might also be beneficial, especially if there are no other treatment options. One case of a young girl was fatal due to aplastic anemia. Her parents denied treatment due to religious convictions and she died three months later as a result of the medical condition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Cognitive and language treatment</title><p>Children with cognitive difficulties can attend special education classes or specialized schools to assist with their learning disabilities. An individual education plan can be developed for each child which emphasizes areas of deficits and needs. By following this educational plan, parents and teachers can help advance a child&#x02019;s abilities while accentuating strengths. Speech therapy can be utilized to develop language deficits. It can also help children learn how to annunciate and articulate words. Due to the abnormities experienced orally with the palate, instruction of tongue placement and voice projection would be beneficial. It will also be necessary to treat social skill deficits and expand self-help skills for individuals with Dubowitz syndrome. Social skills and self-help skills can be taught through roll play, social play, or reinforcement schedules.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Behavioral interventions and management</title><p>There are many behavioral treatments that can be applied to the associated features of the disorder. After thorough assessment, treatment can be implemented for behavior problems, hyperactivity, feeding difficulties, sleep disturbance, and dislike/fear of public places. Differential reinforcement is can be used as an effective treatment with many of the associated behaviors. It is defined by contingent and appropriate reinforcement based of the desired response and ignoring or not acknowledging the target behavior.</p><p>Although medication has proven to be successful with ADHD, behavioral treatments have also shown to be efficacious. Behavioral treatment recommended for hyperactivity, short attention span and behavior problems includes differential reinforcement. Feeding problems associated with Failure to Thrive can also employ differential reinforcement after a thorough functional assessment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29">29</xref>]. Differential reinforcement can increase parental reinforcement and feeding abilities such as bite-acceptance.</p><p>Sleep disturbance is often due to physical anomalies and medical conditions, however sleeping difficulties have also been attributed to hyperactivity and behavior problems. It is necessary to carry out a functional assessment in order to determine the underlying cause of sleep disruption. If sleep disturbance is not due to physical or medical manifestations, then a behavioral treatment can be implemented. A behavioral treatment can decrease sleep disturbance and help a child sleep thru the night. Use of differential reinforcement or a token system can encourage more sleep and decrease restfulness. Keeping a sleep log and recording sleep latency, duration, waking episodes and behaviors that accompany them.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Empirical Status/Outcome Research</title><p>There is a lack of information on the long-term outcome of the disorder, associated medical problems, and adult level of functioning. Few cases have been studied longitudinally, and the outcomes of the disorder vary for each individual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. Individual outcomes appear to be related to the primary physical, medical, cognitive, and psychological manifestations of the disorder, how they progressed over time, treatment, and the individuals adaptability.</p><p>A longitudinal study of the first child diagnosed with Dubowitz syndrome describes childhood, adolescence, and adulthood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>]. The female in the study had mild mental retardation and completed high school in special education classes. She had undergone multiple surgeries, including plastic surgery to her face. She had experienced abnormal menstruation at age 13. At age 22, she endured two seizures for which she was prescribed phenobarbital for two years with no later recurrence. As a child, she had severe eczema that caused sleep disturbance. By adulthood, her eczema had subsided and she was able to sleep through the night. She appeared young for her age and had high tolerance to pain. At the time of evaluation, she was living independently and working full-time in a sheltered workshop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Implications for Future Research</title><p>Future study of children with Dubowitz syndrome should include cognitive, behavioral, and psychological evaluation. Focus should be given to assessment of these features, which can provide specific information to direct treatment, as well build on the current knowledge-base of the disorder. Behavioral interventions that address associated characteristics should be prominent in future research. More research is needed concerning the long-term functioning and adaptability of these individuals. Children with the disorder appear and function differently from peers. It would be essential to evaluate the affects of the disorder on an individuals self-esteem, social, and relational aspects. Much research is needed in regard to the cognitive, behavioral, and psychological status of children with Dubowitz syndrome.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Summary/Conclusion</title><p> Dubowitz Syndrome is a rare childhood disorder. It has shown to affect individuals physically, medically, cognitively, behaviorally, and psychologically. The serious medical and physical manifestations of the disorder highlight a need for further evaluation of cognitive, behavioral, and psychological aspects of children with Dubowitz syndrome. Review of the literature revealed a lack of thorough evaluation regarding these features. Previous reports provide a record of associated characteristics, but fail to mention assessment and treatment options for behavioral and psychological findings. This paper suggests various assessment and treatment implications concerning cognitive, behavioral, and psychological symptomology. Much research is needed to advance the current knowledge of the disorder and to improve the quality of care for individuals with Dubowitz syndrome.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R01"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dubowitz</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Familial Low Birthweight Dwarfism with an Unusual Facies and a Skin Eruption</article-title><source>J Med Genet</source><year>1965</year><volume>42</volume><issue>12-17</issue><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14296916</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R02"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Opitz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>The Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Z Kinderheilkd</source><year>1971</year><volume>110</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5088752</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R03"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilroy</surname><given-names>RS</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><article-title>The Dubowitz syndrome: the psychological status of ten cases at follow-up</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1980</year><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7190357</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R04"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Berthold</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Fatal aplastic anaemia in a child with features of Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Eur J Pediatr</source><year>1987</year><volume>146</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3428295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R05"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tsukahara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Opitz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: review of 141 cases including 36 previously unreported patients</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>63</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8723121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R06"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Desposito</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Aplastic anemia in Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>J Pediatr</source><year>1985</year><volume>106</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>623</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4038999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R07"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Paradisi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mostaccioli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cianchini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Atzori</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Puddu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome with keloidal lesions</article-title><source>Clin Exp Dermatol</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>425</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7955507</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R08"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sunku</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><article-title>Epileptic seizures, EEG abnormalities, and neuronal heterotopia in the Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Am J</source><year>1998</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R09"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nowicki</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome and achalasia: two rare conditions in a child</article-title><source>Clin Pediatr</source><year>1998</year><volume>37</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9545609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Swartz</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Resnick</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Iskandar</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wargowski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockmeyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Opitz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><article-title>Craniocervical anomalies in Dubowitz syndrome. Three cases and a literature review</article-title><source>Pediatr Neurosurg</source><year>2003</year><volume>38</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>238</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12686766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Opitz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pferffer</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermann</surname><given-names>JPR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushnick</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>Studies of malformation syndromes of man XXIVB: The Dubowitz syndrome. Further observations</article-title><source>Z Kinderheilk</source><year>1973</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thuret</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Philip</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hairion</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Capodano</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrimond</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Chromosomal instability in two siblings with Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Br J Haematol</source><year>1991</year><volume>78</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2043468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Nemri</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kilani</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Salih</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Ajlan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><article-title>Embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma and chromosomal breakage in a newborn infant with possible Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>2000</year><volume>92</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10797433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hirano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Growth hormone deficiency in Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Acta Paediatr Jpn; Overseas edition</source><year>1996</year><volume>38</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8741320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amalfitano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishnani</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: a defect in the cholesterol biosynthetic pathway?</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1999</year><volume>86</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takahira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondoh</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Obatake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal><article-title>Klippel-Feil anomaly in a boy and Dubowitz syndrome with vertebral fusion in his brother: a new variant of Dubowitz syndrome? Am J Med Genet</article-title><source>Part A</source><year>2005</year><volume>138A</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16152634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Oguz</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozgen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Erdem</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>Cranial midline abnormalities in Dubowitz syndrome: MR imaging findings</article-title><source>Eur Radiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1057</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12695828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: report of a case with emphasis on the oral features</article-title><source>J Dent Child</source><year>2005</year><volume>72</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16568913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Betlloch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Banuls</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>What syndrome is this? Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Pediatr Dermatol</source><year>2005</year><volume>22</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16191007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodden</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Crouch</surname><given-names>ER</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Leichtman</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><article-title>Ophthalmologic findings in the Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>J Pediatr Ophthalmol Strabismus</source><year>1999</year><volume>36</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9972513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Orrison</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Schnitzler</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><article-title>The Dubowitz syndrome: further observations</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1980</year><volume>7</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6258433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fryns</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Willemyns</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Berghe</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Brief clinical report: the Dubowitz syndrome in a teenager</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1979</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>347</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">575467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thienpont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vermeesch</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fryns</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><article-title>Facial asymmetry, cardiovascular anomalies and adducted thumbs as unusual symptoms in Dubowitz syndrome: a microdeletion/duplication in 13q</article-title><source>Genet Couns</source><year>2006</year><volume>17</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17375538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mohrenschlager</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Abeck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ring</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Atopic eczema in monozygotic twins with Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>1998</year><volume>138</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9747384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ilyina</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Lurie</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: possible evidence for a clinical subtype</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1990</year><volume>35</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2185633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Komatsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakakibara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Ichthyosiform eruption in a patient with Dubowitz syndrome</article-title><source>Pediatr Dermatol</source><year>1995</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7659638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vieluf</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Korting</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun-Falco</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>JU</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: atopic dermatitis, low birth weight dwarfism and facial dysmorphism</article-title><source>Dermatologica</source><year>1990</year><volume>180</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2358105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxova</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Dubowitz syndrome: long-term follow-up of an original patient</article-title><source>Am J Med Genet</source><year>1995</year><volume>55</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7536394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooper-Brown</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wacker</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><article-title>The use of descriptive analysis to identify and manipulate schedules of reinforcement in the treatment of food refusal</article-title><source>Journal of Behavioral Education</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children</article-title><edition>4th</edition><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>2003</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wechsler Individual Achievement Test</article-title><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>2001</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wechsler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wechsler Preschool and Primary Scale of Intelligence</article-title><edition>3rd</edition><publisher-loc>San Antonio; TX</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>2002</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thorndike</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sattler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stanford-Binet Intelligence Scale</article-title><edition>4th</edition><publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Riverside</publisher-name><year>1986</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bayley Scales of Infant Development</article-title><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-loc>San Antonio</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation: Harcourt Brace &#x00026; Company</publisher-name><year>1993</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherbenou</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnsen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Test of Nonverbal Intelligence</article-title><publisher-loc>Austin, TX</publisher-loc><publisher-name>PRO-ED</publisher-name><year>1982</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankenburg</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The DENVER II Technical Manual</article-title><publisher-loc>Denver CO</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Denver Developmental Materials Inc</publisher-name><year>1996</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elliott</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential Ability Scales: Administration and Scoring Manual</article-title><publisher-loc>San Antonio, TX</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>1990</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sparrow</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Balla</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cicchetti</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vineland Adaptive Behavior Scales</article-title><publisher-loc>Ciricle Pines, MN</publisher-loc><publisher-name>AmericanGuidance Service</publisher-name><year>1984</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test-3rd Edition</article-title><publisher-loc>Circle Pines, MN</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ACS</publisher-name><year>1997</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Giddan</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of Child Language Comprehension</article-title><publisher-loc>Palo Alto, CA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Consulting Psychologist Press</publisher-name><year>1973</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiig</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Secord</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical Evaluation of Language Fundamentals-Revised</article-title><source>Examiner's Manual</source><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Psychological Corporation</publisher-name><year>1987</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>