<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6936047</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1558</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12883-019-1558-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Ischemic stroke in Morocco: a systematic review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kharbach</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name><address><email>kharbach.a.lbrce@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Obtel</surname><given-names>Majdouline</given-names></name><address><email>majdobtel7@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lahlou</surname><given-names>Laila</given-names></name><address><email>drlailalahlou@ymail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aasfara</surname><given-names>Jehanne</given-names></name><address><email>a.jehanne@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mekaoui</surname><given-names>Nour</given-names></name><address><email>nourwen@hotmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Razine</surname><given-names>Rachid</given-names></name><address><email>razinerachid@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2168 4024</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.31143.34</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Social Medicine (Public Health, Hygiene and Preventive Medicine), Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy of Rabat, </institution><institution>Mohamed V University, </institution></institution-wrap>10100 Rabat, Morocco </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2168 4024</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.31143.34</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Biostatistics, Clinical Research and Epidemiology (LBRCE), Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy of Rabat, </institution><institution>Mohamed V University, </institution></institution-wrap>10100 Rabat, Morocco </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Neurology, International Cheikh Khalifa University Hospital, Mohammed VI University of Health Sciences (UM6SS), 82403 Casablanca, Morocco </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2156 6183</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417651.0</institution-id><institution>Faculty of Medicine and Pharmacy of Agadir, </institution><institution>Ibn Zohr University, </institution></institution-wrap>80060 Agadir, Morocco </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Pediatric medical emergencies service of the Children Hospital, 10100 Rabat, Morocco </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><elocation-id>349</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The aim of this systematic review is to determine the epidemiological and etiological profiles, the influential factors of the prehospital delay, thrombolysis management, the acute and 3-month mortality rate and the genetic aspect of ischemic stroke in Morocco.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The present work is a systematic review that was conducted according to the recommendations of the &#x0201c;Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analysis&#x0201d;. We used Pubmed, Sciencedirect, Scopus, Clinicalkey, and Google scholar databases for the raking of the gray literature during the time frame 2009 and 2018. The protocol of the review was registered in the PROSPERO register (CRD42018115206).</p><p id="Par3">These studies were analyzed based on: Age, sex ratio, risk factors, etiological profile according to Trial of ORG classification 10,172 in Acute Stroke Treatment, prehospital delay average and its influential factors, thrombolyzed patients&#x02019; proportion, acute and 3-month mortality and the genetic factors of ischemic stroke in Morocco.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par4">Twenty-nine (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;29) studies were selected. The average age ranged from 49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.2 to 67.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.9&#x02009;years old. Moreover, we reported male predominance within all ages in 13 studies. High blood pressure, diabetes, smoking and heart disease were the four identified main risk factors by the prementioned studies. Atherosclerosis and cardioembolic were the main described etiologies of cerebral ischemia, and the average prehospital time ranged from 26 to 61.9&#x02009;h. The proportion of thrombolysed patients ranged from 1.8% to 2.9%, the mortality rate varied in the acute phase from 3 to 13%, and the 3-month mortality ranged from 4.3 to 32.5%. It is also important to highlight that most of these studies, which were conducted in hospital environment, have a reduced sample size and no confidence interval.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par5">Ischemic stroke is affecting more likely the young population with male predominance. Moreover, the long prehospital delay and the low proportion of thrombolysed patients are alarming. This indicates the need to investigate in depth the key factors influencing the access to care for Moroccan patients in order to improve the management of this neurologic deficit in Morocco.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ischemic stroke</kwd><kwd>Trial of ORG classification 10,172 in acute stroke treatment classification</kwd><kwd>Prehospital delay</kwd><kwd>Thrombolysis</kwd><kwd>Morocco</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par17">Stroke has become a major public health concern and a real growing burden on African countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], regarding its cost on the social, psychological, and economic levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The incidence of stroke continues to increase in developing countries, including the North African region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">From an etiological point of view, previous studies have described multiple causes of stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. According to the epidemiological survey conducted in the two metropolitan Moroccan cities (Casablanca and Rabat), ischemic stroke (IS) represented 70.9% of all types of stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Multidisciplinary and fast approaches are highly required in term of therapeutic management since they are key determinants of the prognosis and evolution of the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In addition, a major evolution in IS care management is occurring during the last years. The two main improvements are the approval of intravenous thrombolysis and the intra-arterial mechanical thrombectomy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Stroke is thus considered as a critical challenge in terms of prevention and patients&#x02019; management in acute phase in order to improve the mortality and morbidity of this pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">In the context of low-and-middle income countries, and despite the enormous burden of stroke, only 15% of medical and fundamental research is dedicated to study and explore this medical condition compared to 85% in high-income countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, in Morocco, there is a lack of data concerning the temporal patterns of the incidence or the long-term evolution of this debilitating disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Since ischemic stroke is largely preventable, it is important to study the epidemiological and other aspects of care to reduce the incidence rate and the resulting burden on our kingdom. It is important to highlight that this is the first systematic review of the literature on stroke to be conducted in Morocco. In this respect, the objective of this work was to evaluate, through the systematic review, the epidemiological and etiological profiles, influencing factors of the prehospital delay, thrombolysis management, mortality rate in the acute phase and at 3&#x02009;months, along with the genetic aspect of IS in Morocco.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Research strategy</title><p id="Par21">This systematic review was conducted in accordance with the methodological criteria of the Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses (PRISMA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The protocol has been previously registered and published (PROSPERO: CRD42018115206/<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.crd.york.ac.uk/PROSPERO/display_record.php?ID=CRD42018115206">http://www.crd.york.ac.uk/PROSPERO/display_record.php?ID=CRD42018115206</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par22">This is a systematic review of the literature by adopting a multisource research strategy, consulting the databases of Pubmed, Sciencedirect, Scopus, Clinicalkey, and Google scholar for raking gray literature (National Scientific Research Works such as Master theses and PhD dissertations of medicine) between 2009 and 2018 (Last questioning on November, the 29th 2018).</p><p id="Par23">The key words used were as follows: (Ischemic stroke) or (cerebral infarction) or (Cerebral ischemia) or (ischemic stroke) or (ischemic attack) or (Cerebral ischemia) or (Cerebral infarction) and (Morocco) or indicating specific cities of the kingdom.</p><p id="Par24">Two authors (KA and OM) independently verified titles and abstracts to identify the to-be included studies. Complete articles of the potential studies were downloaded for a more detailed evaluation and the list of references in all relevant articles were examined for additional documents as well as for the citing papers. No restrictions were made on the language of publication.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Inclusion and exclusion criteria</title><p id="Par25">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par26">Studies were conducted in Morocco and published after 2009 concerning IS.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27">Studies on the following data: age, sex ratio, risk factors, etiologic profile, prehospital delay and the management of cerebral ischemia including thrombolysis.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par28">Studies on genetic polymorphisms related to the occurrence of cerebral ischemia in Morocco.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par29">Studies on IS in patients aged less than 15&#x02009;years old where cerebral venous thromboses have been excluded.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Extraction and analysis of data</title><p id="Par30">The data extracted from the identified documents were the following: average age, sex ratio, risk factors, etiological profile according to the Trial of ORG classification 10,172 in Acute Stroke Treatment (TOAST) classification, prehospital delay, stroke management (thrombolysis), mortality rate at the acute phase and at 3&#x02009;months according to the modified Rankin score, and genes involved in the occurrence of cerebral ischemia in Morocco.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Risk of bias in individual studies</title><p id="Par31">Bias risk assessment was conducted by two authors independently through the use of &#x0201c;Quality Assessment Tool for Case Series Studies&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Quality Assessment Tool for Cross-Sectional Studies&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Newcastle-Ottawa Quality Assessment Scale Case-Control Studies&#x0201d;.</p><p id="Par32">Two reviewers (KA and OM) assessed the methodological quality of the studies independently and then the agreement between the two examiners&#x02019; results was analyzed by the Kappa statistical coefficient (&#x003ba;).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><p id="Par33">Twenty-nine (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;29) studies were selected (The flow chart is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Based on study type: Full original papers (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;13), conference abstracts (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;6), medical theses (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;10). By locations: Rabat (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;5), Casablanca (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;7), Casablanca and Rabat (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;1), Marrakech (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;7), Fez (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;8), and Meknes (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;1). According to the study design: (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;15) were retrospective case series, (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;8) were prospective case series, (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;1) were prospective cross sectional study, and (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;5) were prospective case-control studies. According to the age of the target population of the selected studies, (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;25) studies targeted all ages combined (More than 15&#x02009;years old) and (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies focused on the young population (15&#x02013;45&#x02009;years old). All studies were hospital series.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA 2009 flow diagram</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2019_1558_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">The Kappa statistical coefficient was (&#x003ba;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.64). The Quality Rating of &#x0201c;case series&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;cas-control&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;cross-sectional&#x0201d; studies were considered &#x0201c;good&#x0201d; with an average score of 7.5/9 (the results of the methodological evaluation of case series studies are shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Quality assessment tool for case series studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Criteria</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</th><th>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1. Was the study question or objective clearly stated?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>2. Was the study population clearly and fully described, including a case definition?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>3. Were the cases consecutive?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>4. Were the subjects comparable?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>5. Was the intervention clearly described?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>6. Were the outcome measures clearly defined, valid, reliable, and implemented consistently across all study participants?</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>7. Was the length of follow-up adequate?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>8. Were the statistical methods well-described?</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>9. Were the results well-described?</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Score</td><td>9</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>8</td><td>6</td><td>9</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>6</td><td>8</td><td>7</td><td>6</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>8</td><td>7</td><td>9</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>8</td><td>8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Mean age and sex ratio of patients with ischemic stroke in Morocco</title><p id="Par35">Twenty-three studies focusing on IS in all age groups revealed an average age ranging from 49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.2 to 67.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.9&#x02009;years old. Thus, the average age is listed in the fifth and sixth decade [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. However, two studies did not specify the average age of patients. The first study was conducted by Chraa (2010), who reported that the age was below 45&#x02009;years old in 36% of cases and more than 45&#x02009;years old in 64% of cases, while the second by Bourazza et al. (2013) indicated an age between the two extremes of 24 and 104&#x02009;years old [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par36">As for the sex ratio (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;13), studies revealed a male predominance with a ratio ranging between 1.23 and 3.45 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. A ratio of 1 has been reported only in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Similarly, a slight female predominance with a ratio between 0.7 and 0.9 was reported in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;9) studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">Concerning IS in early adulthood, four studies (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) included patients aged between 15 and 45&#x02009;years old. The first was a study by Mbagui (2009) with an age ranging between 15 and 45&#x02009;years old, the second of Ibouajbane (2014) between 16 and 45, the third of Chraa et al. (2014) with an age between 18 and 45 and the fourth of Allaoui et al. (2018), which included all patients admitted to internal medicine under the age of 45 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">According to the studies of IS in young people, the average age ranged from 28.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2 to 39&#x02009;years old (Extremes: 16&#x02013;45&#x02009;years old) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">Concerning the sex-ratio of IS in young cases, (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;2) studies reported values less than 1. The first is attributable to the one by Ibouajbane (2014) with a clear female predominance (sex -ratio of 0.4) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], and the second was performed by Allaoui et al. (2018) showing a slight female predominance with a sex ratio of 0.7 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par40">Male predominance was described by Chraa et al. (2014) with a sex ratio of 1.4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In addition, the Mbagui (2009) study did not show any significant difference between the two genders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Risk factors for ischemic stroke in Morocco according to the selected studies</title><p id="Par41">Studies included in the present critical review of the literature have revealed several risk factors associated with cerebral ischemia in the local populations of interest. Indeed, high blood pressure (HBP), diabetes, smoking and heart disease were the four main risk factors listed and are as follows: HBP was reported in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;20) studies (31 to 65.4%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], diabetes in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;20) studies (12&#x02013;41.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], cardiac diseases in 14 studies (7&#x02013;44.3%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], atrial fibrillation as associated heart disease was specified in 9 studies (2,5&#x02013;22%), and smoking in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;19) studies (4&#x02013;41.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">In addition to these risk factors, other risk factors have been reported such as dyslipidemia in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;16) studies (0&#x02013;61.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], obesity in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;6) studies (10.7&#x02013;26.1%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], the notion of a previous stroke was noted in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;10) hospital series (5&#x02013;26.6%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], alcoholism in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;10) studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], oral contraception in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies (6.6&#x02013;12.2%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and migraine in a single study at 6.5% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">Concerning the young population, the reported risk factors were smoking in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (5&#x02013;40.6%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], HBP in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (8% - 49.2%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], oral contraception in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (12&#x02013;31.2%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], cardiac diseases only by Chraa et al. (2014) with a percentage of 17.9% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], diabetes in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (7.5&#x02013;13.2%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], migraine in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (1.5&#x02013;24%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], dyslipidemia in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies (0&#x02013;15.3%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], alcoholism in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies (5&#x02013;8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], obesity only (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;1) by the study of Ibouajbane (2014) with a percentage of 2.5% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], previous strokes history in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;2) studies by Chraa et al. (2014) and by Ibouajbane (2014) with a percentage of 2.3% and 2.5%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], the first-degree family history of stroke was reported in a single study by Allaoui et al. (2018) with a percentage of 25% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and pregnancy was reported as key risk factor in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;2) studies, conducted by Mbagui (2009) and Chraa et al. (2014) with percentages of 0.9% and 1.5% respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] (The results are detailed in Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Risk factors for ischemic stroke in Morocco according to selected studies (First part)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Studies</th><th>Location</th><th>Age (years)</th><th>Sample size</th><th>HBP (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th><th>Diabetes (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th><th>Dyslipidemia (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th><th>Cardiac diseases (%)/AF (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>MBAGUI, R., 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>39</td><td>93 <sup>YIS</sup></td><td>11,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Abjaw, Z et al., 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>62,3</td><td>84 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>40,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>25</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>14,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Rhissassi et al., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>65,5</td><td>342 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>N A-Y AMESSAN., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>59,9</td><td>46 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>51</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>30</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>25/15</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>352 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>42,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5,7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>They TP et al., 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>49/46,2<sup>NS</sup></td><td>91 <sup>ISC</sup>/182<sup>Cl</sup></td><td>50,5/9,9<sup>**&#x02020;</sup></td><td>9,3 4,9-17,6</td><td>17,6/8,8<sup>*&#x02020;</sup></td><td>2,2 1,05-4,7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>AZDAD, O., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>66,3</td><td>1300 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>40,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>21,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>3,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>RACHDI, L., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</td><td>Meknes</td><td>63</td><td>40 <sup>ISTr</sup></td><td>32</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>24/17</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Bendriss, L et al., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>60,8</td><td>110 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>65,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>41,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>19,9/9</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>60,6</td><td>50 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>48</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>18</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>14</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02212;/22</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Saraya, T., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>66,7</td><td>242<sup>IS</sup></td><td>56,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>38,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>18,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Bourazza, A., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1256<sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>They TP et al., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>49/46,2<sup>NS</sup></td><td>91<sup>ISC</sup>/182<sup>Cl</sup></td><td>50,5/9,9<sup>**&#x003a9;</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17,6/8,8<sup>* &#x003a9;</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Ibouajbane, M., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>Meknes</td><td>36</td><td>40 <sup>YIS</sup></td><td>12,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>0</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Balar, K et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>57</td><td>165</td><td>50,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>21,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>11</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>28,3</td><td>128 <sup>YIS</sup></td><td>49,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>13,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>56,5</td><td>165</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Allaoui, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>36</td><td>25<sup>YIS</sup></td><td>8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>RACHDI., L et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>66</td><td>439 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>43</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>29</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>0</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02212;/7</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Belkouch et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>63</td><td>13 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>61</td><td>665 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>42,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5,7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>44,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>57</td><td>170 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>50,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>22,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Benkirane, N et al.,2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td>C and R<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td>59,5</td><td>157 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>59,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>31,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>61,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Yonmadji, N., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>64,9</td><td>1184 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>39,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>30</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9,6/2,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Daouda et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>67,3</td><td>46 <sup>IStr</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>57,1</td><td>175 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>50,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>20,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa M et al., 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>61</td><td>442 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>42,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>44,3/13,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Hadi, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>66,3</td><td>230 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>61</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>41</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>28,9/9</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>63</td><td>52 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>31</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>27/17</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>AF</italic> Atrial fibrillation, <italic>IS</italic> Ischemic Stroke, <italic>ISC</italic> Ischemic stroke cases, <italic>Cl</italic> Controls, <italic>NS</italic> Not significant, <italic>YIS</italic> Young Ischemic Stroke, <italic>ISTr</italic> Ischemic stroke trombolysed, <italic>Ob</italic> Obesity, <italic>M</italic> Migraine, <italic>HBP</italic> High Blood Pressure, <sup>&#x02021;</sup> Casablanca and Rabat;<sup>*</sup>
<italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;&#x02009;0,05; <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;&#x02009;0,001; <sup>&#x02020;</sup>: <italic>P</italic>-values obtained using Mantel&#x02013;Haenszel chi-square exact test; <sup>&#x003a9;</sup>
<italic>P</italic> value obtained using Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, <italic>OR</italic> Odds ratio, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Risk factors for ischemic stroke in Morocco according to selected studies (Part Two)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Studies</th><th>Location</th><th>Smoking (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th><th>Previous stroke/ family history of stroke (%)</th><th>Alcoholism (%)</th><th>OR 95% CI</th><th>Oral contraception (%)</th><th>Others (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>MBAGUI, R., 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char">33,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17,3</td><td>4,8</td></tr><tr><td>Abjaw, Z et al., 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>13,1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17,8</td><td>13,1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>10,7 <sup>ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Rhissassi et al., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>N A-Y AMESSAN., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>15</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5</td><td>2,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>25,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>11,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12,2</td><td>19,88 <sup>ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>They TP et al., 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>22<sup>C</sup>/7,1<sup>Cl*&#x02020;</sup></td><td>3,7 1,7-7,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,4 <sup>C</sup> /2,2 <sup>Cl**&#x02020;</sup></td><td>8,8 2,6-</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>AZDAD, O., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>12,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>0,2</td><td>25,4</td><td>6,64</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>RACHDI, L., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</td><td>Meknes</td><td>13</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Bendriss, L et al., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>35,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,4<sup>ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>14</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12</td><td/><td>&#x02013;</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Saraya, T., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>41,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4,7</td><td>4,13</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>19,4<sup>ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Bourazza, A., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>They TP et al., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>22<sup>C</sup>/7,1<sup>Cl*&#x003a9;</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>15,4<sup>C</sup>/2,2<sup>Cl**&#x003a9;</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Ibouajbane, M., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>Meknes</td><td>5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2,5</td><td>5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>17,5</td><td>2,5<sup>ob</sup>/5<sup>M</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Balar, K et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td/><td>&#x02013;</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>40,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2,3</td><td>8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>31,2</td><td>1,56 <sup>M</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Allaoui, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>32</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02212;/25</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>12</td><td>24<sup>M</sup></td></tr><tr><td>RACHDI., L et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Belkouch et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>Rabat</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>25,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>34,1</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Benkirane, N et al.,2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td>C and R<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td>31,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>26,1<sup>Ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Yonmadji, N., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>18,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8,4</td><td>0</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8,8</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Daouda et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>Casablanca</td><td>33,7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>8</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa M et al., 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>25,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Hadi, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>Marrakech</td><td>33,3</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>9,2</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>20 <sup>Ob</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]</td><td>Fes</td><td>4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>C</italic> Cases, <italic>Cl</italic> Controls, <italic>IS</italic> Ischemic Stroke, <italic>YIS</italic> Young Ischemic Stroke, <italic>ISTr</italic> Ischemic stroke trombolysed, <italic>Ob</italic> Obesity, <italic>M</italic> Migraine, <italic>HBP</italic> High Blood Pressure</p><p><sup>&#x02021;</sup>Casablanca and Rabat; <sup>*</sup><italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;&#x02009;0,05; <sup>**</sup><italic>P</italic>-value&#x0003c;&#x02009;0,001; <sup>&#x02020;</sup><italic>P</italic>-values obtained using Mantel&#x02013;Haenszel chi-square exact test; <sup>&#x003a9;</sup><italic>P</italic> value obtained using Fisher&#x02019;s exact test</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Genetic risk factors for ischemic stroke in Moroccan studies</title><p id="Par44">The present systematic review includes only (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;5) studies focusing on the genetic factors associated with IS in Morocco.</p><p id="Par45">The first study by They et al. (2011) suggested that the <italic>MTHFR C677T</italic> variant could be a determinant of the atherothrombotic event of IS in Morocco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The same team, They et al. (2013) demonstrated an interaction between <italic>MTHFR C677TT</italic> and <italic>F2 20210GA</italic> polymorphisms linked to an increased risk of IS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The third study by Diakite et al. (2014) suggested another statistically significant association between <italic>G894&#x02009;T</italic> polymorphism at the level of <italic>eNOS</italic> gene and IS in the recessive, dominant and additive models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par46">In addition, another genetic study by Diakite et al. (2015) evaluated the association of the <italic>FVF C2491T</italic> mutation with the risk of IS, suggesting that carriers of the mutated T allele were associated with a high risk of IS. But this risk was 8.95 times higher when the subject had the TT genotype (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x000a0;0.0001) and 4.08 times higher with the CT genotype, and they concluded that the <italic>FVF C2491T</italic> mutation could be a genetic risk factor for IS in the Moroccan population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p><p id="Par47">The fourth genetic research was conducted by Diakite et al. (2016) on <italic>T-1131C APOA5</italic> polymorphism; he observed a modest risk of IS with CC and C alleles. In addition, the same study explored also the risk of IS related to <italic>SG13S114 ALOX5AP</italic> and showed a significant association with TT and T alleles. Despite the reduced sample size, variants of <italic>T-1131C APOA5</italic> and <italic>SG13S114</italic> could be considered as an independent genetic risk factor IS in the Moroccan population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Furthermore, the fifth study by Balar (2014), showed that <italic>MTHFR</italic> gene (patients with <italic>MTHFR</italic> CT/ TT patients without CT/TT) and other factors (sex, age, HBP, diabetes, smoking, alcoholism, dyslipidemia) did not reveal significant correlation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. (Results are detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Results of published studies on the association between six genes and ischemic stroke in Morocco</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Study</th><th>Cases</th><th>Controls</th><th>Genes</th><th>Mutations</th><th char="&#x000d7;">Genotypes</th><th>Methods</th><th>Odds Ratio 95% (CI)</th><th><italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">They, TP et al., 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">91</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="2">182</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>MTHFR</italic></td><td rowspan="2"><italic>C677T</italic></td><td>T allele and Stroke</td><td rowspan="2">PCR</td><td>1.1 (0.59&#x02013;2.04)</td><td>0.303<sup>&#x003a9;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>T allele and atherothrombotic subtype stroke</td><td>2.1 (1.17&#x02013;3.8)</td><td>0.012<sup>&#x003a9;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>They, TP et al., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]</td><td char="." align="char">91</td><td char="." align="char">182</td><td><p><italic>MTHFR</italic><sup><italic>*</italic></sup></p><p><italic>F2</italic></p></td><td><p><italic>C677T</italic></p><p><italic>G20210A</italic></p></td><td><p><italic>677TT/CC</italic></p><p><italic>20210GA</italic>/<italic>GG</italic></p></td><td>PCR-RFLP</td><td><p>4.99 (1.75&#x02013;14.2)</p><p>5.29 (1.63&#x02013;17.1)</p></td><td><p>0.001<sup>&#x0220f;</sup></p><p>0.005<sup>&#x02211;</sup></p></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Diakite, B et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">165</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">182</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>eNOS</italic></td><td rowspan="3"><italic>G894&#x02009;T</italic></td><td>TT vs. GG&#x02009;+&#x02009;GT Recessive</td><td rowspan="3">PCR-RFLP</td><td>2,68 (1,08-6,70)</td><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char">0.034 <sup>&#x00394;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>GT&#x02009;+&#x02009;TT vs. GG Dominant</td><td>1.78 (1,16&#x02013;2,73)</td><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char">0.009 <sup>&#x00394;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>T vs. G Additive models</td><td>1.71 (1,21&#x02013;2,43)</td><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char">0.003 <sup>&#x00394;</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Diakite, B et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">170</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="3">211</td><td rowspan="3"><italic>FV</italic></td><td rowspan="3"><italic>C2491T</italic></td><td>T all&#x000e8;le</td><td rowspan="3">PCR-RFLP</td><td>3.77 (2.70&#x02013;5.25)</td><td rowspan="3">&#x0003c; 0.0001<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td>CT</td><td>4.08 (2.55&#x02013;6.49)</td></tr><tr><td>TT</td><td>8.95 (4.15&#x02013;19.29)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Diakite, B et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="4">175</td><td char="." align="char" rowspan="4">201</td><td rowspan="2"><italic>APOA5</italic></td><td rowspan="2"><italic>T1131C</italic></td><td>CC</td><td rowspan="2">PCR-RFLP</td><td>2.86 (1.24&#x02013;6.58)</td><td rowspan="2">0.014 <sup>&#x022ff;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>C allele</td><td>1.54 (1.01&#x02013;2.33)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"><italic>ALOX5AP</italic></td><td rowspan="2"><italic>SG13S114</italic></td><td>TT</td><td rowspan="2">PCR-RFLP</td><td>2.57 (1.49&#x02013;4.83)</td><td>0.009 <sup>&#x022ff;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>T allele</td><td>1.59 (1.16&#x02013;2.19)</td><td>0.008 <sup>&#x022ff;</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Balar, K et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</td><td colspan="2">165<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td><italic>MTHFR</italic></td><td>Facteurs de risque <sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td>CT/TT</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>NS ^</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>PCR-RFLP</italic> Polymerase Chain Reaction-Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism, <sup>*</sup>Synergistic effect of MTHFR C677T and F2 G20210A polymorphisms on ischemic stroke. <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Prospective study, <sup>&#x02021;</sup>Age/Diabetes/High Blood Pressure/Smoking/Alcoholism/ Cholesterol, NS: Not significant, <sup>&#x003a9;</sup>Hardy&#x02013; Weinberg equilibrium tests were performed for MTHFR C677T polymorphism separately among cases and controls with the use of Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, <sup>&#x0220f;</sup>Univariate analysis for the combined polymorphisms, <sup>&#x02211;</sup>multivariate analysis for the combined polymorphisms, <sup>&#x00394;</sup>The law of the genotype distribution for G894&#x02009;T eNOS polymorphism among disease cases and controls were performed with Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg equilibrium test with the use of &#x003c7;2 test, <sup>**</sup>Significant; HWE, Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg equilibrium, <sup>&#x022ff;</sup>Hardy&#x02013;Weinberg equilibrium test with the use of &#x003c7;2 test or Fisher test, ^the multivariate analysis (logistic regression)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>TOAST etiological classification of ischemic stroke in Moroccan studies</title><p id="Par48">The most prominent etiology is atherosclerosis of large arteries according to (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;16) studies (16&#x02013;57.8%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The cardioembolic origin comes second in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;17) studies (8.8&#x02013;50%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], undetermined causes were present in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;12) studies (5.5&#x02013;34%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], lacunar ischemic stroke was reported in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;12) studies (0&#x02013;39%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and other identified causes are recorded in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;13) studies (0&#x02013;27.4%] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par49">Concerning the etiological category &#x0201c;Other identified causes&#x0201d;, five studies have specified the pathologies involved in the ontogeny and the occurrence of ischemic stroke conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The first study was performed by Chraa (2010), and has reported 14 cases of syphilitic arteritis, 12 cases related to disorders of clotting factors, 5 cases of arterial dissection, 4 cases of systemic diseases, 4 cases of migraine, 1 case of chemotherapy, and 1 case of human immunodeficiency virus . The second study was conducted by Chtau (2012) and revealed that 2% of all cases were related to arterial dissections. The third was done by Rachdi (2012) and who reported 1 case of Vaquez disease. The fourth study by Saraya (2013) revealed 1 case of polycythemia, 1 case with interhemispheric Meningioma, a toxic IS after Cannabis consumption, and an IS after cerebral angiography as part of the assessment of a C3 Neuroma. The last study was conducted by Rachdi (2015) and showed that 5% of all cases were related to carotid stenosis when it was greater than 50%. However, six other studies did not identify the &#x0201c;Other identified causes&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par50">With respect to the young population (15&#x02013;45&#x02009;years old), the undetermined causes were identified in four studies. The first study was by Mbagui (2009) with a percentage of 29% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The second by Chraa et al. (2014) with a percentage of 40.6% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The third by Ibouajbane (2014); 55% of all cases were linked to undetermined causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Finally, Allaoui et al. (2018) reported a percentage of 24% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">The IS of cardioembolic origin was also highlighted in four studies; the first study was performed by Mbagui (2009) and reported a percentage of 21.5% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The second by Ibouajbane (2014) showed a percentage of 15% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Interestingly, the third study was by Chraa et al. (2014) revealed that 33.6% of all cases were present with cardioembolic source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. By contrast, the fourth study by Allaoui et al. (2018) reported a percentage of 4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par52">As for the other determinant causes, they were identified in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;4) studies (Mbagui, 2009; Chraa et al., 2014; Ibouajbane, 2014; Allaoui et al., 2018) with 21.5%, 14.1%, 15% and 72% respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">Concerning the details on the etiological class &#x0201c;other specific causes&#x0201d;, four studies specified the causes involved in the occurrence of IS in young population. The first by Mbagui (2009) highlighted the implication of blood diseases, vasculitis, oral contraception and carotid dissections with percentages of 35%, 25% (2 cases of Behcet, 1 case of Takayashu, 2 cases of undetermined vasculitis), and 15%, respectively. In addition, 1 case of sneddon syndrome, and 1 post-partum cases were reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">The second by Ibouajbane (2014), angiitis accounted for 5% of cases, hematological disorders for 5% of the cases, 1 case was observed during pregnancy and especially during the sixth month, and thrombophlebitis in another case [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The third by Chraa et al. (2014) described 11 cases of syphilis, 3 cases of carotid dissections, 2 cases of coagulation protein deficiency (C), 1 case of sneddon syndrome, and 1 case of anti-phospholipids&#x02019; antibody syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par55">The fourth study by Allaoui et al. (2018) described a percentage of determinate causes of 72%. The etiologies in this study were dominated by systemic lupus (32%) associated with antiphospholipid syndrome (80%), Behcet&#x02019;s disease (16%), Takayasu&#x02019;s disease (12%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par56">With respect to atherosclerosis of large arteries, it was reported in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies; Chraa et al. (2014), Ibouajbane (2014) and Mbagui (2009) with proportions respectively of 11.7%, 12.5% and 25.8% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par57">Lacunar IS was found in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;2) studies, including Mbagui (2009) and Ibouajbane (2014) with ratios of 2.1 and 2.5%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. In Allaoui et al. study (2018), TOAST III (lacunary) patients were 73% smokers, 8% had type II diabetes and/or High blood pressure, and 12% had oestroprogestative contraception at the time of diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. (Results are detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>TOAST etiological classification of ischemic stroke according to selected studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Studies</th><th>Sample size</th><th>Atherosclerosis of large arteries (%)</th><th>Cardio-embolic Stroke (%)</th><th>Occlusion of small vessels (Lacunar) (%)</th><th>Other determinate causes of stroke (%)</th><th>Undetermined causes of stroke (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td char="&#x000d7;" align="char">Chraa, M., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>352</td><td>32,1</td><td>28,4</td><td>7,38</td><td>11,65</td><td>20,45</td></tr><tr><td>Mbagui., 2009 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]</td><td>93<sup>YIS</sup></td><td>25,81</td><td>21,51</td><td>2,15</td><td>21,51</td><td>29,03</td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]</td><td>52</td><td>32</td><td>50</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>Chtaou, N., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</td><td>50</td><td>44</td><td>28</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2</td><td>26</td></tr><tr><td>Yonmadji, N., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>1184</td><td>57,8</td><td>21,4</td><td>10</td><td>5,25</td><td>5,55</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</td><td>170</td><td>39,4</td><td>27,1</td><td>6,5</td><td>27,1</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Belkouch et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>13</td><td>41,3</td><td>27</td><td>22</td><td>0</td><td>9,7</td></tr><tr><td>Hadi, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>230</td><td>16</td><td>32</td><td>34</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</td><td>175</td><td>39,4</td><td>26,9</td><td>6,3</td><td>27,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Rachdi, L., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]</td><td>40</td><td>39</td><td>43,9</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>2,5</td><td>14,6</td></tr><tr><td>Ibouajbane., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]</td><td>40<sup>YIS</sup></td><td>12,5</td><td>15</td><td>2,5</td><td>15</td><td>55</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>128<sup>YIS</sup></td><td>11,72</td><td>33,59</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>14,06</td><td>40,62</td></tr><tr><td>Diakite, B et al., 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</td><td>165</td><td>56,36</td><td>32,12</td><td>4,84</td><td>6,66</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Bendriss, L et al., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>110</td><td>28</td><td>18</td><td>39</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>14,5</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M et al., 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>442</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>28,4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Saraya, T., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>242</td><td>18,6</td><td>25,6</td><td>17,8</td><td>20,3</td><td>17,8</td></tr><tr><td>They TP et al., 2011 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td><td>91</td><td>46,2</td><td>8,8</td><td>26,4</td><td>12,1</td><td>6,6</td></tr><tr><td>Azdad, O., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>1300</td><td>53,8</td><td>30,7</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>1</td><td>13,8</td></tr><tr><td>Rachdi, L et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>439</td><td>21</td><td>24</td><td>16</td><td>5</td><td>34</td></tr><tr><td>Rhissassi et al., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>342</td><td>52,1</td><td>27,6</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Allaoui, A et al., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]</td><td>25<sup>YIS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>72</td><td>24</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>YIS: Ischemic stroke of young adult (15&#x02013;45&#x02009;years)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Prehospital delay in patients with ischemic stroke in Morocco</title><p id="Par58">Since the notion of time is crucial in the management of cerebral ischemia, (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;5) studies evaluated the prehospital delay, which consists of the time extending between the time of the symptoms onset and the patient arrival to the emergency department of the different hospital structures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In this perspective, a minimum prehospital average delay was 26&#x02009;h [Extremes: 15&#x02009;Minutes- 8&#x02009;months] according to the study by Azdad (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and a maximum mean prehospital delay 61.9&#x02009;h [Extreme: 0.5&#x02009;h-216&#x02009;h] which was listed in the Yonmadji (2016) study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. (The results are detailed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Mean prehospital stroke delay (symptom onset to emergency department arrival) and percent arriving in 3, and after 24&#x02009;h in Morocco publication</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Studies</th><th rowspan="2">Study dates</th><th rowspan="2">Location</th><th rowspan="2">Population reported on</th><th rowspan="2">Delay in hours</th><th colspan="2">Per cent arriving in</th></tr><tr><th>&#x0003c;&#x02009; 3&#x02009;h</th><th>&#x0003e;&#x02009; 24&#x02009;h</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Rhissassi et al., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</td><td>During the year 2009</td><td>UHC Hassan II Fes</td><td>342<sup>IS</sup></td><td>61</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>N A-Y AMESSAN., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>November 2009 to April 2010</td><td>SH Rabat</td><td>46<sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>28</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Chraa, M., 2010 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]</td><td>January2000 to December2009</td><td>UHC Marrakech</td><td>352 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>AZDAD, O., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</td><td>01/01/2009 to 01/2/2010</td><td>UHC Hassan II Fes</td><td>1300 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>26</td><td>9,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Bendriss, L et al., 2012 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]</td><td>January 2005 and August 2008</td><td>Cardiology MHAM</td><td>110 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>41</td></tr><tr><td>Saraya, T., 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</td><td>January2009 to December 2011</td><td>MVMTH Rabat</td><td>242<sup>IS</sup></td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>4,5</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>RACHDI, L et al., 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]</td><td>June 2014 and December 2014</td><td>UHC Hassan II Fes</td><td>439 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>27</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td>Yonmadji, N., 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</td><td>January2013 to December 2014</td><td>UHC Hassan II Fes</td><td>1184 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>61,9</td><td>12,2<sup>a</sup></td><td>68,3</td></tr><tr><td>Hadi, A., 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]</td><td>January2010 to December 2014</td><td>Cardiology MHAM</td><td>230 <sup>IS</sup></td><td>36</td><td>&#x02013;</td><td>&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>IS</italic> Ischemic stroke, <italic>UHC</italic> University Hospital Center, <italic>SH</italic> Specialty Hospital, <italic>MHAM</italic> Military Hospital Avicenna Marrakech, <italic>MVMTH</italic> Mohamed V Military and Training Hospital</p><p><sup>a</sup>Patients received within 4.5&#x02009;h after onset of symptoms</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par59">Concerning the consultation period of young patients, It was assessed in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Mbagui (2009) and Ibouajbane studies (2014) reported 134.4&#x02009;h and 342&#x02009;h, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Moreover, Allaoui et al. (2018) showed that the delay between the onset of symptoms and the performance of the first cerebral imaging exceeded 12&#x02009;h in 100% of cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. No study investigated the factors influencing the consultation and admission time of patients with IS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>The percentage of patients with thrombolyzed ischemic stroke in Morocco</title><p id="Par60">Four studies conducted at the neurology department of the Hassan II University Hospital of Fez had focused on the thrombolysis management. The proportion of thrombolysed patients ranged from 1.8% in the Azdad study (2012) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] to 2.9% in the Rachdi (2015) study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. In addition, two studies by Yonmadji (2016) and Daouda et al. (2018) revealed two medium proportions of thrombolysed patients of 1.94% and 2.8%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Mortality in the acute phase and mortality in the chronic phase (3&#x02009;months) in Morocco</title><p id="Par61">Six studies reported the mortality rates in the acute phase, ranging from 3% in Yonmadji (2016) study to 13% for Chraa (2010) study. In addition, four studies by Saraya (2013), Rhissassi et al. (2010), Chtaou (2016) and Azdad (2012) revealed intermediate values of 5.8%, 9.9%, 10% and 10.8%, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>].</p><p id="Par62">The rate of mortality after 3&#x02009;months onset of the disease was reported in seven studies. Three studies by Bendriss et al. (2012), Rachdi (2015), and Hadi (2018) reported respectively the mortality rates of 5.4%, 10%, and 8%. Four studies by Daouda et al. (2018), Yonmadji (2016), Chtaou (2016), and Rachdi (2012), respectively reported mortality rates of 4.3%, 21.7%, 29%, and 32.5% in IS treated with thrombolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par63">The mortality during the acute phase in the young population was indicated in (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;3) studies. The first from Ibouajbane (2014) stated a mortality rate of 0% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], the second by Mbagui (2009) at 1.1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and the third by Chraa et al. (2014) with a mortality rate of 16.4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p><p id="Par64">For the mortality after 3&#x02009;months, no study elucidated this parameter.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par65">The average onset age of IS in Morocco was between 49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.2 and 67.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.9&#x02009;years old. The studies by Mbagui (2009), Chraa (2010) and Chraa et al. (2014) showed that the onset of IS occurs in 12.3%, 28.9% and 36% respectively of the population under 45 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The early onset of IS in Morocco according to the studies could probably be due to the young age of the Moroccan population and the low percentage of the elderly (over 60&#x02009;years old), which represents 9.4% according to the results of the last national census of the population of 2014 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. The young age could be explained by the high frequency of embolic heart disease, rheumatic heart disease and sexually transmitted infections (syphilis, and acquired immunodeficiency syndrome) in Morocco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. In addition, cardioembolic disease is considered as the leading cause of IS in the young population in our country due to the preponderance of rheumatic heart disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Similarly, it may also be due to the very high level of consanguinity and the significant association with the incidence of health conditions in the Moroccan population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par66">Furthermore, the average onset age of cerebral ischemia in Morocco is still lower with respect to the average age of patients admitted for IS in France in 2014 (74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15&#x02009;years old) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and in comparison to the average age identified in a systematic review in the Arab countries (58.5 and 63&#x02009;years old) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Besides, the average age of the young population ranged between 28 and 39&#x02009;years, which is in accordance with the results reported in other North African and the Middle Eastern countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Since Morocco is a country from the Middle East and North Africa region (MENA), the average age reported in Moroccan studies is lower than the one described in non-MENA countries. This confirms the results obtained from the results of Safe Implementation of Treatments in Stroke (SITS)-MENA register (in MENA 55&#x02009;years versus 73&#x02009;years in Non-MENA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">Most Moroccan studies have reported male predominance, consistent with the results of a literature review in the Arab world, which indicated that men were most often victims of stroke (between 55.9 and 75%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par68">These findings are also consistent with the results of a literature review at the level of Eastern Mediterranean countries, which has explored higher prevalence of stroke between men compared to women with a sex ratio up to 3.5 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Moreover, the same findings are in accordance with the results reported in the Middle East between 1980 and 2015 reporting gender differences, and that 75% of studies reported a high sex ratio in patients with stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. This is also confirmed by a recent observational study based on the results of the SITS-MENA register, which showed a male predominance (72%) in MENA countries compared to non-MENA countries (53.6%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. This result could be due to hormonal factors including estrogen, which seems to have protective effects on both the vascular and cerebral systems [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].</p><p id="Par69">In addition to diabetes, HBP is the main risk factor for IS in Morocco, smoking and heart disease represented the other identified risk factors. In the African context more than half of patients with ischemic stroke had HBP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. This joins the results of the literature review of studies conducted in the Middle East between 1980 and 2015, showing that HBP was the most common risk factor, followed by diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. These findings are also consistent with data collected in the Eastern Mediterranean countries, where the prevalence of HBP was above 50% in 38 studies, diabetes percentage was higher than 25% in 36 studies, and smoking was higher than 15% in 26 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The same results are consistent with those found in a recent observational study showing that hypertension, diabetes and smoking were the main risk factors identified in MENA countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par70">For atrial fibrillation, most of the studies included in the present review demonstrated percentages exceeding 9%. This rate is higher than the proportion recorded in the SITS-MENA register (8.8%), while atrial fibrillation in non-MENA countries accounted for 19.4% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</p><p id="Par71">The elevated frequency of these vascular risk factors in Morocco could be due to the phenomena of urbanization (60.3% of the population), and to changes in lifestyle of the Moroccan population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], as well as to the westernization of the behavior and the food habits between Moroccans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. However, a study conducted in the city of Casablanca showed that fast foods have a high composition of sodium and saturated fatty acids and a small concentration of unsaturated fatty acids, contributing thus to the increased prevalence of cardiovascular diseases and stroke in Morocco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>].</p><p id="Par72">Concerning the risk factors of IS between young people, HBP and smoking remains the most reported factors. This can be justified by the fact that Morocco is considered one of the highest tobacco consuming countries in the Mediterranean area with a consumption rate of 15 billion cigarettes each year, and that 42% of men aged between 30 and 39&#x02009;years old are smokers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p><p id="Par73">Oral contraception is also a preponderant risk factor between the young subjects. These results can be justified in Morocco by the massive use of hormonal contraceptive methods. For this reason, and according to the performance of the national family planning program established in 2015, the pill represents a percentage of 90% of all contraceptive used methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Similarly, a meta-analysis of 16 studies conducted in America in 2015 showed that oral contraceptives are associated with an increased relative risk of cerebral infarction of 2.75 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>].</p><p id="Par74">Genetically speaking, studies have suggested that <italic>MTHFR C677T</italic> variant could be a determining event of atherothrombotic IS in Morocco, which is perfectly in line with the results reported in a recent meta-analysis showing that the <italic>MTHFR C677T</italic> mutation increased the risk of IS in adulthood, particularly in atherosclerosis of large arteries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. The study by Diakite et al. (2014) suggested a statistically significant association between G894&#x02009;T polymorphism of eNOS gene and IS, which is consistent with the results of a meta-analysis confirming that G894&#x02009;T polymorphism of eNOS gene is associated with high risk of IS among Asian populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>T-1131C APOA5</italic> mutation could be considered as a genetic risk factor nondependent on IS between the Moroccan population. The same findings were reported in the Chinese population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. For <italic>SG13S114 ALOX5AP</italic>, a significant association was observed in subjects with TT and T alleles in Morocco. The same result was obtained for the Iberian population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>].</p><p id="Par75">Regarding the etiological classification of TOAST, the present work showed that atherosclerosis of the major arteries is the most dominant etiology. This is probably due mainly to the increased prevalence of HBP and diabetes in the Moroccan population. HBP and diabetes are estimated at 29.3% and 10.6%, respectively, in addition to poor compliance with antihypertensive therapy or poor glycemic controls, according to the national survey on common risk factors for non-communicable diseases (NCDs) both in 2017 and 2018. In line with this, the percentage of people with HBP who do not take medication in Morocco is estimated at 71.4% [CI: 69.1&#x02013;73.7%]. Furthermore, the proportion of people who have never tested their blood glucose levels is 63.2% [CI: 61.8&#x02013;64.6%] according to the same survey on risk factors common to NCDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].</p><p id="Par76">The average prehospital delay for patients with IS in Morocco has ranged between 26 to 61.9&#x02009;h, which far exceeds the therapeutic window recommended by randomized clinical trials [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>].This finding is in accordance with the median admission time (31&#x02009;h) mentioned in a review of literature on the African continent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. What is more, it joins the average consultation time mentioned in a prospective cross-sectional study conducted at the Center of Brazzaville University Hospital in the Republic of Congo, where they reported a period of 28.2&#x02009;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. A longer time period (16&#x02009;h) was also recorded in a study conducted at the Sahloul Hospital Center in Sousse, Tunisia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. These very long delays listed in our review, were collected mainly in the two university hospitals of Fez and Marrakech and could be explained by the lack of knowledge of the early signs of cerebral infarction. Furthermore, this delay of consultation in the Moroccan population could be linked to the lack of awareness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. This finding was confirmed by a study conducted at the Mohamed VI University Hospital Center in Marrakech, in which 59.8% of the interviewees could not name any revealing signs of cerebral ischemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. However, these different findings could probably be due to the elevated illiteracy rate within the Moroccan population (32.2% according to the results of the last census) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. This could also be explained by the fact that most of the patients arrived at the emergency rooms using personal or common means of transportation (taxi, personal car), and only a minority used ambulance services (3.5%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. From the same perspective, a recent review demonstrated that low awareness of the signs and symptoms of stroke, the shortage of medical transportation, health care staff and stroke management units, as well as the economic cost of the access to brain imaging facilities and thrombolysis were reported as major obstacles to improve stroke care and stroke management in Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].</p><p id="Par77">Concerning the management of IS patients, all thrombolysis-related studies were conducted at the University Hospital of Fez. Therefore, the small percentage of recruited patients could be due, in major part, to the fact that this technique has been recently implemented in the Hassan II University Hospital of Fez [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Interestingly, the Daouda study (2017) showed that 11% of cerebral infarcts did not benefit from thrombolysis because they were admitted after 4.5&#x02009;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Moreover, the Rachdi (2015) study also showed that the majority of patients were not thrombolysed because of the long consultation time and other interfering factors such as the lack of patient&#x02019;s awareness about the clinical signs of IS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p><p id="Par78">Hence, the transportation means (car, taxi, private ambulance), the organizational issues of the emergency medical service (EMS), the difficulties in the recognition of symptoms of IS by the patient, the delays in seeking appropriate emergency care and in obtaining an urgent brain scan and the non-coverage of recombinant tissue plasminogen activator (rt-PA) by the Moroccan National Health System are the main causes involved in the non-access of the population to thrombolysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par79">Moreover, the performance of the Moroccan neurovascular departments is completely in accordance with the data reported in the literature. In this respect, reperfusion treatments (thrombolysis) were administered only to 1&#x02013;8% of the admitted patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. A recent meta-analysis showed that only 3% (95% CI 2&#x02013;4%) of patients were thrombolysed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>].</p><p id="Par80">Indeed, raising the public awareness on a large scale on the neurological signs of the disease are therefore an urgent need, and the organization of pre-hospital medical care from the perspective of reducing admission time and increasing the number of thrombolyzed patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par81">In addition, the present review revealed that acute mortality ranged from 3% to 13%. These results are lower than the rates reported in other Arab and African countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. These rates are below the estimated mortality rate described (18%) in sub-Saharan Africa during the first week of 2013 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. These rates are also lower than the one-month overall lethality rates in Middle Eastern countries, which was ranging from 12 to 32% according to a systematic review between 1980 and 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Similarly, this finding was confirmed by a very recent prospective observational study in the MENA region, showing decreased likelihood of patients death in the MENA with respect to non-MENA countries (6.5 versus 9.6%, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x02009;&#x000a0;0.001) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p><p id="Par82">Despite the importance of atherosclerotic ischemic and embolic origins in the context of studies of populations, the present critical review demonstrated low rates of lethality and minor rates of occlusion of small arteries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. These findings could be due to the implementation of a strategy of diagnosis and effective etiological treatment of cerebral ischemia in the studies we included in our review. Low mortality rates could also be explained by the lack of ischemic stroke studies evaluating mortality rates in Morocco [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Three-month mortality in thrombolyzed patients exceeded 20%, according to most studies, which is higher than the mortality rates recorded in a meta-analysis (about 13.4%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par83">The present review suffered from several limitations; for example, the studies in question cover only five major cities located in the central parts of the country. We still do not have any data about IS in the north and south of Morocco. Thus, it is difficult to draw any conclusions about the general population. Similarly, most studies were conducted at university hospitals, while most of the Moroccan population has limited access to these facilities. Besides, we should consider the limited access to health care services in rural areas, and the fact that half of stroke patients are not treated in hospitals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>], which exclude a wide range of epidemiological data.</p><p id="Par84">Furthermore, the most of the research on IS was only observation-based studies (Case series and cross-sectional studies), so the authors only tried to describe the patterns of the different variables (risk factors, etiologies&#x02026;) without using any statistical analysis to reveal potential correlations. Also, the very lacking data originated from the nature of the studies and the implemented local logistics.</p><p id="Par85">Another limitation concerns Moroccan hospital facilities, which mostly receive patients with severe stroke conditions displaying consciousness perturbations and severe hemiplegia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>], decreasing the medical attention toward minor strokes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par86">The IS remains a multi-factorial debilitating disorder in Morocco. Overall, available data show a concentration of all studies at university hospitals in metropolitan cities. Also, they suggest that cerebral ischemia is characterized by precocious onset (begins at an early age), male predominance, and etiologies and vascular risk factors observed in patients with IS, which is generally similar to findings in other Arab and African countries. What is more, several genetic markers have been suggested as predisposing factors of cerebral infarction in Morocco. The prehospital delays are very long, compared to the different deadlines listed in developed countries with pathways for the management of IS. Therefore, the expansion of epidemiological studies, particularly in other regions of the country will provide an opportunity to sharpen the incidence and prevalence. Finally, it is high time to further investigate the factors associated with long hospital admission delays in this invalidating pathology to increase the level of brain infarction eligibility for thrombolysis.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AF</term><def><p id="Par6">Atrial fibrillation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMS</term><def><p id="Par7">Emergency medical service</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HBP</term><def><p id="Par8">High blood pressure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IS</term><def><p id="Par9">Ischemic stroke</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MENA</term><def><p id="Par10">Middle-East and North African</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NCDs</term><def><p id="Par11">Noncommunicable diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PRISMA</term><def><p id="Par12">Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>rt-PA</term><def><p id="Par13">Recombinant tissue plasminogen activator</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SITS</term><def><p id="Par14">Safe implementation of treatments in stroke</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TOAST</term><def><p id="Par15">Trial of ORG classification 10,172 in Acute Stroke Treatment</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YIS</term><def><p id="Par16">Young ischemic stroke</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank Mr. Eloukili Mohamed the curator of the library of the faculty of medicine and pharmacy of Casablanca for his precious collaboration for making medical theses accessible to us. We are grateful to Mr. Achbani Abderrahmane, a member of the Laboratory Cell Biology and Molecular Genetics of the Faculty of Sciences of Ibnozohr University of Agadir, for his collaboration all along the completion of this review. We are also grateful to Dr. Ouhaz Zakaria (Department of Experimental Psychology, University of Oxford, United Kingdom) and Professor Acim Rachid (Ibn Zohr University, Agadir, Morocco) for their assistance in reviewing the quality of the English language manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>KA participated in the conceptualization and design of the review, performed the selection of studies, as well as data extraction, and he drafted the entire review. OM was involved in the conceptualization, the design of the review and data-extraction. OM was involved in the conceptualization and design of the review, data-extraction. She involved in the evaluation of the risk of bias for each included study. Also, she reviewed the article in different phases. LL involved in the evaluation of the risk of bias for each included study, participated in the writing of the protocol of the systematic review. AJ participated in revising the manuscript and more specifically the clinical component. MN participated in revising the manuscript. RR involved in the conceptualization and design of the review, supervised the review, and reviewed the results and the final approval of the manuscript. All authors participated in revising the manuscript and the final approval of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>There was no funding for this study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data used in the publication of this work were obtained from published studies. Also, the data supporting the conclusions in this article are available in the additional files.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par87">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par88">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par89">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirzaei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leeder</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of stroke in the Middle East and North Africa</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>295</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2010.05.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20541222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20541222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adeloye</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An estimate of the incidence and prevalence of stroke in Africa: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>e100724</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0100724</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24967899?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24967899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Campbell BC, Bladin CF, Donnan GA, Davis SM. Acute ischemic stroke. In: Handbook of neuroemergency clinical trials. 2nd ed: Elsevier; 2018. p. 3&#x02013;21.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Streletz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mushtak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimassi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahmoud</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dargham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu Raddad</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khattab</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of stroke in the MENA region: a systematic review</article-title><source>Int J Neurol Neurol Disord</source><year>2017</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>21</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Isabel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mas</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke prevention</article-title><source>Presse Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>45</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>e457</fpage><lpage>e471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lpm.2016.10.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27816341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27816341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engels</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Baglione</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Audibert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Viallefont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mourji</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Faris</surname><given-names>MEA</given-names></name><collab>Group GS</collab></person-group><article-title>Socioeconomic status and stroke prevalence in Morocco: results from the Rabat-Casablanca study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>e89271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0089271</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24586649?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24586649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boussen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accident vasculaire c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral isch&#x000e9;mique</article-title><source>Anesth R&#x000e9;anim</source><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anrea.2017.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moussaddy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Demchuk</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thrombolytic therapies for ischemic stroke: triumphs and future challenges</article-title><source>Neuropharmacology</source><year>2018</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>272</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2017.11.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29505787?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29505787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blanc-Labarre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Delpont</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hervieu-B&#x000e8;gue</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Osseby</surname><given-names>G-V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricolfi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Thouant</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Giroud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e9;jot</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prise en charge aigu&#x000eb; des infarctus c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux en 2017</article-title><source>Rev Med Interne</source><year>2018</year><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>408</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.revmed.2017.07.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28867531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28867531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global variation in stroke burden and mortality: estimates from monitoring, surveillance, and modelling</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1474-4422(09)70023-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19233730?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19233730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benamer</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosset</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke in Arab countries: a systematic literature review</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>284</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2009.04.029</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19428027?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19428027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tetzlaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>151</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>269</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-151-4-200908180-00135</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19622511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19622511</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abjaw Z, Zoubir M. Prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux au service de r&#x000e9;animation de l&#x02019;h&#x000f4;pital militaire Avicenne. Diab&#x000e8;te. 21:25 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bit.ly/2DZUwzS">https://bit.ly/2DZUwzS</ext-link>. Accessed 21 Nov 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allaoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Echchilali</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouissar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Moudatir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaoui</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>El Kabli</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accidents vasculaires isch&#x000e9;miques chez le sujet jeune en m&#x000e9;decine interne</article-title><source>Rev Med Interne</source><year>2014</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>A141</fpage><lpage>A142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.revmed.2014.10.241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AMESSAN NDA-Y. S&#x000e9;curisation du circuit du m&#x000e9;dicament en milieu hospitalier: exp&#x000e9;rience dans les accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;mique: Universite Mohammed V; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belkouch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jidane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouaib</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Elbouti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nebhani</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirbou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakkali</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Belyamani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thrombolysis for acute ischemic stroke by tenecteplase in the emergency department of a Moroccan hospital</article-title><source>Pan Afr Med J</source><year>2015</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><?supplied-pmid 26405473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26405473</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendriss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Les accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques. Fr&#x000e9;quence des &#x000e9;tiologies cardiovasculaires document&#x000e9;es par un bilan cardiovasculaire approfondi. &#x000c0; propos de 110 cas</article-title><source>Ann Cardiol Angeiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>2012</volume><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ancard.2012.04.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benkirane</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bennis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellakhdar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Habbal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>El Alaoui</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>El Otmani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>El Moutawakil</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafai</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Slassi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke risk factors in a Moroccan population: a multicentric prospective study</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>357</volume><fpage>e367</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2015.08.1314</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourazza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsaini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology study of stroke about 1256 cases</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>333</volume><fpage>e248</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2013.07.960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chraa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaqda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for ischemic stroke, about 442 cases</article-title><source>J Neurol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jns.2017.08.3353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chraa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facteurs de risque des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux</article-title><source>Rev Neurol</source><year>2015</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>A35</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurol.2015.01.074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chraa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Louhab</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke in young adults: about 128 cases</article-title><source>Pan Afr Med J</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24932348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24932348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chtaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachdi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>El Midaoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Souirti</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlgren</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Belahsen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous thrombolysis with rt-PA in stroke: experience of the moroccan stroke unit</article-title><source>Pan Afr Med J</source><year>2016</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>207</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11604/pamj.2016.24.207.8815</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27795802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27795802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daouda</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chtaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Midaoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Souirti</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Belahsen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thrombolysis alert in Hassan II University Teaching Hospital of Fez (Morocco): a prospective study of 2 years</article-title><source>J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1100</fpage><lpage>1106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2017.11.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29290532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chtaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><source>D&#x000e9;pistage du syndr&#x000f4;me d'apn&#x000e9;es obstructive du sommeil chez les accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques</source><year>2012</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bendriss</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatouri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>L&#x02019;apport des explorations cardiovasculaires r&#x000e9;alis&#x000e9;es de mani&#x000e8;re syst&#x000e9;matique lors du bilan &#x000e9;tiologique d&#x02019;un AVC isch&#x000e9;mique constitu&#x000e9; (&#x000c0; propos de 230 cas)</article-title><source>Ann Cardiol Angeiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>67</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ancard.2018.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rachdi L. Thrombolyse intraveineuse des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux : Etude prospective &#x000e0; propos de 40 cas. Th&#x000e8;se de m&#x000e9;decine. Universit&#x000e9; Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Facult&#x000e9; de m&#x000e9;decine et de pharmacie de F&#x000e8;s; 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rachdi L. Pronostic des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques : Etude prospective sur 7 mois, Exp&#x000e9;rience du service de neurologie, CHU Hassan II F&#x000e8;s. Th&#x000e8;se de m&#x000e9;decine. Universit&#x000e9; Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Facult&#x000e9; de m&#x000e9;decine et de pharmacie de F&#x000e8;s; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mbagui</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><source>Accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques du sujet jeune &#x000e9;tude d&#x02019;une s&#x000e9;rie de 93 cas</source><year>2009</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chraa M. La prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques. Th&#x000e8;se de m&#x000e9;decine. Universit&#x000e9; Cadi Ayyad, Facult&#x000e9; de m&#x000e9;decine et de pharmacie de Marrakech; 2010.p. 1-116.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ibouajbane M. L&#x02019;accident vasculaire c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral isch&#x000e9;mique du sujet jeune : A propos de 40 cas collig&#x000e9;s &#x000e0; l'H&#x000f4;pital Militaire Molay Ismail. Th&#x000e8;se de m&#x000e9;decine. Universit&#x000e9; Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Facult&#x000e9; de m&#x000e9;decine et de pharmacie de F&#x000e8;s; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Younmadji N. Prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques au service de neurologie du CHU Hassan II : A propos de 1184 Cas. Th&#x000e8;se de m&#x000e9;decine. Universit&#x000e9; Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah, Facult&#x000e9; de m&#x000e9;decine et de pharmacie de F&#x000e8;s; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Azdad O. Prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques au CHU Hassan II de F&#x000e8;s au cours de cours de la p&#x000e9;riode 2009&#x02013;2010 : a propos de 1300 cas: Universit&#x000e9; Sidi Mohamed Ben Abdellah; 2012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rhissassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Amazian</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chtaou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Messouaka</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Belahsen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Le profil &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologique des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques pris en charge au CHU de F&#x000e8;s, Maroc, 2009</article-title><source>Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique</source><year>2010</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>S61</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.respe.2010.06.048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Profil &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologique, clinique et &#x000e9;tiologique des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques chez le sujet &#x000e2;g&#x000e9; [Th&#x000e8;se]</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Rabat</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Universit&#x000e9; Mohamed V- Souissi</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>BALAR</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>NADIFI</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>Correlation between MTHFR and clinical risk factors in ischemic stroke</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diakite</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmimech</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadifi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First study of C2491T FV mutation with ischaemic stroke risk in Morocco</article-title><source>J Genet</source><year>2015</year><volume>94</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12041-015-0525-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26174681?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26174681</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diakite</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hmimech</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadifi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic polymorphisms of T-1131C APOA5 and ALOX5AP SG13S114 with the susceptibility of ischaemic stroke in Morocco</article-title><source>J Genet</source><year>2016</year><volume>95</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>309</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12041-016-0635-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27350673?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27350673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diakite</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamzi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Slassi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Yahyaoui</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaoui</surname><given-names>MME</given-names></name><name><surname>Habbal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sellama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G894T endothelial nitric oxide synthase polymorphism and ischemic stroke in Morocco</article-title><source>Meta Gene</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mgene.2014.04.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25606419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25606419</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>They-They</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadifi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Battas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Slassi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methylenehydrofolate reductase (C677T) polymorphism and large artery ischemic stroke subtypes</article-title><source>Acta Neurol Scand</source><year>2011</year><volume>123</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0404.2010.01348.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20637011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20637011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>They-They</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Battas</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadifi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic effect of MTHFR C677T and F2 G20210A polymorphisms on ischemic stroke</article-title><source>Neurosci Bull</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12264-013-1381-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N'Drin</surname><given-names>AYA</given-names></name></person-group><source>S&#x000e9;curisation du circuit du m&#x000e9;dicament en milieu hospitalier: exp&#x000e9;rience dans les accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Allaoui A, Echchilali K, Moudatir M, Alaoui FZ, Elkabli H. Etiologies des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques chez les jeunes: apport de l&#x02019;interniste. Pan Afr Med J. 2018;30.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haut commissariat au Plan-Maroc. Recensement g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;ral de la population et de l'habitat; 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talbi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Khadmaoui</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soulaymani</surname><given-names>AE-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chafik</surname><given-names>AE-A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etude de la consanguinit&#x000e9; dans la population marocaine. Impact sur le profil de la sant&#x000e9;</article-title><source>Antropo</source><year>2007</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecoffre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>de Peretti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimaud</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Woimant</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Giroud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>L&#x02019;accident vasculaire c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral en France: patients hospitalis&#x000e9;s pour AVC en 2014 et &#x000e9;volutions 2008-2014</article-title><source>Bull Epid&#x000e9;miol Hebd</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>94</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benbekhti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Henaoui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Meguenni</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux au centre hospitalier universitaire de Tlemcen, Alg&#x000e9;rie</article-title><source>Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique</source><year>2016</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>S240</fpage><lpage>S241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.respe.2016.06.266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kefi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Larbi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouni</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bougacha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouslama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamzaoui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>M'rad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Young ischemic stroke in Tunisia: a multicentric study</article-title><source>Int J Neurosci</source><year>2017</year><volume>127</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>314</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00207454.2016.1214131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27426935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27426935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>FY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors of young ischemic stroke in Qatar</article-title><source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source><year>2007</year><volume>109</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>773</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clineuro.2007.07.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17719720?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17719720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Rukn S, Mazya M, Akhtar N, Hashim H, Mansouri B, Faouzi B, Aref H, Abdulrahman H, Kesraoui S, Hentati F. Stroke in the middle-east and North Africa: a 2-year prospective observational study of intravenous thrombolysis treatment in the region. Results from the SITS-MENA registry. Int J Stroke. 2019:1747493019874729.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boutayeb</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Derouich</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutayeb</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamlili</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Cerebrovascular diseases and associated risk factors in WHO eastern Mediterranean countries</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Hajj</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salameh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rachidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosseini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of stroke in the Middle East</article-title><source>Eur Stroke J</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>180</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2396987316654338</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 31008279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31008279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sztajzel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Devuyst</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>L&#x02019;accident vasculaire c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral chez la femme</article-title><source>Rev Med Suisse</source><year>2002</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>22170</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mensah</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of stroke and high blood pressure in Africa</article-title><source>Heart</source><year>2008</year><volume>94</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>697</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/hrt.2007.127753</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18308869?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18308869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allali</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution des pratiques alimentaires au Maroc</article-title><source>Int J Med Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>70</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Kardi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Anide</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Derouiche</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Composition en sodium et en acides gras satur&#x000e9;s et trans dans six type de fast foods au Maroc</article-title><source>Nutr Clin M&#x000e9;tab</source><year>2017</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>82</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nupar.2016.10.123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nejjari</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arharbi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chentir</surname><given-names>M-T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boujnah</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kemmou</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Megdiche</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulahrouf</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Messoussi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazek</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bulatov</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiological trial of hypertension in North Africa (ETHNA): an international multicentre study in Algeria, Morocco and Tunisia</article-title><source>J Hypertens</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23221932?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23221932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Minist&#x000e8;re de la sant&#x000e9; DdlPedRF, Division de la Planification et des Etudes, Service des Etudes et de l&#x02019;Information Sanitaire: Sant&#x000e9; en chiffre. 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillum</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mamidipudi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ischemic stroke risk with oral contraceptives: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2000</year><volume>284</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.284.1.72</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10872016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MTHFR C677T mutation increased the risk of ischemic stroke, especially in large-artery atherosclerosis in adults: an updated meta-analysis from 38 researches</article-title><source>Int J Neurosci</source><year>2016</year><volume>126</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/00207454.2014.990559</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25453894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25453894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between endothelial nitric oxide synthase gene polymorphisms and ischemic stroke: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Acta Neurol Scand</source><year>2013</year><volume>128</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ane.12120</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23560937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23560937</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between T-1131C polymorphism of apolipoprotein A5 and cerebral infarction in Chinese Han population in Hunan</article-title><source>J Apoplexy Nerv Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>533</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domingues-Montanari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Cadenas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>del Rio-Espinola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbeto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Krug</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Manso</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouveia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobral</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendioroz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Morales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Association of a genetic variant in the ALOX5AP with higher risk of ischemic stroke: a case-control, meta-analysis and functional study</article-title><source>Cerebrovasc Dis</source><year>2010</year><volume>29</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000302738</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20357438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20357438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Direction de la l'Epid&#x000e9;miologie et de Lutte contre les Maladies MdlsdM: Enqu&#x000ea;te nationale sur les Facteurs de Risque communs des Maladies Non Transmissibles 2017&#x02013;2018. In<italic>.</italic>; 2019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larrue</surname><given-names>VJR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traitement thrombolytique de l&#x002c8;accident isch&#x000e9;mique c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral</article-title><source>R&#x000e9;animation</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>392</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1164-6756(01)00130-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urimubenshi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadilhac</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kagwiza</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Langhorne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke care in Africa: a systematic review of the literature</article-title><source>Int J Stroke</source><year>2018</year><volume>13</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1747493018772747</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29664359?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29664359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ossou-Nguiet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gombet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ossil-Ampion</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellenga-Mbolla</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Otiobanda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahoungou-Guimbi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandzouzi-Ndamba</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Facteurs de mortalit&#x000e9; des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux au CHU de Brazzaville</article-title><source>RAMUR</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>19</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemaa</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Slamia</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammouchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Benammou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>D&#x000e9;lais de prise en charge des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux: Exp&#x000e9;rience de la r&#x000e9;gion du centre tunisien</article-title><source>Presse Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1502</fpage><lpage>1503</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lpm.2008.05.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18653308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18653308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Mesbahy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chraa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000c9;valuation des connaissances de la population sur les facteurs de risque et les signes d&#x02019;alerte de l&#x02019;infarctus c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;bral: enqu&#x000ea;te &#x000e0; Marrakech</article-title><source>Rev Neurol</source><year>2017</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>S163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurol.2017.01.307</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>RMG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bermejo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>&#x000c1;A</given-names></name><name><surname>del Saz</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Arroyo</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Manero</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response to symptoms and prehospital delay in stroke patients. Is it time to reconsider stroke awareness campaigns?</article-title><source>J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</source><year>2018</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2017.09.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29108809</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khatib</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Arevalo</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berendsen</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhakaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Huffman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presentation, evaluation, management, and outcomes of acute stroke in low-and middle-income countries: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Neuroepidemiology</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><issue>1&#x02013;2</issue><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000491442</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30025394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30025394</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellalem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amroune</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Amiri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayadi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G-9 &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologie des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux isch&#x000e9;miques et classification des sous-types selon les crit&#x000e8;res TOAST &#x000e0; S&#x000e9;tif en Alg&#x000e9;rie</article-title><source>Rev Neurol</source><year>2007</year><volume>163</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>18</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0035-3787(07)90515-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tour&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawadogo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Basse</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Diagne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Diop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaye</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Diop</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cisse</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Seck</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mortalit&#x000e9; des patients hospitalis&#x000e9;s pour AVC isch&#x000e9;mique en neurologie au CHU de Fann &#x000e0; Dakar</article-title><source>NPG Neurol Psychiatr G&#x000e9;riatr</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>100</issue><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.npg.2016.11.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balogou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guinhouya</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Belo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x000c9;pid&#x000e9;miologie des accidents vasculaires c&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;braux en Afrique subsaharienne</article-title><source>Rev Neurol</source><year>2013</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>A244</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neurol.2013.01.611</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rukn</surname><given-names>Suhail Al</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazya</surname><given-names>Michael V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentati</surname><given-names>Faycal</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassi</surname><given-names>Samia Ben</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabli</surname><given-names>Fatma</given-names></name><name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>Zakharia</given-names></name><name><surname>Faouzi</surname><given-names>Belahsen</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>Husnain</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd-Allah</surname><given-names>Foad</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansouri</surname><given-names>Benhan</given-names></name><name><surname>Kesraoui</surname><given-names>Selma</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebeily</surname><given-names>Souheil</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulrahman</surname><given-names>Husen</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhtar</surname><given-names>Naveed</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>Niaz</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahlgren</surname><given-names>Nils</given-names></name><name><surname>Aref</surname><given-names>Hany</given-names></name><name><surname>Almekhlafi</surname><given-names>Mohammed</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>Tiago</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stroke in the Middle-East and North Africa: A 2-year prospective observational study of stroke characteristics in the region&#x02014;Results from the Safe Implementation of Treatments in Stroke (SITS)&#x02013;Middle-East and North African (MENA)</article-title><source>International Journal of Stroke</source><year>2019</year><volume>14</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1747493019830331</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30860454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30860454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>GDJS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue plasminogen activator for acute ischemic stroke in clinical practice: a meta-analysis of safety data</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2003</year><volume>34</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>2847</fpage><lpage>2850</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.STR.0000101752.23813.C3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14605319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14605319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Alaoui</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Les accidents vasculaires au Maroc : R&#x000e9;sultats et enseignements d&#x02019;une enqu&#x000ea;te &#x000e9;pid&#x000e9;miologique. Bulletin d'information de l'acad&#x000e9;mie Hassan II des sciences et techniques</source><year>2013</year><fpage>53</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>