<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Neurol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-2295</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6384232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fneur.2019.00114</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Neurology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Pain Catastrophizing in Childhood Migraine: An Observational Study in a Tertiary Headache Center</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sciruicchio</surname><given-names>Vittorio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/662636/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simeone</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foschino Barbaro</surname><given-names>Maria Grazia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanzi</surname><given-names>Roberta Caterina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Delussi</surname><given-names>Marianna D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Libro</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>D'Agnano</surname><given-names>Daniela</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Basiliana</surname><given-names>Roberta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Tommaso</surname><given-names>Marina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/131386/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Children Epilepsy and EEG Center</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Associazione Italiana di Psicoterapia Cognitiva S.r.l (AIPC)</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Psychological Pediatric Service, Policlinico General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Applied Neurophysiology and Pain Unit, Basic Medical, Neuroscience and Sensory System Department, Policlinico General Hospital, Bari Aldo Moro University</institution>, <addr-line>Bari</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Massimiliano Valeriani, Bambino Ges&#x000f9; Children Hospital (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Marco Carotenuto, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi della Campania Luigi Vanvitelli Caserta, Italy; Ishaq Abu-Arafeh, Royal Hospital for Sick Children, United Kingdom; Romina Moavero, Bambino Ges&#x000f9; Children Hospital (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Marina de Tommaso <email>marina.detommaso@uniba.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Headache Medicine and Facial Pain, a section of the journal Frontiers in Neurology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>114</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 Sciruicchio, Simeone, Foschino Barbaro, Tanzi, Delussi, Libro, D'Agnano, Basiliana and de Tommaso.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sciruicchio, Simeone, Foschino Barbaro, Tanzi, Delussi, Libro, D'Agnano, Basiliana and de Tommaso</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Background:</bold> Migraine is the most common cause of primary headache in children leading to a decrease in the quality of life. During the last decade, pain catastrophizing construct became a major focus of interest in the study and treatment of pain.</p><p><bold>Aim of the study:</bold>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To evaluate pain catastrophizing in episodic and chronic migraine children and adolescents selected in a tertiary headache Center.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To test whether the children's pain catastrophizing might be associated (a) with the frequency of attacks and disability (b) with psychopathological aspects (c) with allodynia and total tenderness score as symptom of central sensitization.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To test the best discriminating clinical variables and scores between episodic and chronic migraine, including pain catastrophizing.</p></list-item></list></p><p><bold>Methods:</bold> We conducted a cross sectional observational study on consecutive pediatric patients affected by migraine. We selected 190 headache patients who met the diagnostic criteria for Migraine without aura, Migraine with aura and Chronic migraine. We submitted all children to the Child version of the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS-C), and to the disability scale for migraine (PedMIDAS), general quality of life estimated by children (PedsQL) and parents (PedsQL-P), anxiety and depression (SAFA-A; SAFA-D) scales. We also evaluated headache frequency and the presence and severity of allodynia and pericranial tenderness.</p><p><bold>Results:</bold> No difference was detected in Total Pain Catastrophizing score (PCS-C) between chronic and episodic migraine groups (ANOVA <italic>F</italic> = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> = 0.70); the PedMIDAS, the PedsQL-P for physical functioning and the Total Tenderness Score were discriminant variables between episodic and chronic migraine. The PCS-C was not correlated with migraine related disability as expressed by Ped MIDAS, but it was significantly correlated with general low quality of life, allodynia, pericranial tenderness, anxiety, and depression.</p><p><bold>Conclusion:</bold> Pain catastrophizing seems a mental characteristic of a clinical phenotype with psychopathological traits and enhanced expression of central sensitization symptoms. This clinical profile causes general decline in quality of life in the child judgment, with a probable parents' underestimation. In childhood age, it would not be a feature of chronic migraine, but the possibility that it could predict this evolution is consistent and worthy of further prospective evaluation.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>migraine</kwd><kwd>children</kwd><kwd>pain catastrophizing</kwd><kwd>allodynia</kwd><kwd>pericranial tenderness</kwd><kwd>central sensitization</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Universita degli Studi di Bari Aldo Moro<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100005362</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="41"/><page-count count="8"/><word-count count="5866"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Migraine is the most common cause of primary headache in children leading to a decrease in the quality of life (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Chronic migraine affects 0.8&#x02013;1.8% of adolescents and 0.6% of children and it is a common reason for pediatric patients to seek medical care (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Consequently, this age group demands special attention. A better understanding of specific pain mechanisms, disease progression, and potential complications in childhood migraine allows the development of more specific and more efficient ways of prevention and therapy. Nowadays, the most important recognized factors associated to chronic migraine are obesity, depression, presence of allodynia, and stressful life events (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>).</p><p>During the last decade, pain catastrophizing construct became a major focus of interest in the study and treatment of pain. Pain catastrophizing is a negative cognitive-affective response to anticipated or actual pain. More recently, Flink et al. argued that it is a form of negative repetitive thinking, difficult to disengage from, with reduced capacity in problem solving and downregulation of negative affect. It is a complex process involving cognitions, emotions, and behavior, linked to poor outcomes such as higher ratings of pain and disability (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Pain catastrophizing could be a model to explain the processes of transitions to a chronic state during childhood and adolescence. Describing pain catastrophizing could thus enable to individuate cases with possible negative evolution and multiple psychological and cognitive features. In a validation study of Fear of Pain Questionnaire (FOPQ) in a pediatric headache sample, an association between pain catastrophizing and Fear of Pain emerged (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Pain catastrophizing is associated with a number of indices of pain sensitivity in experimental settings including healthy pain-free participants and individuals with various chronic pain conditions (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). In particular, one of the most consistent findings was the correlation between pain catastrophizing and heightened pain experience (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). The literature also indicates consistent and generally robust associations between pain catastrophizing and measures of clinical pain severity, pain-related activity interference, disability, depression and quality of life (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Thanks to the development of a pediatric version of the Pain Catastrophizing Scale (PCS-C) (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>), the interest in pain catastrophizing in the pediatric area is progressively going into increase. Several studies found significant positive associations between PCS-C reports and pain intensity, disability (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), and anxiety ratings (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). The PCS-C items describe different thoughts and feelings that children may experience when they are in pain, using a total score and three subscale scores for rumination, magnification, and helplessness (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). It showed consistency across different children populations. In a German study on children with recurrent pain and specifically headache, pain catastrophizing showed significant association with anxiety, pain severity and disability (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>).</p><p>In a recent neurophysiological study on children migraine, we observed a correlation between pain catastrophizing and allodynia, which is a symptom of central sensitization (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>).</p><p>In order to better understand some of the precipitating and aggravating factors of migraine in pediatric patients, the present cross-sectional observational study aimed:</p><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>To evaluate pain catastrophizing in episodic and chronic migraine children and adolescents selected in a tertiary headache Center.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To test whether the children's pain catastrophizing might be associated a) with the frequency of attacks and headache related and general disability b) with psychopathological aspects as anxiety and depression c) with allodynia and total tenderness score as symptom of central sensitization.</p></list-item><list-item><p>To test the best discriminating clinical variables and scores between episodic and chronic migraine, including pain catastrophizing.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>We conducted a cross sectional observational study on consecutive pediatric patients affected by primary headache and referred to the Applied Neurophysiology and Pain Unit of Bari University.</p><p>Among the 500 consecutive pediatric patients come for the first time to the Applied Neurophysiology and Pain unit between January 2017 and January 2018, we selected 190 headache patients who met the diagnostic criteria for Migraine without aura, Migraine with aura and Chronic migraine, according to the actual International Classification of Headache Disorders (Headache Classification Committee) (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Diagnosis was based on history and the headache diaries (see below). Exclusion criteria included the presence of another neurological diagnosis, or psychiatric and medical comorbidities. None of the children was under current use of preventive treatments or other psychotropic medications, at the time of the study.</p><sec><title>Data Collection</title><p>Upon the first access to the booking desk, the hospital staff gave parents the headache diary and the questionnaire of allodynia in the adult version. All parents and patients were invited to fill the headache and allodynia diary for 3 months, and to present it at their first visit date. We decided to include only patients at their first access to our Unit, because one exclusion criteria was the use of preventive treatment for migraine, which we generally suggest during the first visit.</p></sec><sec><title>Clinical Evaluation</title><p>We supposed the frequency of the headache from the diaries. Based on the frequency reported, patients were divided into four categories of frequencies (1&#x02013;4; 5&#x02013;9; 10&#x02013;14; 15&#x02013;30 days/month).</p><p>A team of neurologists and psychologists with experience in headache evaluated the patients and considered the headache and allodynia diaries. One psychologist administered the anxiety and depression scales, the disability scales and pain catastrophizing questionnaires. All children were examined during the not symptomatic phase.</p><p>The study was approved by the local Ethic Committee of Bari Policlinico General Hospital. Parents and children were informed about the details of the study procedure and parents signed an informed consent prior to the enrolment, in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Measures and Procedures</title><sec><title>Child Version of the Pain Catastrophizing Scale</title><p>The PCS-C is a 13-item self-report measure designed to assess the extent to which children and adolescents experience catastrophic thoughts and feelings when in pain. Items are responded to on a 5-point scale ranging from zero (not at all) to four (extremely). Higher scores indicate more frequent catastrophic pain beliefs (scores range from 0 to 52). The PCS-C assesses three catastrophizing domains: Rumination (i.e., &#x0201c;I cannot keep it out of my mind&#x0201d;), Magnification (i.e., &#x0201c;I am afraid that pain will get worse&#x0201d;), and Helplessness (i.e., &#x0201c;There is nothing I can do to reduce pain&#x0201d;). The original version of measure was adapted from the adult PCS for use with Flemish-speaking children and adolescents. It demonstrated good reliability (total scale a = 0.87, rumination a = 0.73, magnification a = 0.68, helplessness a = 0.79), predictive validity, and invariance across age and sex among Flemish-speaking children and adolescents. The English language version of this measure was validated in a community sample of children (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>) and a clinical sample of youth with chronic pain (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). In this study, we used an Italian language version of the PCS-C, translated with the agreement of Geert Crombez, according to the back-translation method (Simeone et al. in preparation). Briefly, the instrument was translated in English by an independent professional native English translator, who had no knowledge of the questionnaire. Only a few discrepancies arose, which the expert panel discussed until a satisfactory version was reached. The total score of this translated version showed high internal consistency (a = 0.9).</p></sec><sec><title>Psychiatric Self-Administration Scales for Youths and Adolescents</title><p>Psychiatric Self-Administration Scales for Youths and Adolescents (SAFA) (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The SAFA is an Italian standardized battery which includes six self-report scales for the assessment of a wide range of psychiatric symptoms according to the DSM IV-TR diagnostic criteria. They can be used together or separately with satisfactory psychometric properties (reliability by internal consistency and test&#x02013;retest; convergent, discriminant, and content validity) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.giuntios.it/catalogo/test/safa">https://www.giuntios.it/catalogo/test/safa</ext-link>). In the present study, we used the anxiety (SAFA A) and depression (SAFA D) scales that includes two or three versions, each tailored for a specific age range. All items rates are on a three-point scale (two = &#x0201c;true,&#x0201d; one = &#x0201c;partly true,&#x0201d; and zero = &#x0201c;false&#x0201d;). The SAFA-A evaluates generalized, social and separation anxiety and anxiety related to the school. The SAFA-D measures depressed mood, anhedonia, disinterest; irritable mood, feelings of inadequacy, low self-esteem, insecurity, guilt, hopelessness.</p></sec><sec><title>Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory</title><p>The Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory <bold>(</bold>PQL<bold>)</bold> and the modules developed for various diseases assess health-related quality of life in healthy children and adolescents, as well as p<italic><bold>e</bold></italic>diatric patients with acute or chronic conditions. They combine into a single system several generic scales and modules for specific diseases (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). In the present study, we used the PQL 4.0 Generic Core Scales, both in the self-report form and in the parent proxy-report form. The PQL 4.0 Generic Core Scales include 23 items self-report form about physical functioning (eight items), emotional functioning (five items), social functioning (five items), school functioning (five items). Child self-report format includes ages 5&#x02013;7 (young child), 8&#x02013;12 (child), and 13&#x02013;18 (adolescent). The instrument instructions ask to score each item, taking into consideration the last month. The choice of answer for each item is on a 5-point Likert scale: zero = never a problem, one = almost never a problem, two = sometimes a problem, three = often a problem, four = almost often a problem). For self-reports by children 5&#x02013;7 years old, the Likert scale included 3-points (zero = not a problem at all; two = sometimes a problem; four = a great problem), each choice of response being attached to a happy-sad faces scale.</p><p>The parent proxy report (PedParQL) also includes ages 2&#x02013;4 (toddlers), 5&#x02013;7 (younger children), 8&#x02013;12 (children), and 13&#x02013;18 (teens). The two forms, for children and parents, are parallel, providing for an indication of the child's and the parent's perception. The instrument instructions ask how frequently a problem was present during the past 1 month. In the present study, we considered the PedsQL and PedParQL total scores, Physical functioning (PedsQLP, PedParQLP) and Emotional functioning (PedsQLE, PedParQLE) sub scores (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Pediatric Migraine Disability Assessment</title><p>Pediatric Migraine Disability Assessment Scale (PedMIDAS) is a measure for migraine related disability in children and adolescents. The PedMIDAS is based on the adult MIDAS with developmentally appropriate changes and adjustments for childhood lifestyle. The first three questions are about the impact of headache at school: question 1 asks about school day absences; question 2 asks about partial day absences; and question 3 asks about functioning at 50% or less ability in school. The fourth question assesses the impact due to headache at home and includes inability to perform homework and chores. The final two questions assess disability in social functioning including sports; question 5 asks about complete absence from activities, while question 6 asks about functioning at 50% or less of their ability. A raw score is obtained by adding the six individual questions (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Allodynia Questionnaire</title><p>According to previous studies (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>), we used the same allodynia questionnaire employed for adults, consisting of the symptom's checklist reported by Lipton et al. (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). We asked mothers to interview their children during migraine attack, in order to help them in filling the allodynia questionnaire for each migraine attack. The allodynia questionnaire is not presently adapted for children, so we suggested the parents to indicate as &#x0201c;not applicable&#x0201d; those questions specific to adults (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). We classified patients as allodynic based on the presence of at least one symptom reported in the questionnaire in over the 50% of the headache episodes. Furthermore, for the allodynia severity, the average number of allodynia symptoms across different attacks was considered.</p></sec><sec><title>Total Tenderness Score</title><p>We measure the pericranial tenderness, using the scale validated by Langermak and Olesen (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), and employed in childhood headaches (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>We summarized the quantitative continuous and categorical variables, age and sex, in the main migraine subgroups, and used the ANOVA test and chi square test to compare them among groups.</p><p>To satisfy the aim 1), taking into consideration the distribution of cases in the main migraine subgroups, we divided children in episodic and chronic migraine groups (EM and CM), merging the groups including migraine with aura and without aura in a sole group. Data were analyzed by Levene test for equality of variance, which was not significant for any of the considered variables. The Student's <italic>t</italic>-test for non-paired data was used to compare the Total PCS and the sub-items between groups.</p><p>To satisfy the aim 2) we applied the Person correlation test and curve estimation using the linear regression test, between PCS-C total and sub-items and main clinical features. Considering the number of correlations, we took into consideration only those exceeding the 0.01 significance level. We also used a one way ANOVA model and the <italic>post-hoc</italic> Bonferroni, to check for total PCS-C and sub-items differences among headache frequencies categories.</p><p>To satisfy the aim 3, we run out a step-wise discriminant analysis between chronic and episodic migraine, using the Mahalanobis distance, and <italic>F</italic> value 0.05 and 0.1 respectively as inclusion and exclusion factor.</p><p>The variables introduced into analysis were PedMIDAS, TTS, allodynia, SAFA-A, SAFA-D, PQL-ad, PQL-P, and total PCS-S.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Demographic data of selected patients are reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The most of patients were diagnosed as episodic migraine without aura &#x02013;MO. Patients with migraine with aura were older than were patients with migraine without aura. Females prevailed in all but the MA group, though in a not significant way (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In the Supplementary table, the details of clinical features and PCS-C sub-items in Episodic and Chronic Migraine are reported (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1S</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic data of migraine patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>age (years)</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>sex F</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>M</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11,89</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MO</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MA/MO</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANOVA df 3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chi square df 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> = 5.2, <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.002</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.21 n.s</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bonferroni MA VS. MO <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>MA, Migraine With Aura; MO, Migraine Without Aura; CM, Chronic Migraine; MA/MO, Migraine with aura associated to Migraine without aura</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Aim 1: Total Pain catastrophizing score was similar between chronic and episodic migraine groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Mean and 95% confidence intervals of total pain catastrophizing test (PCS-C) and main sub-items in the migraine chronic and episodic subgroups. Total PCS-S Student's <italic>t</italic>-test 1.24, <italic>p</italic> = 0.2; rumination, <italic>t</italic> = 0.49, <italic>p</italic> = 0.62; magnification, <italic>t</italic> = 1.71, <italic>p</italic> = 0.088; helplessness <italic>t</italic> = 0.36, <italic>p</italic> = 0.33.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneur-10-00114-g0001"/></fig><p>Aim 2: Total Pain Catastrophizing and sub-items did not correlate with Migraine related disability as expressed by Ped MIDAS, but a significant correlation was present with general low quality of life, both for physical and psychological functioning, as judged by children, allodynia, pericranial tenderness, anxiety, and depression (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). Some correlations showed a low statistical significance, as for the sub-items Rumination and Magnification and the parents' quality of life scores (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Pearson correlation test among Pain Catastrophyzing Total Scale (PCS-S) and main sub-items, and clinical features evaluated in 190 migraine patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>TTS</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ALLODYNIA</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PedMIDAS</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL-PHY</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL-PSY</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL-P</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL-P-PHY</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>PEDS-QL-P-PSY</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SAFAA_TOT</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SAFAD_TOT</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCS-S</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.210**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.243**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.380**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.0262**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.385**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.492**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.475**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sig</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rumination</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.229**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.163*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.197**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.292**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.259**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sig</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnification</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.181*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.190**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.384**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.229**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.448**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.177*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.183**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.539**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.516**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sig</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Helplessness</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pearson correlation</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.171*</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.230**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.337**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.252**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.331**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.419**</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.425**</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sig</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&#x0003c;0.0001</bold></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>The mean and standard deviations of single items are reported in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Table 1S</xref></italic>.</p><p><italic>TTS, Total Tendenrness Score; PedMIDAS, Pediatric Migraine Disability Scale-MIDAS; PEDS-QL, Pediatric Quality of Life; PEDS-QL-Phy, Physical functioning of PED-QL; PEDS-QL-Psy, Psychological functioning of PED-QL; PEDS-QL-P, Pediatric Quality of Life for Parents; PEDS-QL-P-Phy, Pediatric Quality of Life for Parents Physical functioning; PEDS-QL-P-Psy, Pediatric Quality of Life for Parents Psychological functioning; SAFA-A, Psychiatric Self-Administration Scales for Youths and Adolescents-Amxiety; SAFA-D, Psychiatric Self-Administration Scales for Youths and Adolescents-Depression</italic>.</p><p><italic>Significant p values are reported in bold</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Linear regression analysis curve estimation between Total Pain Catastrophizing Score (PCS-S) and main clinical variables as Quality of Life (PQL), Pediatric MIDAS (PedMIDAS), allodynia, total tenderness score and anxiety, and depression scale (SAFA-A; SAFA-D). Observed cases and linear trends are reported. The power curve is reported in the most significant relationships. ANOVA results, SAFA-A <italic>F</italic> = 42.61, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001; SAFA-D, <italic>F</italic> = 54.8, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001; PedMIDAS <italic>F</italic> = 0.002, <italic>p</italic> = 0.96; PQL, <italic>F</italic> = 28.31, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001; allodynia <italic>F</italic> = 2.27, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.025; Total Tenderness Score <italic>F</italic> = 2.34, <italic>p</italic> = 0.021.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fneur-10-00114-g0002"/></fig><p>The total PCS-S was similar among the different frequencies groups (ANOVA <italic>F</italic> = 0.59, <italic>p</italic> = 0.70).</p><p>Aim 3: The stepwise discriminant analysis allowed selecting the discriminant variables between episodic and chronic migraine, which were the PedMIDAS, the PQL-P for physical functioning and the TTS (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). These variables discriminated between episodic and chronic migraine with 73, 2% accuracy.</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Discriminant variables between Episodic (EM) and Chronic (CM) childhood migraine.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="6" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold>EM</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><bold>CM</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" style="background-color:#bbbdc0;" rowspan="1"><bold>FISCHER DISCRIMINANT LINEAR FUNCTION</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ped-MIDAS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.107</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PQL-P physical fun</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.285</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.255</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TTS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">0.164</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.266</td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Constant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">&#x02212;12.943</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02212;11.884</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Diagnosis</bold></td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>classification</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total</bold></td></tr><tr style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>EM</bold></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>CM</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;Cases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EM</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;%</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EM</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CM</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">73.2% of cases correclty classified</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The general impression emerging from the present results is that Pain Catastrophizing seems an important aspect of children with headache, associated with psychopathological features, general reduction of quality of life and central sensitization symptoms. However, it does not distinguish chronic from episodic migraine in children, similarly to anxiety, depression and general disability. Children with frequent migraine differ from episodic ones for those clinical aspects, which seem intrinsic to head pain, as disability linked to migraine, pericranial tenderness and physical functions decline. In the following paragraph, we report the detailed discussion of single points.</p><sec><title>Pain Catastrophizing Is Not Associated With Chronic Migraine</title><p>The first hypothesis of the study was negative, as this aspect of pain feeling was similar among children with different headache frequencies. More than 20 years ago, Lefebvre et al. studied 252 young subjects to determine the internal reliability of the Coping Strategies Questionnaire. Subjects reporting higher levels of catastrophizing presented with higher levels of pain and higher frequency of both migraine headaches and low back pain (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>More recent studies in adult migraine, confirmed that pain catastrophizing is associated with more severe and frequent migraine attacks, and that it could be a risk factor for chronic migraine (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>The results of Orr et al study on pediatric migraine (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>), confirmed what we observed, that pain catastrophizing was not associated to migraine related disability, but was a negative factor for quality of life.</p><p>Structural and functional MRI study, demonstrated that pain catastrophizing as single aspect of migraine, was negatively associated with gray matter volume in areas implicated in processing the sensory, affective, and cognitive aspects of pain in patients, and with disrupted connectivity between default mode, salience, cognitive, visuospatial, and sensorimotor networks (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>).</p><p>Overall, the exaggerated negative mental disposition toward pain and anticipated pain experience may be an intrinsic feature of migraine patients who could prospectively develop severe migraine.</p></sec><sec><title>Correlation Between Pain Catastrophizing and Main Clinical and Psychopathological Variable and Central Sensitization Symptoms</title><p>In accord with the similarity of PCS-C values between episodic and chronic migraine, pain catastrophizing did not correlate with disability linked to migraine, but it correlated with general low quality of life. The reason may be in the positive association between this mental set and anxiety and depression levels, which was well-described in adult migraine (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p><p>This association is also present in children with other forms of chronic pain (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>). The increase in pain catastrophizing could thus summarize a clinical phenotype characterized by anxiety, depression and a mental status of hyper-estimation of pain experience, which is causative for poor quality of life. It is conceivable that such clinical phenotype could present with an abnormal function within cognitive and emotional network (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). This cortical network could partly correspond to the so-called salience matrix, which is fundamental in the processing of pain experiences (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), being modified in adult migraine patients (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). In fact, we observed that pain catastrophizing correlated positively with allodynia and pericranial tenderness, which are symptoms of central sensitization. The predisposition to develop central sensitization phenomena was associated with psychopathological factors and pain catastrophizing in adult patients with muscle skeletal pain (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). At the time of the present evaluation, children sharing this clinical phenotype were not chronic migraneurs, but further prospective studies could clarify if this mental trait could be predictive of chronic evolution. These children, however, presented with a poor quality of life, and low physical and psychological functioning, that could suggest that this clinical phenotype is disabling <italic>per se</italic>, independently from the severity of migraine. Parents seemed not sentient of this frailty, as they generally tended to attribute the reduction of quality of life to migraine severity and perceived the poor quality of life of children with chronic, but not episodic migraine. The tendency to pain amplification, associated to anxiety and depression tracts, could thus be underestimated in parents' consideration, at least as a cause of low quality of life. There was a mild correlation between PCS sub-items, as rumination and magnification, and children quality of life as judged by parents, who probably advise the distress caused by some traits of this mental behavior.</p></sec><sec><title>Discriminating Factors Between Chronic and Episodic Migraine</title><p>The discriminant analysis confirmed that in our children sample, pain catastrophizing, and associated psychopathological features were not distinguishing factors between episodic and chronic forms, while clinical factors directly associated to migraine, as disability linked to headache frequency, and the general decline in physical functioning in the parents' judgment, distinguished with discrete accuracy episodic from chronic forms. Pericranial tenderness was the other discriminating factor, because persistent muscle pain characterizes chronic migraine in adult and childhood age (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>). In previous studies on juvenile cohorts, obesity, depression, presence of allodynia and stressful life events were risk factors for chronic pain (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Pain catastrophizing could summarize a mental behavior predisposing to evolution into chronic migraine, which seems underestimated in parents consideration and worthy of further evaluation in prospective studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Study Limitation</title><p>The Italian PCS-C scale has not been presently validated in children, though this study could be considered preliminary to the final publication of the translated version, obtained with the agreement of Geert Crombez, according to the back-translation method [Simeone et al, in preparation; (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>)]. The other clinical scales and assessments, as allodynia and pericranial tenderness, were originally applied in adult migraine, and some changes in children and adolescents could exist (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). However, all symptoms reported in the classification could appear phenotypically modified in infantile age (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), possibly requiring adjunctive notes and changes to the criteria provided for adult migraine (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>).</p><p>Another important limit relies in data referring to a selected patients group of a tertiary headache center, and not to general population. The episodic migraine children, who requests for headache specialist's visit, could in some way express a psychological frailty predisposing to chronic evolution, so the generalization of present results to the wider population of children with migraine needs to be confirmed.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Pain catastrophizing seems a mental characteristic of a clinical phenotype including psychopathological traits and enhanced expression of central sensitization symptoms. This clinical profile causes general decline in quality of life in the child judgment, with a probable parents' underestimation. In childhood age, it would not be a feature of chronic migraine, but the possibility that it could predict this evolution is consistent and worthy of further prospective evaluation.</p><p>The utility of this easy evaluation in the clinical setting of children migraine seems highly supported by present results.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>MdT: study design and coordination, statistical analysis, manuscript editing. VS: manuscript preparation, clinical data collection. MS: manuscript preparation, psychological assessment. DD: manuscript editing. GL, RB, and MD: clinical data collection, data entry. MF: psychological assessment. RCT: manuscript preparation and editing. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> The study was supported by Bari Aldo Moro research funds.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2019.00114/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fneur.2019.00114/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozge</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sa&#x0015f;maz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bugdayci</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakmak</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurt</surname><given-names>A&#x000d6;</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaleagasi</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The prevalence of chronic and episodic migraine in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Eur J Neurol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-1331.2012.03795.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22882205?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22882205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelfand</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Migraine and childhood periodic syndromes in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Neurol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>262</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/WCO.0b013e32836085c7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23549418?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23549418</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McKillop</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Banez</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Broad consideration of risk factors in pediatric chronic pain: where to go from here?</article-title>
<source>Children</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>E38</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/children3040038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27916884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27916884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flink</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boersma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain catastrophizing as repetitive negative thinking: a development of the conceptualization</article-title>. <source>Cogn Behav Ther</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/16506073.2013.769621</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23978106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23978106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pielech</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cappucci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fear of pain in pediatric headache</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102414534084</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24812036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24812036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Haythornthwaite</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Theoretical perspectives on the relation between pain catastrophizing and pain</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002508-200103000-00008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11289089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11289089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>CO</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Bathon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haythornthwaite</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Catastrophizing and pain in arthritis, fibromyalgia and other rheumatic disease</article-title>. <source>Arthritis Rheum.</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.21865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16583384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quartana</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain catastrophizing: a critical review</article-title>. <source>Expert Rev Neurother</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/ern.09.34</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19402782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19402782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain catastrophizing: an updated review</article-title>. <source>Indian J Psychol Med</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0253-7176.106012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23441031?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23441031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crombez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bijttebier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eccleston</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascagni</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mertens</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goubert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The child version of the pain catastrophizing scale (PCS-C): a preliminary validation</article-title>. <source>Pain</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13072/midss.212</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12927636?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12927636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pielech</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczynski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Pain catastrophizing in children with chronic pain and their parents: proposed clinical reference points and reexamination of the PCS measure</article-title>. <source>Pain</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>155</volume>:<fpage>2360</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2014.08.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25180013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaulieu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crombez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalibert&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thibault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Pain catastrophizing scale for francophone adolescents: a preliminary validation</article-title>. <source>Pain Res Manag</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2008/845674</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18301812?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18301812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kr&#x000f6;ner-Herwig</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Maas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The GERMAN Pain Catastrophizing Scale for Children (PCS-C) &#x02013; psychometric analysis and evaluation of the construct</article-title>. <source>J Psychosoc Med</source>. (<year>2013</year>) 10:Doc07. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3205/psm000097</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23922617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23922617</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Tommaso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciruicchio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Delussi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Goffredo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Simeone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Symptoms of central sensitization and comorbidity for juvenile fibromyalgia in childhood migraine: an observational study in a tertiary headache center</article-title>. <source>J Headache Pain</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s10194-017-0764-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28560539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Headache Classification Committee of the International Headache Society (IHS) The international classification of headache disorders</collab></person-group>, <edition>3rd edition</edition>
<source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102413485658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cianchetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sannio Fancello</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Scale Psichiatriche di Autosomministrazione per Fanciulli e Adolescenti (SAFA) [Psychiatric Self Administration Scales for Youths and Adolescents (SAFA)]</source>. <publisher-loc>Firenze</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Giunti O.S</publisher-name> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varni</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Seid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rode</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The PedsQL: measurement model for the pediatric quality of life inventory</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source> (<year>1999</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10024117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10024117</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trapanotto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giorgino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zulian</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Benini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Varni</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Italian version of the PedsQL in children with rheumatic diseases</article-title>. <source>Clin Exp Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2009</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 19473585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Grazzi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Usai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrasik</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Leone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigamonti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Use of the migraine disability assessment questionnaire in children and adolescents with headache: an Italian pilot study</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2003</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1526-4610.2003.03134</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12890131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12890131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hershey</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vockell</surname><given-names>ALB</given-names></name><name><surname>LeCates</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabbouche</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Maynard</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>PedMIDAS: development of a questionnaire to assess disability of migraines in children</article-title>. <source>Neurology</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>2034</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.57.11.2034</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11739822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11739822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Tommaso</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sciruicchio</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricci</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Montemurno</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gentile</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecchio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Laser-evoked potential habituation and central sensitization symptoms in childhood migraine</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102415597527</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26232104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26232104</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigal</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Silberstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Cutaneous allodynia in the migraine population</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>63</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.21211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18059010?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18059010</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raieli</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapolino</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitaleri</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Consolo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Juvenile migraine and allodynia: results of a retrospective study</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.12530</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25760465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25760465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langemark</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Olesen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pericranial tenderness in tension headache</article-title>. A blind, controlled study. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>1987</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1468-2982.1987.0704249.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3427625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3427625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tornoe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersen</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Skotte</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Skov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reduced neck-shoulder muscle strength and aerobic power together with increased pericranial tenderness are associated with tension-type headache in girls: a case-control study</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0333102413515341</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24351277?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24351277</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Keefe</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain in young adults. II: the use and perceived effectiveness of pain-coping strategies</article-title>. <source>Clin J Pain</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7787337?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7787337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipton</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical pain catastrophizing in women with migraine and obesity</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>923</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.12597</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26087348?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26087348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Radat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanraud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Scala</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dousset</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Psychological and neuropsychological correlates of dependence-related behavior in medication overuse headaches: a one year follow-up study</article-title>. <source>Headache Pain</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>59</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1129-2377-14-59</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holroyd</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Romanek</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heh</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impaired functioning and quality of life in severe migraine: the role of catastrophizing and associated symptoms</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-2982.2007.01420.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17784854?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17784854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seng</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Buse</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Klepper</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayson</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinberg</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosberg</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>psychological factors associated with chronic migraine and severe migraine-related disability: an observational study in a tertiary headache center</article-title>. <source>Headache</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/head.13021</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28139000?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28139000</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orr</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McMillan</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Disability, quality of life, and pain coping in pediatric migraine: an observational study</article-title>. <source>J Child Neurol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>717</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0883073817702025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28393667?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28393667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moayedi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Keaser</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>High frequency migraine is associated with lower acute pain sensitivity and abnormal insula activity related to migraine pain intensity, attack frequency, and pain catastrophizing</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2016.00489</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27746728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27746728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keaser</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Seminowicz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Altered brain structure and function correlate with disease severity and pain catastrophizing in migraine patients</article-title>. <source>eNeuro</source> (<year>2014</year>) 1:e20.14. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/ENEURO.0006-14.2014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25893216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25893216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esteve</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquina-Aponte</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez-Maestre</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Postoperative pain in children: association between anxiety sensitivity, pain catastrophizing, and female caregivers' responses to children's pain</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.e1. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2013.10.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24360639?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24360639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bakshi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lukombo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Belfer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishnamurti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain catastrophizing is associated with poorer health-related quality of life in pediatric patients with sickle cell disease</article-title>. <source>J Pain Res.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>947</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/JPR.S151198</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29773954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29773954</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsook</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Elman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Becerra</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Pain and analgesia: the value of salience circuits</article-title>. <source>Prog Neurobiol</source>. (<year>2013</year>) <volume>104</volume>:<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>105</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pneurobio.2013.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23499729?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23499729</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwedt</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hougaard</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brain functional connectivity in headache disorders: a narrative review of MRI investigations</article-title>. <source>Cereb Blood Flow Metab.</source> (<year>2017</year>) 1:271678X17740794. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0271678X17740794</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29154684?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29154684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gervais-Hup&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollice</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlesso</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Validity of the central sensitization inventory with measures of sensitization in people with knee osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Clin Rheumatol</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>3125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10067-018-4279-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30178171?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30178171</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bendtsen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Muscles and their role in episodic tension-type headache: implications for treatment</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>166</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>75</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ejp.748</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26147739?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26147739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkerson</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Noel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pag&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Asmundson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Factorial validity of the english-language version of the pain catastrophizing scale&#x02014;child version</article-title>. <source>J Pain</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpain.2013.06.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24012382?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24012382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Padula</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Agapejev</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Padovani</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Critical analysis of the international classification of headache disorders diagnostic criteria (ICHD I-1988) and (ICHD II-2004), for migraine in children and adolescents</article-title>. <source>Cephalalgia</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1042</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1468-2982.2005.00954.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16232155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16232155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>