<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Prim Care Community Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Prim Care Community Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JPC</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spjpc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Primary Care &#x00026; Community Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2150-1319</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2150-1327</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6873267</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31747822</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/2150132719885286</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_2150132719885286</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>What Works for Managing Chronic Pain: An Appreciative Inquiry
Qualitative Analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5301-4014</contrib-id><name><surname>Holtrop</surname><given-names>Jodi Summers</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-2150132719885286"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>Mary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>Doreen E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-2150132719885286">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Awadallah</surname><given-names>Nida S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nease</surname><given-names>Donald E.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zittleman</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Westfall</surname><given-names>John M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-2150132719885286">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-2150132719885286"><label>1</label>University of Colorado Denver School of
Medicine, Aurora, CO, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-2150132719885286"><label>2</label>Colorado State University, Fort Collins,
CO, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="corresp1-2150132719885286">Jodi Summers Holtrop, Department of Family
Medicine, School of Medicine, University of Colorado Denver, 12631 East 17th
Avenue, Aurora, CO 80045, USA. Email:
<email>jodi.holtrop@cuanschutz.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><season>Jan-Dec</season><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>2150132719885286</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications Inc unless otherwise noted.
Manuscript content on this site is licensed under Creative Commons
Licenses</copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons
Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>) which
permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work
without further permission provided the original work is attributed as
specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><bold>Background:</bold> Chronic pain is a prevalent and dynamic condition for
both patients and providers. Learning how patients with chronic pain
successfully manage their pain may prove helpful in guiding health care
providers in their treatment of other patients with chronic pain. This research
sought to identify successful strategies for managing chronic pain from
interviews with individuals experiencing chronic pain who were able to do &#x0201c;most
of what they want on most days.&#x0201d; <bold>Methods:</bold> Qualitative, descriptive
study. Patients were from metro Denver, Colorado, USA and were recruited from
community and health care settings. Appreciative inquiry (AI) was used as an
approach to elicit stories of successful pain management. We conducted
one-on-one, in person interviews using a semistructured interview guide.
Analysis was completed using a grounded hermeneutic editing approach.
<bold>Results:</bold> Twenty-four interviews were completed representing a
range of adult ages, genders, race/ethnicities, and underlying reasons for
chronic pain. Consistent themes were found in that all patients had developed
multiple strategies for ongoing pain management and prevention, as well as a
mental approach embedded with elements of positive beliefs and determination.
Friends, family, support group members, and health care providers were key in
support and ongoing management. Although 10 patients regularly used opioid pain
medications, none were dependent, and all stated an active desire to avoid these
medications. <bold>Conclusions:</bold> Successful chronic pain management seems
possible as displayed from the patient narratives but requires persistence
through individual trial and error. Recommendations for health care provider
teams are made to apply these findings to assist patients with chronic pain.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>chronic pain</kwd><kwd>primary care</kwd><kwd>qualitative research</kwd><kwd>community-based participatory research</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="award1-2150132719885286"><funding-source id="funding1-2150132719885286"><institution-wrap><institution>patient-centered outcomes research institute</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100006093</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id rid="funding1-2150132719885286">ME-1303-5843</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January-December 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="section1-2150132719885286"><title>Background</title><p>
<disp-quote><p>I think it&#x02019;s important for us to hold onto our dreams . . . to never lose
sight of who we were before we became the injured person we were and know
that there&#x02019;s always a new beginning. There&#x02019;s always hope. There&#x02019;s always
change. You can never give up. [P17]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Chronic pain is a common condition in the United States, affecting approximately 11%
of the adult population<sup><xref rid="bibr1-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> with 3% to 4% of the general population using prescribed opioids for
long-term treatment.<sup><xref rid="bibr2-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="bibr3-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>
The experience of persistent pain elicits a complex biopsychosocial phenomenon<sup><xref rid="bibr4-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> that extends well beyond the biologic sensation of pain itself.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> These biopsychosocial effects include a decreased ability to work, disability
classification, loss or increase of appetite, inability to sleep, and general
decreased quality of life.<sup><xref rid="bibr6-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Additionally, chronic pain is associated with other medical and mental health
conditions, including cardiovascular disease, depression, and anxiety.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p>Patients seeking relief from chronic pain often do so from primary care clinics. Yet,
primary care physicians report feeling conflicted about treating chronic
pain.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> On the one
hand, they want to help patients alleviate their pain, but on the other, are
encouraged to limit or avoid prescribing controlled pain medications due to practice
guidelines and regulations.<sup><xref rid="bibr11-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="bibr12-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr13-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Therefore,
many primary care clinicians (ie, physicians or advanced practice providers or
primary care physicians [PCPs]) feel underprepared to manage pain conditions without
a clear pathophysiologic mechanism<sup><xref rid="bibr14-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="bibr15-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> and find the management of
chronic pain stressful.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> As a result, patients sometimes report feeling disrespected and distrusted
when seeking care for their chronic pain.<sup><xref rid="bibr16-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup></p><p>The literature on pain management interventions in primary care reveals many studies
on improving adherence to chronic pain medication management guidelines and less on
helping patients select other pain management strategies.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="bibr18-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> While there is literature on
patient-provider concordance and effective pain management regarding opioid and
other analgesic prescribing,<sup><xref rid="bibr19-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">19</xref><xref rid="bibr20-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr21-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr22-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> demonstrating both discordance
and concordance in prescribing goals, there are few papers that describe a
comprehensive approach to pain management in primary care specific
settings.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Although multidisciplinary pain care has been systematically studied,<sup><xref rid="bibr25-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> gaps exist in primary care implementation. As well, there is an emergence of
studies describing new methods of pain management; however, there is a lack of
guidance on how to sort through these different studies and implement an effective
comprehensive approach tailored to patients.</p><p>Given the gap in clear implementation strategies in the primary care setting, we
began by investigating how patients who self-report successfully managing their
chronic pain were doing so. To gain insight from these patients, we used a process
called appreciative inquiry (AI) in a qualitative study research design. AI has been
used predominantly as an approach to help teams identify, and focus attention on,
what <italic>is</italic> working well as opposed to immediate problem solving that
gets bogged down in barriers and problems.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> AI has been used to identify solutions and to gain representation from many
voices, facilitating eventual implementation.<sup><xref rid="bibr27-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup> AI has also been used to create change within health care; however, it has
not been used to address overcoming chronic pain.<sup><xref rid="bibr28-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">28</xref><xref rid="bibr29-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr"/><xref rid="bibr30-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr"/>-<xref rid="bibr31-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup> In this study, AI is used as a
method to identify successful strategies, as reported by patients with chronic pain,
to assist primary care physicians and their care teams in chronic pain management
from a patient centered perspective.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="section2-2150132719885286"><title>Methods</title><p>Approval was obtained from the Colorado Multiple Institutional Review Board (COMIRB)
for this qualitative, descriptive study, which occurred between 2014-2017. The
research team included academic researchers, local community health research
nonprofit organization members, and the Colorado Research Network (CaReNet)
practice-based research network (PBRN) patient advisory council (PAC). The CaReNet
PAC was created in 2004 and includes 12 members selectively chosen to represent
patient perspectives from the PBRN clinics. All groups participated in every phase
of the research.</p><sec id="section3-2150132719885286"><title>Defining Successful Chronic Pain Management</title><p>As the study purpose was to utilize AI to identify successes, the key was to
first identify patients who had successful experiences to share: patients who
were able to report functional, although not necessarily pain-free, lives.
Therefore, the PAC deemed that functional status was being able to do &#x0201c;most of
what they want on most days&#x0201d; and were absent of a diagnosis of opioid use
disorder. This became the definition used to target a group of patients.
Although a physician verified the patient&#x02019;s story preinterview, objective
measurement of pain and the patient&#x02019;s successful management was not
conducted.</p></sec><sec id="section4-2150132719885286"><title>Setting and Participants</title><p>Participants were recruited from health care and community settings in the metro
Denver, Colorado area via community organization partners and PAC members using
descriptive study flyers, personal contacts, and through physicians identifying
and offering study participation to patients in 2 local family medicine clinics.
Given the recruitment methods, it is unclear how many patients were offered an
opportunity for participation. Once identified, participants were given
information about the study and a number to call for further information. After
initial contact, participants completed a brief screening with one of 2 study
physicians. The screening questions were &#x0201c;please describe your chronic pain and
what do you consider successful pain management?&#x0201d; to assess the participant&#x02019;s
pain experiences to ensure that he or she met our study-defined definition of
successful pain management. For the remainder of the paper, we will use the term
patients rather than participants for those individuals in the AI interviews as
this study was conducted to inform health care delivery.</p></sec><sec id="section5-2150132719885286"><title>Qualitative Data Collection and Analysis Team</title><p>The qualitative core team consisted of 2 female PhD-level qualitative
methodologists, a male physician, and a female master&#x02019;s degree&#x02013;prepared
qualitative research assistant. The 3 qualitatively trained personnel had
extensive experience conducting qualitative data collection and analysis and at
least 1 of the 3 was present at all interviews. The team members had no prior
relationships with the interview participants except for 3 patients who were
members of the PAC. Interviewers had no other roles than to conduct the
interview and glean perspectives on chronic pain management. The larger research
team included 2 additional male physician researchers, 2 additional research
assistants, and a community stakeholder. The PAC additionally informed the
research process through reporting and feedback sessions.</p></sec><sec id="section6-2150132719885286"><title>Instrument</title><p>A semistructured interview guide was developed with this main question stem,
&#x0201c;Please tell me about what you do to manage your chronic pain.&#x0201d; Prompts
throughout the interview were used to guide the patient back to successful
strategies. During the interview, patients shared information about the onset,
type, frequency, and duration of the chronic pain, while discussing their
experiences and strategies for successful management. A very brief written
questionnaire was given that asked about age, gender, and race/ethnicity.
Interviews occurred with one patient at a time and lasted 45 to 60 minutes.
Interviews were conducted in person by a study investigator and research
assistant in a private location selected by patients, such as their home or
public library meeting room. Patients were compensated with a gift card and no
repeat interviews occurred. Interviews were audio recorded, transcribed, and
loaded into ATLAS.ti version 6 (ATLAS.ti GmbH, Berlin, Germany), which is a
qualitative analysis software program.</p></sec><sec id="section7-2150132719885286"><title>Analysis</title><p>The qualitative process proceeded using a grounded hermeneutic editing approach.<sup><xref rid="bibr32-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></sup> First, all core team members independently read through several
transcripts to establish terms and definitions for the codes to be assigned (ie,
emergent process). This continued until codes were established and a coding
guide was developed. Then 2 team members qualitatively coded the data in
ATLAS.ti. Discrepancies were discussed and reconciled with the entire team. Once
all the data were entered, co-occurrences of codes were queried and further
examined, noting areas of overlap and the meaning of this overlap, and quotation
reports generated. The qualitative core analysis team met biweekly over 4 months
to complete the analysis after the coding was completed. Each member of the core
team independently read through the quotations reports and created
representative summary statements. The larger team then met to share their
summaries and discuss the emerging themes, relevancies, key messages, and
overall research findings.</p><p>During the examination and analysis of the seven emergent dominant treatment
codes: medications, chronic pain specific medications, physical
therapy/exercise, prayer/meditation/relaxation, self-care, alternative care, and
procedure, it became evident that patients used a variety of methods to
successfully manage their pain, based on personal life conditions and
environment. The team created a spreadsheet to record if a patient had used at
least 1 treatment method for each of the 7 treatment codes. Tallies were
computed for the total number of different treatment categories used per patient
to track frequency, significance, and identify cross-patient themes.</p><p>Given the consistency of responses by diverse interviewees, the core team
determined that saturation was reached. Confirmation of this determination
occurred through coded and thematic data sharing to both the larger research
team and the PAC, twice. This confirmation process was also completed to assure
analysis coherence and community relevance. These efforts allowed and encouraged
the core team to revisit the data, and confirm, modify, or refute initial
impressions, and identify additional areas for further analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="section8-2150132719885286"><title>Results</title><p>Twenty-four patients were interviewed. Patients varied by age, race, socioeconomic
status, and chronic pain conditions (<xref rid="table1-2150132719885286" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Patients&#x02019; definition of
successful pain management ranged from being pain-free to decreasing pain levels to
allow for participating in daily activities. Although patients varied by gender,
age, and conditions, common themes were indicated across these groups, therefore
results were analyzed together as one group.</p><table-wrap id="table3-2150132719885286" orientation="portrait" position="float"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150132719885286-table3"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall themes for successful chronic pain
management:<break/>&#x02022;&#x02003;Multiple approaches to pain
management<break/>&#x02022;&#x02003;Positive beliefs and
determination<break/>&#x02022;&#x02003;Significance of important
relationships<break/>&#x02022;&#x02003;Desire to avoid chronic pain
medications</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table1-2150132719885286" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Description of Study Patients.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150132719885286-table1"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Descriptor</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25-77; mean 58.25</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gender</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 female, 4 male</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 white, 10 African American, 3 Hispanic, 2 mixed race</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patient description of the diagnosis of painful condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Musculoskeletal: 18<break/>Inflammatory conditions (Crohn&#x02019;s
disease, ankylosing spondylitis): 3<break/>Neurologic
(headaches, painful neuropathy): 8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Perceived duration of pain, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reported experience with opioid use</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 of 24 people reported some experience with opioid use; none
had past or current opioid use disorder or were using any form
of medication-assisted treatment</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><sec id="section9-2150132719885286"><title>Key Themes</title><sec id="section10-2150132719885286"><title>Theme 1: Multiple Approaches to Pain Management</title><p>Seven pain treatment and management codes emerged to account for treatment
engagements and strategies that patients reported (<xref rid="table2-2150132719885286" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) with patients reporting
about 5 strategies being used (mean = 4.8; range 3-6) of seven used by each
patient. Therefore, a primary finding was that patients used a variety of
strategies to reduce or eliminate pain, concurrently and in various
combinations, to achieve &#x0201c;living with chronic pain successfully.&#x0201d; Patients
employed these options strategically to respond to 4 key areas: (1) the
mental/mind-set approach to their pain (theme 2), (2) pain prevention such
as a migraine sufferers avoiding pain triggers like loud, stimulating
environments, (3) ongoing management of pain such as regular visits with a
<italic>trusted</italic> health care partner to assess overall chronic
pain issues and underlying problems, and (4) dealing with acute and severe
pain episodes such as taking ibuprofen or a warm Epsom salt bath.</p><table-wrap id="table2-2150132719885286" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Treatment and Management Categories.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150132719885286-table2"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/><col align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examples</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Procedure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health care intervention to address the pain or
underlying condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corticosteroid injections, surgery, diagnostic
testing</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Activities that intended to care for the chronic pain
that the patient sought out or did themselves</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heating pads, icing, baths, nutrition/diet changes,
weight loss</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medications taken for the underlying condition</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Antidepressants or antianxiety medications, other
medications to treat the underlying condition</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic pain-specific medications</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medications specifically for the management of chronic
pain, either opioid or nonopioid. Includes 2 categories:
over the counter (OTC) and by prescription</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">OTC: ibuprofen, aspirin, acetaminophen,
marijuana<break/>Prescribed: gabapentin, fentanyl,
morphine, oxycodone, oxycontin</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alternative care</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overlaps with self-care (double coded) but considered
complementary and alternative medicine</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Massage, chiropractic, acupuncture, dietary supplements,
herbal supplements</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prayer/meditation/relaxation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overlaps with alternative care (double coded) but
activity with the goal of producing a relaxation
response and/or connection with higher power and usually
mental centering</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prayer, meditation, reading the Bible, focusing on
music, going to a dark room, breathing exercises,
visualization</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical therapy/exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Movement for purposes of decreasing or preventing
pain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Formal or informal physical therapy, exercise of any
type, stretching, yoga/Pilates</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Although patients never explicitly delineated these categories as categories
themselves, there was acknowledgment that multiple approaches within the
categories were needed for their pain management.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>This has been a life-long thing . . . I just thank God I am where I&#x02019;m
at because now . . . You know without all these tools you know. It&#x02019;s
like having a tool bag. [P2]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Patients illustrated how they become informed and engaged in their treatment
options over time and found approaches that worked for them individually.
Most took a &#x0201c;trial and error&#x0201d; approach until developing a package of
approaches that worked, as well as when and how they worked. For many, there
was a continuing evolution of modalities to try, include, and adjust. While
this individualized approach may appear self-evident or commonsense, our
experience with pain management experiences is that this personally relevant
exploration was ground-breaking and critical to patient care and patient
success.</p></sec><sec id="section11-2150132719885286"><title>Theme 2: Positive Beliefs and Determination</title><p>A persistent and reverberating theme in our data was the use of an
<italic>encouraging or affirming</italic> mental approach that supported
and described a sense of resilience, or &#x0201c;can do,&#x0201d; &#x0201c;doing what was needed,&#x0201d;
and &#x0201c;getting on with life&#x0201d; belief.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>The mind is something that&#x02019;s amazing. It can get you through almost
anything if you use the power of your mind over matter, which the
pain was the matter, and I had to concur that through my mind, took
meditation, lots of reading. [P15]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Most patients described that how they understood, felt, or experienced their
pain was critical to their successful management. Being an active agent in
their pain assessment keenly supported their care success. Uniformly,
patients reiterated that positive or affirming beliefs and determination
factored into their overall success. Their knowledge embodied a dynamic
individual understanding of the connection between mind and body as a
necessary foundation.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>Everybody&#x02019;s pain is different. Everybody&#x02019;s activities are different .
. . you know of course your support system. You know a higher power.
Acceptance within yourself, and you have to be able to accept
yourself because no one&#x02019;s ever going to understand what you&#x02019;re going
through. You know don&#x02019;t stop living your life. You have to just keep
pushing. [P16]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Several patients acknowledged that changing expectations and being realistic
with their goals, post their injury or condition, clearly influenced their
successful management. Several ways in which patients acted on these beliefs
were to trust in what they could accomplish versus what they were no longer
able to do; a heightened valuing of a relationship with religion, god or
something beyond them; and/or knowing that they could have some power over
their situation instead of chronic pain determining their life.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>Confiding in something that gives you confidence, that builds your
self-esteem whether it is the people around you, or your personal
relationship with your creator, and once you seek that and begin to
kind of nourish that then you put your faith in the unseen.
[P17]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Yet, in describing their journey with chronic pain, patients often relayed an
initial sense of frustration, sometimes even despair. Thus, our research
illustrated that these patients were more than default optimists. Many
suffered from depression and/or anxiety at some point in their lives.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>. . . so I started actually seeing a psychologist just for anxiety,
and I think that&#x02019;s another huge turning point I think just having .
. . tying everything together I guess like this stimuli things, and
then anxiety playing into it and kind of spiraling things. [P7]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Patients used many methods to achieve this mental state or mindset that
allowed or fostered encouraging lives. Most included a means of reframing
the thoughts or feelings about their pain. Distraction from the pain by
meditating, going for a short car ride, or thinking about their children or
grandchildren was common.</p><p>Significantly, patients were deliberate in their desire to define themselves
as a person, instead of their condition, while also accepting the inherent
limitations that living with chronic pain can bring. This framing also
speaks to a crucial finding that could only come through AI research; in
contrast to conditions, symptoms, diagnosis our participants viewed their
lives as whole and theirs.</p></sec><sec id="section12-2150132719885286"><title>Theme 3: The Significance of Important Relationships</title><p>Relationships with family, friends, significant others, and health care
professionals were especially important in the patients&#x02019; management of their
pain. These relationships served 3 main functions in helping to achieve
success: (1) provide instrumental support, (2) provide a sense of
inspiration and motivation, and (3) assist patients in making decisions
pertaining to their pain management at critical points. Patients named
various groups and types of people who positively influenced their pain
management: family members provided, at times, endless support, empathy, and
caring; children and grandchildren were motivators, cheerleaders, and givers
of happiness and joy; friends provided therapy suggestions or were
companions during physical therapy.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>Well for me I&#x02019;m kind of hard on myself, and I don&#x02019;t like being a
burden to my family because I know they love me and I know that they
worry about me, but you know I have to trust their love, and just
know that you know they love me, and that I&#x02019;m not a burden, and they
know that I do the best I can for myself. They know I do, and I be
honest with them. They let me vent. [P6]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Again, significantly, physicians and health care team members were described
as important individuals to the contribution of successful pain management.
While this may appear self-evident once again, the ability to counter the
presumed futility that comes with chronic pain was keenly expressed and felt
during interviews. Physicians&#x02019; importance was centered on proper diagnosis
and treatment options, while other health care team members were coaches and
additional support systems.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>He [my doctor] finally listened . . . that&#x02019;s what really made me have
acceptance of my injury, inner peace with my injury, and then start
finally trying [to] counteract it and try to fight it, because now I
feel like this guy&#x02019;s finally listening to me. He&#x02019;s trying to help me
with my injury. [P17]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>Patients stated that health care professionals were most helpful when they
listened to their concerns, worked to identify the true problem, advocated
for them, helped them find solutions, and did not label them as &#x0201c;drug
seeking.&#x0201d; Health care team members and individuals offering formal or
informal support were more likely seen as assisting patients with their
decision making and helping them to understand their pain instead of
pointing out some deficiency.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>My psychotherapist said, &#x0201c;If anything you have to learn that pain
puts you in the present. If you&#x02019;re dealing with your pain no matter
what it is . . . you&#x02019;re dealing with the present, and that is good
for you because you&#x02019;re always dealing in the past or where you want
to be in the future, but I don&#x02019;t hear you dealing with where you are
today&#x0201d;. [P22]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>The supportive role that relationships played in patients&#x02019; lives was the most
frequently applied transcript code, and often these support systems were
expressed as significant and seemingly necessary. Successful chronic pain
narratives had the patient engaged and surrounded by others and other
choices versus isolation, dependency and failure/frustration. Moreover, the
importance of these support systems was more pronounced in patients with
more debilitating pain.</p></sec><sec id="section13-2150132719885286"><title>Theme 4: Desire to Avoid Chronic Pain Medications</title><p>Some patients described debilitating pain due to severe conditions such as
fibromyalgia or increased intracranial pressure. This subgroup of patients
often relied on prescription pain medication; however, they tended to
describe this modality for pain relief as undesirable, but necessary.
Although there was expressed resistance to all types of pain medications,
opioid, or addiction-forming medications were especially noted as
undesirable. Numerous patients expressed a desire to avoid opioid
medications entirely or wanting to stop taking those they were on.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>I don&#x02019;t like a lot of chemical stuff in my body. I prefer natural
remedies . . . I have a wonderful physician, and she goes along with
the same thing. As much as you can do naturally to manage pain.
[P8]</p></disp-quote>
</p><p>While some patients were concerned about being labeled a &#x0201c;druggie,&#x0201d; the
majority of patients were not actually concerned about stigmatization
regarding opioid use. They were reluctant to take opioids because they were
concerned about their own safety. In fact, patients across the
self-described pain spectrum were outwardly avoidant of opioid medications,
stating they &#x0201c;made them feel out of it,&#x0201d; were &#x0201c;not safe to have around my
kids,&#x0201d; or that they were &#x0201c;having unwanted side effects&#x0201d; and wanted to avoid
dependence or seeming weak. There was also a resistance to opioid use
because of experienced or perceived side effects including constipation,
lethargy, or mood changes. Negative experiences with use of opioids
sometimes created either an actual or perceived adversarial relationship
between themselves and others that made them feel hurt and distressed.</p><p>Patients instead relied on nonopioid pain medications, such as ibuprofen,
when pain became more severe. Some even avoided nonopioid medication use and
turned to alternative therapies. A small number (n = 3) of patients actively
used marijuana for pain relief. Of the 24 patients we interviewed, 10 took
daily opioids. Although several of these were in an active program to step
down their medication level, none were classified as opioid use disorder or
were utilizing medication assisted treatment.</p><p>
<disp-quote><p>. . . whatever years I have left I really don&#x02019;t want to be dependent
on morphine my whole life, so I&#x02019;ve seen a doctor every month, and
each month we go down a little bit on the dosage, and I&#x02019;m hoping to
get off of it completely so I don&#x02019;t have to worry about that.
[P23]</p></disp-quote>
</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="section14-2150132719885286"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, the most striking result was that across all genders, races, ages, and
underlying conditions, self-identified successful chronic pain patients used a
variety of strategies coupled with affirming and motivating beliefs, and key close
relationships&#x02014;including health care providers&#x02014;to overcome limitations from chronic
pain. Patients greatly valued this multi-pronged, comprehensive approach and the
support of their health care team however, it required persistent, resilient trial
and error, often with the help of support from loved ones and health care
professionals.</p><p>Many qualitative studies have been conducted in the area of chronic pain and its
management; however, the majority of these studies have focused on the volume of
treatment, difficulties with health care provider communications, or difficulties
with managing pain. An extensive meta-ethnographic review by Toye et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr33-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup> chronicles the issues of living with chronic pain and the effect on
relationships with the health care clinicians.<sup><xref rid="bibr34-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup> Few have focused specifically on successful management strategies, and none
have used specifically an appreciative inquiry approach, although some are similar.
These included Owens et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr35-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup> who studied 80 people living with chronic pain with &#x0201c;positive stories to
tell&#x0201d; using semistructured interviews and standardized questionnaires. Their results
included themes of acceptance, openness, self-efficacy, hope, perseverance,
self-regulation, kinesthetic awareness, holistic approaches and integrative
therapies, self-care, spirituality, social support, and therapeutic lifestyle
behaviors. As a whole, the narratives of pain &#x0201c;exemplars&#x0201d; illustrate a &#x0201c;positive
approach model&#x0201d; for living well with pain and a multi-faceted approach. They also
found that many &#x0201c;expressed a strong desire to minimize or eliminate pain
medication.&#x0201d; Richardson et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr36-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup> describe how older adults used flexibility and pragmatism around chronic
joint paint that supports a general model of resilience that incorporates
vulnerabilities. Indeed there is a literature on resilience that should not be
overlooked.<sup><xref rid="bibr37-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="bibr38-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">38</xref></sup> McCluskey et al.<sup><xref rid="bibr39-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup> provide insights on the role of significant others, such as family members,
in supporting individuals with chronic pain. Activity, connectivity, and positivism
were themes in their data. The results from these studies are consistent with our
findings, suggesting a common set of important characteristics to be attended to in
the management of chronic pain.</p><p>These results have implications for how PCPs and their care teams approach treatment
of chronic pain. Although many PCPs and other prescribers are encouraged by the 2016
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Guideline for Prescribing Opioids for
Chronic Pain to simply avoid opioid prescribing, these patients still have pain and
need help. Our findings indicate that it may be beneficial to openly discuss pain
management desires with patients to help identify multiple strategies that work for
each individual. This approach supports patient centered care, where the patient is
at the center and the clinician and team use a holistic approach to identify
strategies that are relevant to each individual. Many patients do not want the risk
of addiction to pain medications. In addition, different patients described a &#x0201c;trial
and error&#x0201d; approach to their pain management which led to a journey that was long
and emotionally challenging and it took time to figure out the right &#x0201c;package&#x0201d; for
each patient. Patients who are left to wander about on their own to discover what
works creates a missed opportunity to get to successful management much sooner by
appropriate coaching and support. Working as a team to help patients identify a
personalized strategy is valuable. Behavioral health professionals could play a role
in encouraging positive mindfulness approaches. Patients may benefit by reassurance
that it may take a while to find the right combination to address their specific
needs. Finally, the importance of supportive relationships should be emphasized. We
found a few studies that describe similar strategies, but more is needed.<sup><xref rid="bibr23-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="bibr24-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> Perhaps the
key is an emphasis on the ongoing supportive relationship combined with strategies
&#x0201c;tried and tweaked&#x0201d; incrementally over time as outlined by Atul Gawande.<sup><xref rid="bibr40-2150132719885286" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup></p><p>This study has several limitations. First, the goal was to illuminate experiences
that add richness and meaning to our understanding of the chronic pain experience.
Therefore, patients were not expected to represent specific conditions, ages,
genders, or races. None of the patients were classified as having opioid use
disorder, at the study time or in the past, and none were using suboxone or other
treatment for medication assisted treatment. Since chronic pain is, by definition,
based on the patients&#x02019; subjective experience, we honored those interpretations and
did not verify the diagnosis or underlying cause/condition. Although many patients
were referred by a physician due to their chronic pain and a separate physician
verified the patient&#x02019;s story pre-interview, objective measurement of pain and
successful management was not conducted.</p><p>Also, the focus of our inquiry was in symptom management rather than disease control.
The strategies shared may offer useful approaches; however, we intentionally avoided
implying or suggesting these choices linearly lead to success. Instead we are
representing the voices of the people who shared their version of success, which may
have utility for others. While some patients did note a history of opioid use, we do
not know to what extent patients may have fully disclosed this information; however,
since some patients did disclose and we created a safe environment for this
information, we believe patients were being truthful. Last, although there is a
temptation to sort the data by condition, age, gender, or other characteristic, our
results indicated common themes that crossed across these patient characteristics
and were uniformly present.</p><p>In summary, this study illustrates how a group of chronic pain sufferers are
successfully managing chronic pain. Specific and varied strategies and mental
approaches seem to underlie this success. Our study supports the work of other
similar studies; yet, it provides further evidence of the need to provide
multi-modal pain management approaches in a supportive health care team
environment.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors wish to thank the participating patients, health systems, and the PAC for
their participation.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; Note:</bold> The data generated and analyzed during this study are in the form of qualitative
interview transcripts. These data are potentially available from the
corresponding author under specific conditions on reasonable request. The data
are de-identified and stored in a password secured database at the University of
Colorado.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author Contributions:</bold> All authors contributed to the writing of and approved the manuscript. JMW and
DEN developed the idea and secured funds for the study; MF, DEM, DEN, NSA, and
LZ identified and recruited participants; JSH, MF, DEM, and LZ developed the
interview guide; MF, JSH, and DEM completed interviews; JSH and MF completed the
qualitative coding; JSH, MF, MS, and DEM completed the qualitative analysis and
DEN, JMW, and LZ provided larger research team review and oversight.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Declaration of Conflicting Interests:</bold> The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support for the
research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: This study was funded
by the Patient Centered Outcomes Research Institute Grant Number
ME-1303-5843.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics Approval:</bold> Institutional review board approval for this study was sought and obtained from
the Colorado Multiple Institutional Review Board (COMIRB). All participants
consented to participate using an IRB-approved consent form.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>ORCID iD:</bold> Jodi Summers Holtrop <inline-graphic xlink:href="10.1177_2150132719885286-img1.jpg"/>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5301-4014">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5301-4014</ext-link></p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-2150132719885286"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haegerich</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>CDC guideline for prescribing opioids for chronic pain&#x02014;United
States, 2016</article-title>. <source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>49</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-2150132719885286"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boudreau</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Korff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rutter</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Trends in long-term opioid
therapy for chronic non-cancer pain</article-title>.
<source>Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1166</fpage>-<lpage>1175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19718704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-2150132719885286"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daubresse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Ambulatory diagnosis and
treatment of nonmalignant pain in the United States,
2000-2010</article-title>. <source>Med Care</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>870</fpage>-<lpage>878</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24025657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-2150132719885286"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The need for a new medical model: a challenge for
biomedicine</article-title>. <source>Science</source>.
<year>1977</year>;<volume>196</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">847460</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-2150132719885286"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="gov">
<collab>Interagency Pain Research Coordinating Committee</collab>.
<article-title>Nationa Pain Strategy: A Comprehensive Population
Health-Level Strategy for Pain</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.iprcc.nih.gov/sites/default/files/HHSNational_Pain_Strategy_508C.pdf">https://www.iprcc.nih.gov/sites/default/files/HHSNational_Pain_Strategy_508C.pdf</ext-link>.
<comment>Accessed July 29, 2016</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-2150132719885286"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wexler</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>McDougle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Miser</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddox</surname><given-names>JD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voices that may not otherwise be heard: a qualitative exploration
into the perspectives of primary care patients living with chronic
pain</article-title>. <source>J Pain Res</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>291</fpage>-<lpage>299</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24940079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-2150132719885286"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Chronic pain has major long-term consequences</collab>. <source>Healthc
Demand Dis Manag</source>.
<year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10724577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-2150132719885286"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>PG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Long-term consequences of chronic pain: mounting evidence for
pain as a neurological disease and parallels with other chronic disease
states</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>996</fpage>-<lpage>1004</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21752179</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-2150132719885286"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthews</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>EL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Beliefs and attitudes about opioid prescribing and chronic pain
management: survey of primary care providers</article-title>. <source>J
Opioid Manag</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>-<lpage>382</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25531955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-2150132719885286"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tighe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rife</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Managing chronic pain in primary care: it really does take a
village</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>931</fpage>-<lpage>934</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28337689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-2150132719885286"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esquibel</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Borkan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Doctors and patients in pain: conflict and collaboration in
opioid prescription in primary care</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>155</volume>:<fpage>2575</fpage>-<lpage>2582</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25261714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-2150132719885286"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfert</surname><given-names>MZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilson</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahl</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>JF.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Opioid analgesics for pain control: Wisconsin physicians&#x02019;
knowledge, beliefs, attitudes, and prescribing practices</article-title>.
<source>Pain Med</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>425</fpage>-<lpage>434</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20002590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-2150132719885286"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Parpart</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyland</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The patient-provider
relationship in chronic pain care: providers&#x02019; perspectives</article-title>.
<source>Pain Med</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1688</fpage>-<lpage>1697</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21044259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-2150132719885286"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffing</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>EE.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contrasting tensions between patients and PCPs in chronic pain
management: a qualitative study</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1689</fpage>-<lpage>1697</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23870100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-2150132719885286"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponte</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson-Tribino</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Attitudes and knowledge about pain: an assessment of West
Virginia family physicians</article-title>. <source>Fam Med</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>37</volume>:<fpage>477</fpage>-<lpage>480</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15988631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-2150132719885286"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upshur</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacigalupe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Luckmann</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>&#x0201c;They don&#x02019;t want anything to do with you:&#x0201d; patient views of
primary care management of chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Pain
Med</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1791</fpage>-<lpage>1798</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-2150132719885286"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dorflinger</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A partnered approach to
opioid management, guideline concordant care and the stepped care model of
pain management</article-title>. <source>J Gen Intern Med</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>suppl
4</issue>):<fpage>870</fpage>-<lpage>876</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-2150132719885286"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RR.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Integrating pain management in clinical practice</article-title>.
<source>J Clin Psychol Med Settings</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>-<lpage>64</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22383018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-2150132719885286"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frantsve</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerns</surname><given-names>RD.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Patient-provider interactions in the management of chronic pain:
current findings within the context of shared medical decision
making</article-title>. <source>Pain Med</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>-<lpage>35</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17244101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-2150132719885286"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Korthuis</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A mixed methods study of
patient-provider communication about opioid analgesics</article-title>.
<source>Patient Educ Couns</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>453</fpage>-<lpage>461</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25601279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-2150132719885286"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffing</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bair</surname><given-names>MJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Communicating about opioids for chronic pain: a qualitative study
of patient attributions and the influence of the patient-physician
relationship</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>835</fpage>-<lpage>843</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24921073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-2150132719885286"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffing</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bair</surname><given-names>MJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>&#x0201c;I&#x02019;m not abusing or anything:&#x0201d; patient-physician communication
about opioid treatment in chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Patient Educ
Couns</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>197</fpage>-<lpage>202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23916677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-2150132719885286"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lasser</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Shanahan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A multicomponent
intervention to improve primary care provider adherence to chronic opioid
therapy guidelines and reduce opioid misuse: a cluster randomized controlled
trial protocol</article-title>. <source>J Subst Abuse Treat</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26256769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-2150132719885286"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobscha</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Corson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrin</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Collaborative care for
chronic pain in primary care: a cluster randomized trial</article-title>.
<source>JAMA</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>301</volume>:<fpage>1242</fpage>-<lpage>1252</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19318652</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-2150132719885286"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamper</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Apeldoorn</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiarotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Multidisciplinary
biopsychosocial rehabilitation for chronic low back pain: Cochrane
systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>350</volume>:<fpage>h444</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25694111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-2150132719885286"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>SA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>The Thin Book of Appreciative Inquiry</source>. <edition>3rd
ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Bend, OR</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thin
Book</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-2150132719885286"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Working in interesting times: employee morale and business
success in the information age</article-title>. <source>Vital Speeches of
the Day</source>. <year>1996</year>;XLII(15).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-2150132719885286"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleich</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hessler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appreciative inquiry and implementation science in leadership
development</article-title>. <source>J Contin Educ Nurs</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>-<lpage>209</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27124073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-2150132719885286"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigulis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Maben</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Making a difference for children and families: an appreciative
inquiry of health visitor values and why they start and stay in
post</article-title>. <source>Health Soc Care Community</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>-<lpage>348</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26584790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-2150132719885286"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appreciative inquiry as an intervention to change nursing
practice in in-patient settings: an integrative review</article-title>.
<source>Int J Nurs Stud</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>60</volume>:<fpage>179</fpage>-<lpage>190</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27297379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-2150132719885286"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Appreciative inquiry: an alternative to behaviour
management</article-title>. <source>Dementia (London)</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>-<lpage>253</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26920347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-2150132719885286"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Addison</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A grounded hermeneutic editing
approach</article-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Crabtree</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Doing Qualitative Research</source>. <edition>2nd
ed.</edition>
<publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks, CA</publisher-loc>:
<publisher-name>Sage</publisher-name>;
<volume>1999</volume>:<fpage>145</fpage>-<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-2150132719885286"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toye</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Seers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannink</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A mega-ethnography of eleven qualitative evidence syntheses
exploring the experience of living with chronic non-malignant
pain</article-title>. <source>BMC Med Res Methodol</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>116</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28764666</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-2150132719885286"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Older peoples&#x02019; strategies for coping with chronic non-malignant
pain: a qualitative meta-synthesis</article-title>. <source>Int J Nurs
Stud</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>-<lpage>50</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28073051</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35-2150132719885286"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Menard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Plews-Ogan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Calhoun</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardelt</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Stories of growth and wisdom: a mixed-methods study of people
living well with pain</article-title>. <source>Glob Adv Health Med</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>-<lpage>28</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26937311</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36-2150132719885286"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Grime</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ong</surname><given-names>BN.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>&#x0201c;Keeping going&#x0201d;: chronic joint pain in older people who describe
their health as good</article-title>. <source>Ageing Soc</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1380</fpage>-<lpage>1396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25067864</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37-2150132719885286"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goubert</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trompetter</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Towards a science and practice of resilience in the face of
pain</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pain</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1301</fpage>-<lpage>1315</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28573783</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38-2150132719885286"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#x000e1;fr&#x000e1;di</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostova</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>PJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The doctor-patient relationship and patient resilience in chronic
pain: a qualitative approach to patients&#x02019; perspectives</article-title>.
<source>Chronic Illn</source>.
<year>2018</year>;<volume>14</volume>:<fpage>256</fpage>-<lpage>270</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29096534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39-2150132719885286"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCluskey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Reneman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>&#x0201c;I think positivity breeds positivity&#x0201d;: a qualitative exploration
of the role of family members in supporting those with chronic
musculoskeletal pain to stay at work</article-title>. <source>BMC Fam
Pract</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26198218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40-2150132719885286"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gawande</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The heroism of incremental care</article-title>.
<source>The New Yorker</source>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/01/23/the-heroism-of-incremental-care">https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2017/01/23/the-heroism-of-incremental-care</ext-link>.
Published January 15, 2017. <comment>Accessed October 12,
2019</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>